<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The three books of Publius Ovidius Naso, De arte amandi translated, with historical, poetical, and topographical annotations by Francis Wolferston ...</title>
            <title>Ars amatoria. English</title>
            <author>Ovid, 43 B.C.-17 or 18 A.D.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 212 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 61 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53639</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing O693</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R841</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12367980</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12367980</idno>
            <idno type="VID">60466</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53639)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 60466)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 219:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The three books of Publius Ovidius Naso, De arte amandi translated, with historical, poetical, and topographical annotations by Francis Wolferston ...</title>
                  <title>Ars amatoria. English</title>
                  <author>Ovid, 43 B.C.-17 or 18 A.D.</author>
                  <author>Wolferston, Francis.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[9], 112 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Joseph Cranford ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of: Ars amatoria.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:60466:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60466:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60466:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60466:2"/>
            <p>THE THREE BOOKS OF Publius Ovidius Naſo, DE Arte Amandi. Tranſlated, with Hiſtorical, Poetical, and Topographical Annotations.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Francis Wolferſton,</hi> of the Inner-Temple, Gent.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Et prodeſſe volet, &amp; delectare.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Joſeph Cranford,</hi> at the <hi>Caſtle</hi> and <hi>Lion</hi> in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1661.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:60466:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60466:3"/>
            <head>TO THE Valiant and truly Noble Major-General <hi>Randolphus Egerton,</hi> Lieutenant to His Majeſties Life-guard.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ad my Endeavours born a Symmetry to my deſires, this which caſts it ſelf at your feet, had been worth your eye; but ſuch is my miſ-fortune, that what I deſigned to be reſponſible for the intereſt of that ſervice I am bound to pay you, being priviledged with your protection, renders mee much more a debtor to you, and <hi>Meanders</hi> mee into ſuch a labyrinth of Obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that they only leave mee capable to evince to the world how great my gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude would appear, were your merit
<pb facs="tcp:60466:4"/>leſs. (Generous Sir) having afforded mee your protection, I ſhall boaſt a fame next to that of your Loyalty, which is ſo well known, and in the moſt dangerous attempts hath been proportioned with a courage no leſs true than the oppugners deſigns were traiterous. Your Soveraign hath ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged, and your Country oweth you for actions beyond the ampleſt Characters of Art to expreſs. Take this (Sir) as the preface to that reſpect I owe you, and grace the front of my labours with your acceptance, an honour that tranſcends my deſert, and ſhall ever be acknowledged Superlative by</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sir,</salute> 
               <signed>Your obedient ſervant, <hi>FR. WOLFERSTON.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:60466:4"/>
            <head>TO The Entertaining Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving lately fabricated ſome Poems o, my own, I feared it might argue too great a preſumption for mee, altogether a ſtranger to the Proſs, at firſt to publiſh things that had never ſwallowed the pills of cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; which timidity, (generous Reader) was the firſt Motive to this Tranſlation, and induced me to preſent you with a <hi>Roman</hi> Muſe, yet habited i. an Engliſh dreſs, which, if (out of your accuſtome<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> civility to ſtrangers) you ſhall pleaſe to grace with a candid reception, I ſhall labour to gratifie with an Engliſh <hi>Thalia:</hi> And though it is as far from my expectation, as ambition to pleaſe all (for I know there are ſuch as would reject <hi>Apollo</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, ſhould bee happen into their prophane hands; whoſe Elogies and detractions are, in the opinion of judicious perſons, equally prejudicial to any that merit an <hi>Iô Paean</hi>) yet I hope to meet with ſome both learned and ingenuous, that will at leaſt allow my pains in a ſuccinct Tranſtation; which (to eſcape the Charybdis of over curious and critical cenſures) I have rendred throughout l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne for line.
<pb facs="tcp:60466:5"/>If I have any where mistaken the Author, I doubt not but you will favourably acquit or correct it, when you ſhall know I have had nothing more, to inſtruct mee in his meaning, than his own words: Notwithſtanding which, I hope you will finde I have forced no conſtruction diſ-intelligible to the Latine. And although this Poem of <hi>Ovids</hi> is by ſome (miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking it for his <hi>Amorum</hi>) accuſed of too much levity and wantonneſs, I have engliſhed it in ſo modeſt a ſenſe, that (if their judgement bee reſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to my expectation) it will bee inoffenſive to the chaſteſt ear. For the Annotations, they are ſuch as I thought convenient, for the amplifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Readers intelligence, to introduce to each book, which to ſome perhaps may ſeem too large, to others not large enough; either of which I might have humoured, but that I was confident the inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious would be better ſatisfied with mediocrity, to whoſe auſpicious and favourable cenſures, theſe firſt indeavours are humbly preſented by</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>FRANCIS WOLFERSTON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="book">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:60466:5"/>
            <head>The firſt Book of <hi>Publius Ovidius Naſo De Arte Amandi:</hi>
            </head>
            <argument>
               <lg>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ovid </hi>ſhews where you may choice Beauties ſee,</l>
                  <l>The Theatre and Forum's places be</l>
                  <l>Well ſtor'd with all ſorts: how you may begin</l>
                  <l>To entertain them with diſcourſe, and win</l>
                  <l>Your ſelf acquaintance: in the ſtories, hee,</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Byblis, Myrrha,</hi> and <hi>Paſiphaë,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Unlawful luſt condemns; next a way ſhows</l>
                  <l>To gain acceſs: doth confidence impoſe.</l>
                  <l>Fine Courtſhip teacheth men, and in the end</l>
                  <l>Forbids to truſt a Miſtreſs with a friend.</l>
               </lg>
            </argument>
            <lg>
               <l>IF any here bee ignorant in Love,</l>
               <l>Let him read theſe, hee ſhall a Lover prove.</l>
               <l>Swift Ships with flying Sails by Art are led,</l>
               <l>Chariots by Art, by Art Love's governed.</l>
               <l>Well could [1] <hi>Automedon</hi> in Chariots ride,</l>
               <l>And [2] <hi>Typhis</hi> the AEmonian ſhip did guide;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Venus</hi> hath mee her Deputy proclaim'd:</l>
               <l>Love's <hi>Typhis</hi> and <hi>Automedon</hi> I'm nam'd.</l>
               <l>Love raging is, hee oft repugneth mee,</l>
               <l>But hee's a Boy, and muſt directed bee.</l>
               <l>(3) <hi>Phillyrides</hi> to harp <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hille<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> taught,</l>
               <l>And furious minds by Art to mildneſs brought.</l>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:60466:6"/>
               <l>Both friends and ſoes hee terrifi'd, 'tis ſaid,</l>
               <l>That the full-yeard-old-man was much afraid.</l>
               <l>Thoſe hands muſt <hi>Hector</hi> feel, which cenſur'd fit</l>
               <l>By's Maſter, bee doth to the Rod ſubmit.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Chiron, Achiller,</hi> I love's Maſter am,</l>
               <l>Both cruel Boyes, both from a (4) Goddeſs came.</l>
               <l>But necks o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eers with Plows ſtill loaded are,</l>
               <l>And in their mouths fierce horſes bridles wear.</l>
               <l>So I can love incline, my heart though hee</l>
               <l>Wound with his bow, and dart his flames at mee;</l>
               <l>Though Love torment, on mee impreſſion make</l>
               <l>In this a nobler Revenge I'le take.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Phoebus,</hi> I feign not Arts inſpit'd by thee,</l>
               <l>Nor that the Aiery Bird premoniſht mee.</l>
               <l>(5) <hi>Clio</hi> nor <hi>Clio's</hi> Siſters have I ſeen</l>
               <l>A keeping Sheep on the <hi>Aſcrean</hi> (6) Green.</l>
               <l>Uſe cauſeth this, to a skill'd Poet bow,</l>
               <l>Truths ſing I: Love grace my beginnings now.</l>
               <l>Be gone yee (7) <hi>Vittae</hi> badge of modeſty,</l>
               <l>And borders which down to the feet do lye.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Venus</hi> ſecure, and granted pleaſures wee</l>
               <l>Sing: in my verſes there no fault ſhall be.</l>
               <l>Thou who a Souldier in this war wouldſt prove,</l>
               <l>Muſt labour firſt to finde out whom to love,</l>
               <l>And next of all the pleaſing Girle to gain,</l>
               <l>Laſt, that her love may 2 long time remain.</l>
               <l>This way, this manner, to our courſe aſſign,</l>
               <l>Nor muſt our Chariot-wheel this Goal decline.</l>
               <l>With out-caſt lures, go ſtill about, chuſe one,</l>
               <l>To whom ſay thus, Thou pleaſeſt mee alone.</l>
               <l>Heaven will not drop one down, then look about</l>
               <l>Until you finde a pleaſing Beauty out.</l>
               <l>The Hunts-man knows well where his toils to lay,</l>
               <l>And in what dale the foaming Boar doth ſtay.</l>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:60466:6"/>
               <l>Fruit-trees the Fowler knows, Fiſhers can chuſe</l>
               <l>The place, to ſwim where ſhoals of fiſhes uſe.</l>
               <l>So you that would a Lover bee, inquire</l>
               <l>To what place moſt your Miſtreſs doth retire.</l>
               <l>To finde her out, I'le not command that thou</l>
               <l>Shouldſt travel far, nor the vaſt Ocean plow.</l>
               <l>(8) <hi>Perſeus</hi> (8) <hi>Andromade</hi> from (9) <hi>India</hi> brought.</l>
               <l>A Girle in <hi>Grecia, Trojan Paris</hi> ſought.</l>
               <l>So many beauties (10) <hi>Rome</hi> affords to thee,</l>
               <l>That in the world there can none greater bee.</l>
               <l>As Corn on (11) <hi>Ida,</hi> Grapes in (12) <hi>Lesbos</hi> found,</l>
               <l>As Sea's with Fiſh, as Trees with Birds abound;</l>
               <l>As Heaven of Stars, of Maids ſo full is <hi>Rome,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Venus</hi> appears i'th' City of her (13) Son.</l>
               <l>If that a tender growing age you prize,</l>
               <l>Unſtained Virgins are before your eyes.</l>
               <l>If one mature you ſeek, here thouſands are,</l>
               <l>You cannot chuſe one, than the reſt, more fair.</l>
               <l>If a grave Matron do delight you much,</l>
               <l>Here uſeth oft to bee a band of ſuch.</l>
               <l>You may but gently walk in <hi>Pompes</hi> Grove.</l>
               <l>When <hi>Sol</hi> doth on the back of (14) <hi>Lee</hi> move.</l>
               <l>Or, where the Mother did t' her Sons gifts add</l>
               <l>A coſtly work, th' outſide with Marble clad.</l>
               <l>You muſt not paſs by (15) <hi>Livies</hi> Porch, where are</l>
               <l>Old Stories, which their Authors name do bear.</l>
               <l>Where (16) <hi>Belides</hi> their Husbands have not ſpar'd,</l>
               <l>But barb'rouſly ſlaughters for them prepar'd.</l>
               <l>Bewail'd (17) <hi>Adonis,</hi> paſs not by, nor that</l>
               <l>Which is to th' man of <hi>Juda</hi> conſecrate.</l>
               <l>Unto the Temple of <hi>Nile's</hi> (18) heifer go,</l>
               <l>Shee many makes, 'cauſe ſhee to <hi>Jove</hi> was ſo.</l>
               <l>Who'd think (19) the <hi>Forum's</hi> ſhould cauſe love, yet there</l>
               <l>The flames of <hi>Venus</hi> many times appear.</l>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:60466:7"/>
               <l>Where (20) <hi>Appias</hi> plac'd in <hi>Venus</hi> Marble fane,</l>
               <l>Yeelds a ſoft ſound, waters powr'd down again.</l>
               <l>Oft hee that love conſults here, love affects,</l>
               <l>Whilſt others he cares for, himſelf neglects.</l>
               <l>Oft in this place the Eloquent are mute,</l>
               <l>New things fall out, they muſt plead their own ſute.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Venus</hi> laughs at that man, who coming too</l>
               <l>Plead for another, for himſelf muſt wooe.</l>
               <l>Chiefly the (21) curved Theatres frequent,</l>
               <l>Choice beauty's hither come, will you content,</l>
               <l>Here you ſhall finde what's lovely, what you could</l>
               <l>Sport gladly with, if touch, for ever hold.</l>
               <l>As buſie Ants in Troops march to and fro,</l>
               <l>And mouths full-ſtor'd with wonted food do go.</l>
               <l>Or as the Bee through groves to paſtures hies,</l>
               <l>There from one flower to another flies.</l>
               <l>So thick the Ladies to the Stage repair,</l>
               <l>Oſt I have wondred at their numbers fair;</l>
               <l>Hither they come to ſee, and to bee ſeen,</l>
               <l>Here modeſty hath oft neglected been.</l>
               <l>Such playes thou (22) <hi>Romnius</hi> deviſedſt, when</l>
               <l>The <hi>Sabine</hi> women pleaſ'd thy widowed men.</l>
               <l>O're th Marble Theatre, then no ſale did wave,</l>
               <l>Nor could the Tragick Stage red colours have.</l>
               <l>Green leaves, the trees excreſcents, then were thrown</l>
               <l>About the Stage, Artleſs the Scene was known;</l>
               <l>On gradual ſeats of ſods and turfs, made fit</l>
               <l>With leavie boughs, then did the people ſit;</l>
               <l>Each man ſits round, and doth his Miſtreſs ſee,</l>
               <l>And in their ſtill breaſts many motions bee.</l>
               <l>Whilſt <hi>Thuſcus</hi> rudely pipes upon his flute,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lydius</hi> ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mps three times on the ground with's foot:</l>
               <l>I th' midſt of all their ſport (which Art did want)</l>
               <l>The King as wiſht ſigns to his men did grant.</l>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:60466:7"/>
               <l>Shouts ſhew their joy, each man leaps from his place,</l>
               <l>And doth in's eager arms a Maid imbrace.</l>
               <l>As fearful Doves do from the Eagle flye,</l>
               <l>Or tender Lambs, when they a Wolf eſpye;</l>
               <l>So the poor Maids afraid o'th' Souldiers fled,</l>
               <l>A total paleneſs all their checks o're-ſpread;</l>
               <l>One fear had all of them, but not one face,</l>
               <l>Theſe tear their hair, and thoſe ſwound in the place;</l>
               <l>Theſe ſilent grieve, thoſe mother call in vain,</l>
               <l>This mourns, that's 'maz'd, this runs, that doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main,</l>
               <l>Thus were the ſhame-fac'd Maids raviſht and led</l>
               <l>A genial prey unto each <hi>Romans</hi> bed.</l>
               <l>If one refuſ'd, her ſervant did imbrace,</l>
               <l>And her ſtraight on his wanton knees would place,</l>
               <l>Then ſay, Why weeps my Dear? I'le be no other</l>
               <l>To thee, than was thy Father to thy Mother.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Romulus</hi> to pay thy men, well didſt thou know,</l>
               <l>So pay mee, and I'le be thy Souldier too.</l>
               <l>From that firſt time the Stage hath yearly bin</l>
               <l>A place for to entrap the faireſt in.</l>
               <l>Th' <hi>Capacious</hi> (23) <hi>Circus,</hi> of a large extent,</l>
               <l>Where right-bred horſes run, you muſt frequent;</l>
               <l>Point not at all with fingers any way,</l>
               <l>Nor with a nodd do you your thoughts betray.</l>
               <l>Accoſt your Miſtreſs, whilſt by none deny'd,</l>
               <l>And gently joyn your ſelf unto her ſide;</l>
               <l>If ſhee refuſe that you ſhould ſit ſo neer,</l>
               <l>The cuſtome of the place allows it there;</l>
               <l>Here you muſt ask (for 'tis the readieſt way</l>
               <l>To gain diſcourſe) things in the preſent play:</l>
               <l>Whoſe horſe is this comes up, and then muſt you</l>
               <l>Whatever ſhee commends, commend it too.</l>
               <l>Or when a ſtately ſhew th' contenders raiſe,</l>
               <l>As you ſee her, ſo you muſt <hi>Venus</hi> praiſe.</l>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:60466:8"/>
               <l>Or if the duſt raiſ'd high fall on her then</l>
               <l>You with your hand muſt bruſh it off agen.</l>
               <l>If none light on her, yet bruſh off that none,</l>
               <l>Action in ſuch a caſe becometh one.</l>
               <l>If her looſe Mantle fall unto the ground,</l>
               <l>To take't up, you muſt bee officious found:</l>
               <l>Whilſt you ſtoop low, obſerve with nimble eye,</l>
               <l>If that you can a dainty legge eſpye.</l>
               <l>Take care leſt they that ſit behinde her puſh,</l>
               <l>Or with their kuees her tender back ſhould cruſh.</l>
               <l>'T is profitable ſleight things pleaſe her oft,</l>
               <l>As with your hand to make her cuſhion ſoft.</l>
               <l>Some, fanning cool air, do their Miſtreſs move,</l>
               <l>Or with a foot eaſ'd give a birth to love.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Circus</hi> yeelds ſuch opportunities,</l>
               <l>Or th' Sand which all about the <hi>Forum</hi> flyes.</l>
               <l>Oſt amorous youths, that on th' (24) <hi>Arena</hi> fought,</l>
               <l>Beholding others wounds, worſe wounds have caught.</l>
               <l>Or whilſt they look for, and a book require,</l>
               <l>And t' have the Victors prize put down deſire,</l>
               <l>Wounded cry out, feeling loves cruel dart,</l>
               <l>And ere they do begin, are ſtruck to th' heart.</l>
               <l>When <hi>Caeſar</hi> from a naval fight did come,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Perſian</hi> and <hi>Athenian</hi> ſhips brought home,</l>
               <l>How many foreiners did then appear?</l>
               <l>A world of people in the City were.</l>
               <l>Who at that time could not a Miſtreſs gain,</l>
               <l>How many did on forein Loves complain?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Caeſar</hi> for's conquered Nations doth prepare,</l>
               <l>And ours the (25) utmoſt bounds o'th' Orient are.</l>
               <l>(26) <hi>Craſſus</hi> rejoyce, <hi>Parthians</hi> our ſpoils return,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Romane</hi> Enſigns by the Barbarous born.</l>
               <l>W'have one though young t'revenge us hath attain'd</l>
               <l>And conqueſts, by ſuch years not got, hath gain'd.</l>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:60466:8"/>
               <l>To count the birth-day of the Gods forbear,</l>
               <l>Before that day the <hi>Caeſars</hi> valiant were.</l>
               <l>Wiſdome Divine his youthful years adorn,</l>
               <l>And he to loſe through Idleneſs doth ſcorn.</l>
               <l>(27) <hi>Tyrinthius</hi> did, when he was but a Boy,</l>
               <l>Worthy ſo great a birth, two Snakes deſtroy.</l>
               <l>Now young man (ſuch thou <hi>Bacchus</hi> didſt appear,</l>
               <l>When conquer'd <hi>India</hi> did thy (28) <hi>Thyrſis</hi> fear)</l>
               <l>Thou at thy Fathers years his arms ſhall wear,</l>
               <l>And every where his proſperous <hi>Trophies</hi> bear.</l>
               <l>Let thy great narne thus much declare to thee,</l>
               <l>Th'art chief of th' young men, and of th' old ſhalt be.</l>
               <l>The young thy Brothers are, revenge their cauſe</l>
               <l>The old thy Fathers be, protect their Laws.</l>
               <l>Thy (29) Countries Fathers arms for thee prepare:</l>
               <l>The foe thy Fathers Kingdomes peece-meale teare;</l>
               <l>Thou pious arms doſt bear, ſo doth not hee,</l>
               <l>Juſtice and Vertue will thy Enſigns be.</l>
               <l>May 'ſt thou in arms the <hi>Parthians</hi> overcome,</l>
               <l>And add <hi>Eöan</hi> wealth to <hi>Latium.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Caeſar</hi> and <hi>Mars</hi> ſmile both when hee doth go;</l>
               <l>Each of you is a God, and ſhall bee ſo.</l>
               <l>I propheſie you'l vanquiſh, and will raiſe</l>
               <l>In lofty verſes a deſerving praiſe.</l>
               <l>Thou with my words thy troops ſhalt animate,</l>
               <l>Let not thy memory theſe diſſipate.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Roman</hi> purſuits, and <hi>Parthian</hi> flights I'le ſing,</l>
               <l>How th'enemies their ſhafts do backward (30) fling.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Parthian</hi> flying, doth his foe aſſayle,</l>
               <l>And with an Omen ſo malign prevail.</l>
               <l>The time ſhall come when thou a Victor known,</l>
               <l>Brave man ſhalt be by four white horſes drawn.</l>
               <l>Before thee Chieftains going, with Gives ſo chain'd,</l>
               <l>That liberty by wonted flight's not gain'd.</l>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:60466:9"/>
               <l>Young Men and Maids will come for to behold,</l>
               <l>And that day many will their minds unfold.</l>
               <l>Then if your Miſtreſs ask a Princes name,</l>
               <l>Or what in's Country is of chiefeſt fame,</l>
               <l>All things declare, yea though ſhee ask of none:</l>
               <l>And talk of things unheard of, as if known.</l>
               <l>(31) <hi>Euphrates</hi> this with Reeds edg'd on each ſide,</l>
               <l>That (31) <hi>Tygris</hi> which with blewiſh ſtreams doth glide</l>
               <l>Call theſe <hi>Armenians,</hi> thoſe of <hi>Perſia:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Say 'tis a City in <hi>Achaemenia;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Theſe were Commanders, them by right names call</l>
               <l>If that you can, if not, feign names for all:</l>
               <l>Banquets preparativcs are, and Tables ſpread,</l>
               <l>But ſomething beſides Wine is to be had.</l>
               <l>Oft <hi>Bacchus</hi> Grapes of all thoſe ſweets the beſt,</l>
               <l>Hath Purple <hi>Cupid</hi> in his ſoft hands preſt,</l>
               <l>Until with Wine his ſpreading wings made wet,</l>
               <l>Hee ſits him down, and ſleeps where hee is ſet.</l>
               <l>Anon the wet from's dabled wings doth ſhake,</l>
               <l>But cannot love from's heart ſo eaſily take.</l>
               <l>Wine doth prepare and heat, our griefs allay,</l>
               <l>Cares in full cups of wine are waſht away;</l>
               <l>It laughter brings, and doth the poor man cheer,</l>
               <l>Sorrow expels, and clouded looks doth clear.</l>
               <l>It oft-times doth our private thoughts declare,</l>
               <l>And by its means with Arts wee furniſht are,</l>
               <l>Oft-times young men with Love it doth inſpire,</l>
               <l>Love joyn'd with Wine, is putting fire to fire.</l>
               <l>Chuſe not in Wine, neither when it is night,</l>
               <l>That injureth your judgement, this your ſight.</l>
               <l>(32) <hi>Paris</hi> the Goddeſſes i'th' day did ſee</l>
               <l>When <hi>Venus</hi> hee the faireſt judg'd to be.</l>
               <l>Night imperfection hides, no faults doth ſhow;</l>
               <l>Makes them that are not fair, ſeem to bee ſo.</l>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:60466:9"/>
               <l>Rich Gemms and Purple in the day peruſe,</l>
               <l>By th' light of th' Sun a good complexion chuſe.</l>
               <l>Why ſhould I mention thoſe that with intent</l>
               <l>To hunt, in numbers do the woods ſrequent?</l>
               <l>Why any thing of ſhoars ſhould I relate,</l>
               <l>Or baths which do ſulphurious ſmoaks create?</l>
               <l>Where ſome being wounded to the heart thus ſpeak,</l>
               <l>This water's not ſo good as ſome would make,</l>
               <l>Loe in the Suburbs <hi>Delia's</hi> Temple ſtands,</l>
               <l>And Kingdomes won by ſword-ſupporting bands.</l>
               <l>'Cauſe ſhee's a Maid, and ſcorns at <hi>Cupids</hi> bow,</l>
               <l>Hee will his ſhafts amongſt her creatures throw.</l>
               <l>The ſeveral places where choice beauties be,</l>
               <l>Hereto hath my <hi>Thalia</hi> ſung to thee.</l>
               <l>That fair one, which thou moſt doſt fancy, now</l>
               <l>T' obtain (the top of Art) I'ſe teach thee how.</l>
               <l>Whoere you bee, your eaſie minds incline,</l>
               <l>And every one obſerve my diſcipline.</l>
               <l>Aſſume a courage firſt, think any may</l>
               <l>Be won, and fearleſs your devices lay.</l>
               <l>Firſt Birds and Locuſts ſhall to ſing forbear,</l>
               <l>And the (33) <hi>Menalian</hi> Hound run from the Hare,</l>
               <l>E're Virgins courted will young men deny,</l>
               <l>The moſt unwilling yeeld moſt willingly.</l>
               <l>Stoln pleaſure's grateful to a young mans fire,</l>
               <l>Ladies as much do privately deſire.</l>
               <l>'Tis fit a Love-ſick Maid her mind ſhould ſhow,</l>
               <l>Leſt hee ſhee loves ſhould to another go.</l>
               <l>Heifers do low after a Bull i'th' Mead,</l>
               <l>After ſton'd-horſes too young Mares have ney'd.</l>
               <l>But luſt's repreſt in us, it rageth not,</l>
               <l>Wee lawful bounds unto our flames allot.</l>
               <l>Of (34) <hi>Byblis,</hi> who inceſtuous love did make,</l>
               <l>And therefore hang'd her ſelf, why ſhould I ſpeak?</l>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:60466:10"/>
               <l>Or (35) <hi>Myrrha</hi> who did for her Father burn,</l>
               <l>How into bark her tender skin did turn?</l>
               <l>Her tears do us perfume, which odours are,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Myrrah's</hi> name thoſe prccious drops ſtill bear.</l>
               <l>On <hi>Ida's</hi> leavie plains under the ſhade,</l>
               <l>A Bull the glory of the herd was laid.</l>
               <l>A hide as white as milk, this beaſt adorns,</l>
               <l>Except a black ſpot juſt betwixt his horns</l>
               <l>(36) <hi>Gnoſſos</hi> and <hi>Cydon</hi> heifers him would gain,</l>
               <l>And gladly on their backs this Bull ſuſtain.</l>
               <l>Luſtful (37) <hi>Paſiphaë</hi> makes him her Mate,</l>
               <l>And therefore doth the lovely heifers hate.</l>
               <l>Known truths I ſing, which <hi>Creet</hi> though uſ'd to be,</l>
               <l>Nor all her (38) hundred Cities can deny.</l>
               <l>Shee with an untaught hand is ſaid to pull</l>
               <l>Green leaves, and mow the Meadows for her Bull.</l>
               <l>Amongſt the droves is in the paſtures born,</l>
               <l>Her Husband leaves, a Bull doth <hi>Minos</hi> horn.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Paſiphaë</hi> why doſt go in cloaths that are</l>
               <l>So rich? thy Bull doth not for ſuch things care.</l>
               <l>Why in a glaſs doſt feign the herd to ſee,</l>
               <l>Or that a hairy skin doth cover thee?</l>
               <l>But yet beleeve thy glaſs, for it will ſhow</l>
               <l>No horns, though wiſht for, on thy fore-head grow.</l>
               <l>Doth <hi>Minos</hi> pleaſe? no other take, at leaſt</l>
               <l>Deceive him with a man, not with a beaſt.</l>
               <l>The Queen, her bed being left, through woods and groves</l>
               <l>Like an enraged Prieſt of <hi>Bacchus</hi> roves.</l>
               <l>How hath ſhee frown'd, when ſhee did Heifer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſee,</l>
               <l>And ſaid, why ſhould my Lord ſo pleaſed bee?</l>
               <l>See how ſhee leaps before him, thinking to</l>
               <l>Pleaſe him, imagines hee's delighted ſo.</l>
               <l>Then ſhee commands her from that place be brought,</l>
               <l>To draw the undeſerved yoak be taught,</l>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:60466:10"/>
               <l>Or her a Sacrifice oth' Altar makes,</l>
               <l>And in her hands the harlots entrails takes.</l>
               <l>How oft ſhe did with ſuch the Gods appeaſe;</l>
               <l>Say thus to th' ſlain go, you my Bull could pleaſe.</l>
               <l>(39) Now <hi>Io</hi> (40) then <hi>Europa</hi> would ſhee turn,</l>
               <l>A Heifer that, this on a Bull was born.</l>
               <l>The Bull deceiv'd by her, cloz'd in a frame,</l>
               <l>The Author of a monſtrous birth became.</l>
               <l>(41) Had <hi>Creſſa</hi> to <hi>Thyeſtes</hi> bed not gone,</l>
               <l>(How hard it is to be content with one)</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sol</hi> i'th' <hi>Meridian</hi> had not ſtaid, nor then</l>
               <l>Back to <hi>Aurora</hi> had return'd agen.</l>
               <l>King (42) <hi>Niſus</hi> daughter ſtole his Purple Hair.</l>
               <l>And now a Birds form is ſuppoſ'd to bear.</l>
               <l>(43) One <hi>Scylla, Circes</hi> made, a monſter foul,</l>
               <l>Under whoſe belly furious Sea-dogs howl.</l>
               <l>(44) <hi>Atrides</hi> from all dangers ſav'd his life,</l>
               <l>Yet fell, a Victim to his luſtful wife.</l>
               <l>(45) The bloody Mother wept not for the breath</l>
               <l>Of her ſlain Sons, neither <hi>Creüſa's</hi> death.</l>
               <l>(46) <hi>Phoenix Amintors</hi> Son no tears doth ſpare.</l>
               <l>(47) <hi>Hippolitus</hi> mad horſes piece-meal tear.</l>
               <l>(48) Doting <hi>Phineus</hi> works his childrens ends,</l>
               <l>And the ſame fate upon himſelf attends.</l>
               <l>All theſe ſad miſchiefs womens luſts have made.</l>
               <l>More raging th'are than ours, and more unſtaid.</l>
               <l>Doubt not to gain what beauty ere you chuſe,</l>
               <l>Mongſt many you'l not finde one to refuſe.</l>
               <l>What they grant or deny, they love to be</l>
               <l>Entreated, let repulſe not trouble thee.</l>
               <l>Be not deceiv'd in change moſt pleaſure finde,</l>
               <l>And a new Love will alienate your minde.</l>
               <l>The Corn is riper in adjacent fields:</l>
               <l>Your neighbours Cow a larger Elder yeelds.</l>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:60466:11"/>
               <l>Firſt let it be your care her Maid to gain,</l>
               <l>For ſhee an eaſie entrance can obtain.</l>
               <l>Be ſure 'tis her that all her ſecrets knows,</l>
               <l>To whom ſhee doth her private thoughts diſcloſe.</l>
               <l>With gifts and promiſes corrupt her, ſhee</l>
               <l>Can eaſily with thy wiſhes furniſh thee.</l>
               <l>Shee'l chuſe a time, and ſo Phyſicians uſe,</l>
               <l>When her you love is leaſt apt to refuſe.</l>
               <l>Shee's fit'ſt for ſuch impreſſions when ſhee ſmiles,</l>
               <l>So ſtanding Corn thrives beſt in fatting ſoils;</l>
               <l>When mirth ſhee entertains, no griefs moleſt,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Venus</hi> is ſoon'ſt admitted to her breaſt.</l>
               <l>(49) <hi>Ilion</hi> when ſad, with arms defended ſits,</l>
               <l>When glad, the foe containing horſe admits.</l>
               <l>Try when ſome foe hath croſt her, for then ſhee</l>
               <l>T'revenge her ſelf on him, will pleaſure thee.</l>
               <l>The Maid imploy'd in dreſſing of her head,</l>
               <l>May move this, and to you aſſiſtance add.</l>
               <l>With a low murmuring noiſe, thus whiſper, ſure</l>
               <l>You cannot his unworthy change endure;</l>
               <l>Then ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e may name you, urge your praiſes high,</l>
               <l>Swear, for her love you are reſolv'd to dye;</l>
               <l>Make haſte then and go to her, leſt ſhee may</l>
               <l>Be angry and grow cold, through your delay.</l>
               <l>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ou ſhould think the beſt way's to begin</l>
               <l>And kiſs her Maid, much danger is therein.</l>
               <l>The Maid is coming, but the Miſtreſs coy,</l>
               <l>That would have what this onely ſhould injoy.</l>
               <l>'Tis hazardous, though ſweet, hard to refrain,</l>
               <l>Yet my advice is, that you ſhould abſtain.</l>
               <l>Headlong o're Precipeeces Ile not tread,</l>
               <l>Nor following mee, ſhall young men be miſ-led,</l>
               <l>Receiving Letters by her, though you finde</l>
               <l>Some pretty poſtures pleaſing to your mind,</l>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:60466:11"/>
               <l>Yet th' Miſtreſs then ſhee's yours, to <hi>Venus</hi> ſee</l>
               <l>That your firſt offering no Handmaid be.</l>
               <l>This I adviſe, if you will credit Art,</l>
               <l>Let not my words like hollow winds depart.</l>
               <l>Never attempt, or elſe a conqueſt make,</l>
               <l>Y'are ſafe, if ever ſhee your crimes partake.</l>
               <l>Neither can Birds from their lim'd feathers flye,</l>
               <l>Nor can the Boar the Windowy Net untye.</l>
               <l>The Fiſh is eaſ'ly caught, when ſtruct by Art,</l>
               <l>Do not unſatisfi'd from her depart.</l>
               <l>The fault being mutual, ſhee will not accuſe,</l>
               <l>Or to declare her Miſtreſs mind refuſe.</l>
               <l>If you keep Counſel, do her not diſcover,</l>
               <l>Shee'l be to you a mind-informing Lover.</l>
               <l>Hee's out that thinks hee may at pleaſure plow,</l>
               <l>Or <hi>Pilots</hi> any time for Sea allow.</l>
               <l>Alwaies the Husbandman doth not prevail,</l>
               <l>Neither do ſhips in every ſeaſon ſail.</l>
               <l>Alwaies to be a courting's not ſecure,</l>
               <l>You onely at convenient times muſt wooe her;</l>
               <l>If it her birth-day bee, or when the Queen</l>
               <l>Of Love, with <hi>Mars</hi> is in conjunction ſeen;</l>
               <l>Or when ſh'has on a cloath of Silver-gown,</l>
               <l>And in the <hi>Circus</hi> a rich prize put down,</l>
               <l>Deſiſt: when winter comes, and (50) <hi>Pleiade<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi>
               </l>
               <l>For that the (51) Goat is ſwallowed in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>'Tis beſt leave off: then they which truſt the deep,</l>
               <l>Scarce any part of their torn ſails can keep.</l>
               <l>Begin ſuch time as (52) <hi>Allia</hi> before</l>
               <l>Began t' look red, and bluſh with <hi>Roman</hi> gore.</l>
               <l>Or on that (53) Feaſt begin to court again</l>
               <l>Which th' (54) man of <hi>Paleſtina</hi> did ordain.</l>
               <l>Be ſure her birth-day ſolemnly be ſpent,</l>
               <l>You ſomething, though cloſe-fiſted, muſt preſent.</l>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:60466:12"/>
               <l>Ladies do many pretty motions make,</l>
               <l>And any thing that is that ſervants take.</l>
               <l>The M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lliner firſt will to your Miſtreſs go,</l>
               <l>You ſtanding by, to her his wares will ſhow;</l>
               <l>Shee'l your opinion ask, and ſomething try,</l>
               <l>Then with a kiſs intice you for to buy.</l>
               <l>Shee'l ſay her uſe it a long time may fit,</l>
               <l>'Tis very cheap, and ſhee hath need of it;</l>
               <l>Then if you ſay you cann't ſo much expend,</l>
               <l>Shee'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bid you write for it unto ſome friend.</l>
               <l>Give her upon her birth-day what you will,</l>
               <l>When ere ſhee wants, that is her birth-day ſtill;</l>
               <l>Or from her ear a Jewels dropt ſhee'l feign,</l>
               <l>And then you muſt buy one for her again.</l>
               <l>Shee'l borrow many things, yet none reſtore,</l>
               <l>Nor ſhall your loſs of them gain favour more.</l>
               <l>Ten mouths, as many tongues too little are</l>
               <l>For mee the Arts of Harlots to declare.</l>
               <l>Firſt let a Letter ſeal'd an entrance finde,</l>
               <l>Let your wax bear the impreſs of your mind:</l>
               <l>And let your Letter love expreſſions bear,</l>
               <l>To which you muſt add an imploring prayer.</l>
               <l>At th' (55) Kings requeſt <hi>Achilles</hi> did refend</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hector:</hi> and Heaven will to prayers bend.</l>
               <l>Promiſes hurt not you, then promiſe much,</l>
               <l>'T makes thoſe that are not rich, ſeem to be ſuch.</l>
               <l>Your Letter wins her, if ſhee credit it,</l>
               <l>Hope's a falſe Goddeſs, yet for you moſt fit.</l>
               <l>Give her not much, for fear that you ſhould part<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>Shee onely gains then, thou the loſer art.</l>
               <l>Bee alwaies giving, yet let nothing go,</l>
               <l>Swains are with barren ſoil deluded ſo:</l>
               <l>The ground will get, and hee beſows in vain,</l>
               <l>Until that l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſs his greedy hands detain.</l>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:60466:12"/>
               <l>Her favour you may without gifts procure,</l>
               <l>If ſhee love <hi>gratis,</hi> it will long'ſt indure.</l>
               <l>With handſome lines you muſt prepare her mind,</l>
               <l>Firſt try if thoſe will entertainment finde.</l>
               <l>A Letter wonn <hi>Cydippe,</hi> which was brought,</l>
               <l>And the poor Maid was with her own words caught.</l>
               <l>I'de have young men the liberal Arts to gain,</l>
               <l>They better may a Clients cauſe maintain.</l>
               <l>The Maids in 's favour pleaſing looks will ſend,</l>
               <l>Whom the grave Judge and Senate do commend.</l>
               <l>To get applauſe, in learning ſtrive t'excel:</l>
               <l>Let not your lips on tedious ſtories dwell.</l>
               <l>Who to his Miſtreſs uſeth to declame?</l>
               <l>Ladies will oft-times long Epiſtles blame.</l>
               <l>Yet ſmoothe and taking words, a handſome ſtile,</l>
               <l>That ſhee may at your pleaſing language ſmile.</l>
               <l>Doth ſhee your Letter back unread reſend,</l>
               <l>Proceed and hope ſhee'l read it in the end.</l>
               <l>In time the ſullen Steer will draw the Plow:</l>
               <l>The reigns in time the ſtubborn horſe will bow:</l>
               <l>The Iron Clivies daily uſe will fret,</l>
               <l>And th' paſſive earth the crooked ſhare doth whet;</l>
               <l>The ſofteſt drops by conſtant falling on,</l>
               <l>Will make impreſſion on the hardeſt ſtone.</l>
               <l>Perſiſt, were ſhee <hi>Penelope,</hi> you'd gain,</l>
               <l>(57) <hi>Pergamus</hi> late, but yet at laſt was tane.</l>
               <l>Urge her not back again to write a line;</l>
               <l>'Tis grace enough if ſhee but look on thine.</l>
               <l>If once ſhee read, ſhee will write back, but theſe</l>
               <l>Great favours ſhee beſtoweth by degrees.</l>
               <l>Perhaps her firſt Letter no pleaſure brings,</l>
               <l>Bids you not trouble her with ſuch fond things;</l>
               <l>But yet ſhee prayes that you may fixt remain;</l>
               <l>Purſue, and fear not but you will obtain.</l>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:60466:13"/>
               <l>If you your Miſtreſs on her bed eſpy,</l>
               <l>Thrown on her back, accoſt her privately,</l>
               <l>Be ſure that none o're-hear, leſt they defame,</l>
               <l>And add a ſcandal to your Miſtreſs name.</l>
               <l>If in the porch you chance to ſpy her ſtay,</l>
               <l>Walk at a diſtance till ſhee go away.</l>
               <l>Sometimes before, ſometimes behinde her go,</l>
               <l>Now you may walk apace, and then walk ſlow;</l>
               <l>When you ſhall overtake her, do n't diffide,</l>
               <l>But go as cloſe as may bee to her ſide;</l>
               <l>If ſhee to th' Curved Theatre be gone,</l>
               <l>There follow her, obſerve what ſhee hath on;</l>
               <l>There you may boldly look on her attire,</l>
               <l>Commend her eyes, and every part admire;</l>
               <l>Applaud the fool that to a Wench doth ſtart,</l>
               <l>And favour him that acts a Lovers part;</l>
               <l>When ſhee ſtands, ſtand, when ſhee ſits, do not ſtire</l>
               <l>And gladly ſpend the time in ſerving her;</l>
               <l>Do not uſe inſtruments to curle your hair,</l>
               <l>Neither your leggs with the rough Pumice wear.</l>
               <l>Thoſe things provide, (58) which <hi>Cybil</hi> did deviſe</l>
               <l>Lamented, Sung to in the <hi>Phrygian</hi> guiſe:</l>
               <l>Neglected Modes become beſt, <hi>Theſeus</hi> brought</l>
               <l>Away <hi>Minois</hi> not by Courtiers taught.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Phaedra, Hippolitus,</hi> though rude, lov'd well:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Adonis, Venus</hi> care, ith' woods did dwell.</l>
               <l>Neatneſs delights, the fields will tan too much,</l>
               <l>Be ſure your cloaths be handſome, without ſmutch;</l>
               <l>Keep your tongue ſmooth, and let your teeth be fair,</l>
               <l>Nor on your feet ſhooes that are too big wear;</l>
               <l>And then your hair in order neatly put,</l>
               <l>Let your beard by a skilful hand be cut;</l>
               <l>Look that your nails be clean, and keep them low,</l>
               <l>Nor let your hairs within your noſtrils grow;</l>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:60466:13"/>
               <l>Your breath if it corrupted be, perſume,</l>
               <l>Let not a Goatiſh luſt your noſe conſume.</l>
               <l>Leave ſuch like things for ſhameleſs Maids to uſe,</l>
               <l>And men that baſely their own fex abuſe.</l>
               <l>(59) <hi>Liber</hi> ſtiles mee his Poet, hee doth aid</l>
               <l>Lovers, and flames within himſelf hath made.</l>
               <l>(60) Poor <hi>Ariadne</hi> on the ſhoar complains</l>
               <l>of <hi>Dia,</hi> which the watery Sea contains.</l>
               <l>Starting from ſleep, bare-leg'd, unlac'd her cloaths,</l>
               <l>Shee with neglected golden treſſes goes.</l>
               <l>Shee cruel <hi>Theſeus</hi> calls, him oft repeats,</l>
               <l>Whilſt a fierce ſtorm her tender body beats;</l>
               <l>Shee weeps and ſighs, but yet ſhee's handſome ſtill,</l>
               <l>Nor do inceſſant tears make her look ill.</l>
               <l>Now ſtriking on her tender breaſt, quoth ſhee,</l>
               <l>Falſe man, hee's gone, what will becomeof mee?</l>
               <l>When towards the ſhoar ſhee hears a Cymbal, and</l>
               <l>A Timbrel ſtruck by a commanding hand;</l>
               <l>Amaz'd ſhee falls, is of all ſenſe bereſt,</l>
               <l>No blood is in her liveleſs body left.</l>
               <l>Lo (61) <hi>Mimalonides</hi> with carelſs hair,</l>
               <l>And Satyrs do before a God appear.</l>
               <l>Loe (62) old <hi>Silenus</hi> drunk, upon his Aſs,</l>
               <l>Scarce ſits, yet holding by the mane, doth paſs.</l>
               <l>And whilſt hee follows flying <hi>Menades,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Hee on his dull beaſt with a cudgel layes;</l>
               <l>And tumbling down, beating his ears hee lies,</l>
               <l>Whilſt the young Satyrs cry, Riſe Father, riſe.</l>
               <l>Next (63) comes the God himſelf up, who was born</l>
               <l>By Tygers, in a Grape-carv'd Chariot drawn.</l>
               <l>Speech, colour, <hi>Theſeus</hi> left the heartleſs Maid,</l>
               <l>Thrice ſhee'd a fled, thrice by her fear was ſtaid,</l>
               <l>As a ſtrong wind the weakeſt ſtem doth ſtir,</l>
               <l>Or Reeds in madid fens, ſo fear ſhakes her.</l>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:60466:14"/>
               <l>To whom the God: Loe here's one that will bee</l>
               <l>More <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, fear not, thou ſhalt marry mee.</l>
               <l>In Heaven I will ſeat thee 'mongſt the Stars,</l>
               <l>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Maid of <hi>Cree<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> ſhalt guide the Mariners.</l>
               <l>Thus ſaid: leſt that his beaſts ſhould her moleſt,</l>
               <l>The God leaps down, his feet the ſand compreſt;</l>
               <l>Then her, unable to reſiſt, doth bring</l>
               <l>Folded in's arms, Gods may do any thing.</l>
               <l>Some <hi>Hymen</hi> ſing, (64) others <hi>Evohe</hi> ſed,</l>
               <l>So th' God and's Bride joyn iſſue in their bed.</l>
               <l>When you to <hi>Bacchus</hi> plenteous pots ſhall come,</l>
               <l>Having a Lady in your bed at home,</l>
               <l>(65) <hi>Nyctelius</hi> your Father beg to lend</l>
               <l>His aid, that Wine may not your head offend.</l>
               <l>You in a latent way may ſpeak things ſo,</l>
               <l>That ſhee, 'tis onely her you mean, may know.</l>
               <l>Let ſweet diſcourſe wait on your Wine, that ſhee</l>
               <l>May Miſtreſs of your Table chuſe to bec;</l>
               <l>And that your flame may be acknowledg'd, you</l>
               <l>Muſt teach your looks as well as lips to wooe.</l>
               <l>Firſt take the Cup, and kiſs the very place,</l>
               <l>Which with her lips ſhee did in drinking grace;</l>
               <l>The meat her fair hand carves deſire, and</l>
               <l>As you receive it, gently touch her hand.</l>
               <l>Let your care be to pleaſe her Father, ſuch</l>
               <l>A friend will properate your buſineſs much;</l>
               <l>When you drink, firſt to him your cup direct,</l>
               <l>In keeping your head bare ſhew him reſpect;</l>
               <l>Whether hee bee your equal, or below,</l>
               <l>Yet ſtill a like reſpect unto him ſhow.</l>
               <l>Through friendſhip to deceive is ſaf'ſt of all,</l>
               <l>Yet hee that ſo deceives is criminal.</l>
               <l>Many will too much liquor quaff, and think</l>
               <l>Others, 'cauſe they have done't, muſt as much drink<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:60466:14"/>
               <l>Obſerve to keep a mean in drinking ſo,</l>
               <l>Your tongue and feet their office beſt will know;</l>
               <l>Chiefly beware of quarrelling in Wine,</l>
               <l>For then your hands too much to blows incline.</l>
               <l>Through too much Wine <hi>Eurition</hi> fell to th'earth:</l>
               <l>Wine and a Banquet are moſt fit for mirth;</l>
               <l>Have you a voice, then ſing, if nimble, dance;</l>
               <l>What pleaſing part ſoe're you have, advance.</l>
               <l>Really drunk doth hurt, but ſo to feign,</l>
               <l>I think is good, if you cannot ſpeak plain,</l>
               <l>Then if you ſpeak, or do what is unfit,</l>
               <l>The Wine is judg'd to be the cauſe of it.</l>
               <l>Say th'man ſhe'l ſleep by ſhall moſt happy bee</l>
               <l>But pray not for him if ſhee means not thee.</l>
               <l>When Dinner's ended, and the Table's gone,</l>
               <l>An opportunity waits you upon.</l>
               <l>Step through the throng, your Miſtreſs come cloſe to</l>
               <l>And foot by foot with her from th'Table go.</l>
               <l>Now is the time to ſpeak, then fears prevent</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Venus</hi> and Fortune aid the confident.</l>
               <l>Our Art cann't Eloquence on you beſtow,</l>
               <l>Onely endeavour't, and you ſhall bee ſo.</l>
               <l>You love muſt act, you feeling wounds muſt feign,</l>
               <l>By all means try a promiſe to obtain.</l>
               <l>Think no pains great, and ſay all lovely are,</l>
               <l>Though ne're ſo foul, ſome do eſteem them fair.</l>
               <l>Oft a diſſembler I have ſeen in love,</l>
               <l>What firſt hee feign'd, at length did real prove.</l>
               <l>Then Ladies uſe men kindly in the end,</l>
               <l>Their love proves true, which they at firſt pretend<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>With praiſes you may captivate her mind,</l>
               <l>So banks are with ſoft water undermin'd.</l>
               <l>Her face admire, her lovely hair commend,</l>
               <l>Her little ſlender foot, her dainty hand.</l>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:60466:15"/>
               <l>The chaſteſt Maids with praiſe delighted are,</l>
               <l>A Virgins beauty is her love and care.</l>
               <l>Th' two Goddeſſes on <hi>Ida</hi> wo'nt appear,</l>
               <l>Becauſe they were not judg'd the faireſt there.</l>
               <l>(66) <hi>Juno's</hi> bird if commended ſpreads his train,</l>
               <l>Silent look on him, and hee'l cloze't again.</l>
               <l>Race-horſes for to have their manes lye ſtraight,</l>
               <l>And to be clapt upon their necks delight.</l>
               <l>Fear not to promiſe, promiſes will move,</l>
               <l>And call the Gods as witneſs to your love.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Jove</hi> from above laughs at Loves perjuries,</l>
               <l>Bidding <hi>Aeolus</hi> blow away ſuch toyes;</l>
               <l>For hee himſelf did falſly uſe to ſwear</l>
               <l>By Styx to <hi>Juno,</hi> his examples are.</l>
               <l>'Tis fit there ſhould be Gods, that wee ſhould know,</l>
               <l>And unto them accuſtomed honours do.</l>
               <l>To careleſs ſleep themſelves they do not give:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The Godhead ſees thee, therefore harmleſs live.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Reſtore what th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u haſt borrowed, none delude,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nor have thy hands in humane blood imbru'd.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Falſhood to Maids only unpuniſht goes,</l>
               <l>Faith's leaſt aſhamed to be broke with thoſe.</l>
               <l>Cheat thoſe deceivers moſt of falſhood made,</l>
               <l>They oft fall into th'nets themſelves have laid.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aegypt</hi> is ſaid nine years t' have wanted Rain,</l>
               <l>And ſo long under parching drought had lain.</l>
               <l>When <hi>Thraſius</hi> to <hi>Buſiris</hi> coming, ſaid,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Jove</hi>'s wrath muſt be with ſtrangers blood allay'd:</l>
               <l>To whom <hi>Buſiris:</hi> then ſhalt thou be ſlain</l>
               <l>A Sacrifice to <hi>Jove</hi> for <hi>Aegypts</hi> Rain.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Perillus</hi> in a red-hot Bull was laid,</l>
               <l>Which hee a torment had for others made;</l>
               <l>Both theſe were juſt, let death-inventers dye,</l>
               <l>And firſt thoſe torments made for others, try.</l>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:60466:15"/>
               <l>So let perfidiouſneſs falſeneſs prevent,</l>
               <l>And women wrong'd, as they wrong us, lament.</l>
               <l>Tears drop, for thoſe a ſtony-heart will move,</l>
               <l>By madid eyes let her perceive your love.</l>
               <l>If tears (for at all times men cannot cry)</l>
               <l>You want, with a wet finger rub your eye.</l>
               <l>Wiſe men mix kiſſes with the words they ſpeak,</l>
               <l>If they'l not give, ſuch things ungiven take.</l>
               <l>But ſhee'l perhaps refuſe, an anger feign,</l>
               <l>Yet wiſhes her reſiſtance be in vain.</l>
               <l>Take heed that when upon her lips you ſeize,</l>
               <l>To preſs them not too hard, leſt it diſpleaſe.</l>
               <l>Who gains a kiſs, and other ſweets gets nor,</l>
               <l>Deſerves to loſe that kiſs which hee hath got.</l>
               <l>If after kiſſes pleaſures wanting were,</l>
               <l>It was thy clowniſhneſs, not baſhful fear;</l>
               <l>Forcing they tearm it, yet that force is ſweet,</l>
               <l>With it, againſt their wills, they gladly meet;</l>
               <l>Shee that's of <hi>Venus</hi> will no rape forſake,</l>
               <l>But let her wantonneſs full pleaſure take;</l>
               <l>And ſhee that may, yet doth untoucht depart,</l>
               <l>Though ſhee ſeem glad, at it is ſad at heart.</l>
               <l>Both (67) <hi>Phaebe</hi> and her ſiſter raviſht were,</l>
               <l>Yet they were grateful to their raviſher.</l>
               <l>Here is a ſtory that deſerves my pen,</l>
               <l>How the (68) <hi>Aemonian</hi> did the <hi>Scyrian</hi> win,</l>
               <l>When <hi>Venus</hi> worthy ſuch a prize to have,</l>
               <l>On <hi>Ida,</hi> her unlucky (69) promiſe gave,</l>
               <l>Which now a daughter doth to <hi>Priam</hi> fly,</l>
               <l>And is receiv'd with welcomes into <hi>Troy.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>All, to revenge the injur'd husband, ſwear</l>
               <l>And each a part do in his ſufferings bear.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Achilles</hi> at his Mothers baſe requeſt,</l>
               <l>Conceals his Sex, in womens cloaths is dreſt.</l>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:60466:16"/>
               <l>What doſt <hi>Aeacides?</hi> don't wooll deſire,</l>
               <l>Titles of honour otherwaies acquire.</l>
               <l>Why doth thy target-arm thoſe baskets wear?</l>
               <l>Why yarn, ith' hand muſt <hi>Hector</hi> kill, doſt bear?</l>
               <l>Never into that hand a ſpindle take,</l>
               <l>Which onely ſhould the Spear of <hi>Peleus</hi> ſhake.</l>
               <l>By chance in the ſame bed a Royal Maid,</l>
               <l>Who quickly found hee was a man, was laid:</l>
               <l>Shee by his force was overcome wee know,</l>
               <l>Yet ſhee was willing to be forced ſo.</l>
               <l>Oft when <hi>Achilles</hi> in the morn would riſe,</l>
               <l>To ſet his diſtaff ſpear betwixt his thighs:</l>
               <l>Now where's that forcing, thou <hi>Deidamia,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>With flattering words thy raviſher wouldſt ſtay?</l>
               <l>They'r baſhful till th' have firſt receiv'd it, then</l>
               <l>Having once try'd, they muſt try't ore agen.</l>
               <l>Alas too much hee to his form doth truſt,</l>
               <l>That doth expect his Miſtreſs ſhould ſpeak firſt.</l>
               <l>Firſt let the man approach her, and beſeech,</l>
               <l>Ladies will hearken to a handſome ſpeech.</l>
               <l>Speak if you would obtain, ſhee would bee askt,</l>
               <l>With words let your deſires be unmaskt.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Jove</hi> ſuppliant went unto the Maids of old,</l>
               <l>Deny his ſure no Virgin ever could.</l>
               <l>If you perceive her ſcorn at, and diſdain</l>
               <l>Your prayers, forbear, from her a while abſlain.</l>
               <l>They love what's not, at what is theirs they ſcoff,</l>
               <l>Take their diſdain away by keeping off.</l>
               <l>Alwaies by courting her ſhee'l never bend,</l>
               <l>Sometimes go wait upon her as a friend;</l>
               <l>By ſuch an action to obtain, I one</l>
               <l>To come neglected, go belov'd, have known.</l>
               <l>Merchants ſhould not have feminine looks, but bee</l>
               <l>Made ſwarthy by the Sun, and ſtorms at Sea.</l>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:60466:16"/>
               <l>It ill-becomes a Plow-man to look fair,</l>
               <l>That turns <hi>Joves</hi> earth up with a crooked ſhare.</l>
               <l>You ſhould not have a Ladies ſmooth-skind face,</l>
               <l>That on your head would <hi>Pallas</hi> Chaplet place.</l>
               <l>In Lovers, pining looks do moſt excel,</l>
               <l>Though ſome ſay not, yet it becomes them well.</l>
               <l>Pale-face't <hi>Orion</hi> in the woods did rove,</l>
               <l>So (70) <hi>Daphnis</hi> lookt for gentle <hi>Nais</hi> Love.</l>
               <l>Thin looks a Lover argue, ſometimes wear</l>
               <l>A ſickly cap upon thy well cut hair.</l>
               <l>Sorrows and griefs immenſe with watchings late,</l>
               <l>Th' effects of Love young men attenuate;</l>
               <l>That you may win, ſeem miſerable, ſo</l>
               <l>That all may ſay, there one in Love doth go.</l>
               <l>Should I adviſe, complain, right, wrong allow,</l>
               <l>Friendſhip and truth are diſ-eſteemed now.</l>
               <l>Praiſe her not to a friend, leſt he ſhould prove</l>
               <l>With her, beleeving your report, in Love.</l>
               <l>Yet <hi>Patroclus</hi> ne're ſtain'd <hi>Achilles</hi> bed,</l>
               <l>And (71) <hi>Pirithous</hi> from baſe <hi>Phedra</hi> fled.</l>
               <l>As <hi>Phaebus, Pallas,</hi> (72) <hi>Hermion, Pylades,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Or as the two Twins lov'd <hi>Tyndarides:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who hopes the like, may look for Plumbs to grow</l>
               <l>On Tam'rix, or that ſtreams with hony flow.</l>
               <l>Baſeneſs delights now, pleaſure's all their care,</l>
               <l>And thoſe, to others griefs, obtained are.</l>
               <l>O wicked! Lovers fear no open ſoe,</l>
               <l>Shun whom you truſt, and you may ſafely go,</l>
               <l>Nor Brother, nor a friend confide in, juſt</l>
               <l>Occaſion they will give you to miſtruſt.</l>
               <l>I've almoſt done what thoughts the Ladies raiſe,</l>
               <l>Their ſeveral humours court their ſeveral waies.</l>
               <l>No places for all grain convenient are,</l>
               <l>That Vines, this Olives, others Corn will bear.</l>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:60466:17"/>
               <l>As many minds on earth as features known,</l>
               <l>And a wiſe man prepares for every one.</l>
               <l>As nimble (73) <hi>Proteus</hi> uſ'd transform'd to bee,</l>
               <l>A Lion, now a Boar, and then a Tree.</l>
               <l>Some fiſh with darts are caught, others with th' hook,</l>
               <l>And ſome within a hollow net are took.</l>
               <l>One way will not with any age agtee,</l>
               <l>Far off old women your devices ſee.</l>
               <l>If learn'd to th' rude you ſeem, or wanton to</l>
               <l>The chaſte, no more ſhee'l truſt her ſelf with you.</l>
               <l>Hence 'tis they fearful, honeſt men forſake,</l>
               <l>And oft th' imbrace of an inferiour take.</l>
               <l>Some of my work's perform'd, ſome's to be made,</l>
               <l>And here my ſhip is by her Anchor ſtay'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>The End of the firſt Book.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="annotations">
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:60466:17"/>
            <head>Annotations on the firſt Book OF <hi>Publius Ovidius Naſo De Arte Amandi.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">(1) <hi>Automedon</hi> in) an expert Charioteer, the Son of <hi>Diora</hi> and ſervant to <hi>Achilles. Virg. Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neid.</hi> 2.</p>
            <q>
               <l>— equorum agitator Achillis</l>
               <l>armiger Automedon —</l>
            </q>
            <p n="2">(2) <hi>Typhis</hi> the <hi>Aemonian</hi>-ſhip) <hi>Typhis</hi> was Pilot to the firſt ſhip framed in <hi>Greece,</hi> called <hi>Argo,</hi> which tranſported the Princes <hi>Jaſon, Hercules, Theſeus, Caſtor, Pollux,</hi> and the reſt of the Miny's to <hi>Colchos</hi> to fetch the golden Fleece, called <hi>Aemonian,</hi> from Mount <hi>Haemus,</hi> which divideth <hi>Theſſaly</hi> from <hi>Thrace,</hi> from which Mountain <hi>Theſſaly</hi> is often called <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">(3) <hi>Phillyrides</hi> to) <hi>Chiren</hi> the <hi>Centaur</hi> ſo called from his Mother <hi>Phillyra,</hi> hee (to omit the fable of his procreation) being grown up, retiring himſelf to the woods, to inquire into the nature of Herbs, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came an excellent Phyſician; hee taught <hi>Aeſculapius</hi> Phyſick, <hi>Hercules</hi> Aſtrology, and <hi>Achilles,</hi> beſides many other things, to play on the Harp.</p>
            <p n="4">(4) Gods came) both <hi>Cupid</hi> and <hi>Achilles; Cupid</hi> from his Mother <hi>Venus,</hi> and <hi>Achilles</hi> from the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſſe <hi>Thetis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">(5) <hi>Clio</hi> nor) The Muſes nine in number, begotten
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:60466:18"/>by <hi>Jupiter</hi> upon <hi>Mnemoſyne,</hi> whence they are called <hi>Mnemoſynides,</hi> we finde them mentioned by many other names, as <hi>Heliconides, Parnaſſides, Aoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, Citherides, Corycides, Pierides, Pegaſides, Aganip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pides, Hippocrenides, I liſſiades, Libethrides, Pimpleides, Caſtalides, Pateides, Ardalides, Maonides,</hi> and <hi>Sice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lides,</hi> all which names are attributed to them, either from their habitations, or from the places conſecrate unto them. Their particular names are <hi>Calliope,</hi> a ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhing ſinger; <hi>Erato</hi> the Lovers Muſe; <hi>Thalia</hi> from her flouriſhing Poetry; <hi>Melpomene</hi> from her delicate warbling, a Tragick Muſe; <hi>Terpſicore</hi> from her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in dancing; <hi>Clio</hi> the celebrater of famous actions; <hi>Euterpe</hi> the inventreſs of the Mathematicks; <hi>Polyhymnia</hi> from her vaſt memory, the Muſe of Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory; <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania</hi> a heavenly ſinger, the Muſe of Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomy. <hi>Heſiod. degenerat. Deorum.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Which I engliſh</p>
            <q>
               <l>Jove <hi>had nine Girls,</hi> Euterpe, Thalia,</l>
               <l>Clio, Melpomene, Polymnia,</l>
               <l>Erato; Urania, Terpſicore,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And 'bove the reſt famous</hi> Calliope.</l>
            </q>
            <p n="6">(6) <hi>Aſcrean</hi> Green) a Plain in <hi>Boeotia,</hi> neer <hi>Heli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con:</hi> ſuch an expreſſion hath <hi>Propertius</hi> in <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>ad Muſam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nondum etiam Aſcreos norint mea carmina fontes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">(7) <hi>Vittae</hi> badge of modeſty; and borders) a Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen Band or Fillet which the Veſtal Nuns tye up their hair with: <hi>Ovid</hi> ſpeaking of <hi>Daphne's</hi> chaſtity. <hi>Met.</hi> 2. ſaith,</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:60466:18"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>—innuptae<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> aemula Phoebes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vitta coërcebat poſitos ſine lege capillos.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>— and aemulous of <hi>Phoebe</hi> chaſte</l>
               <l>The Vitta her neglected hair imbrac't.</l>
            </q>
            <p>For the borders. I take them to be the nether end of the gown, which <hi>Sigonius</hi> calls <hi>Stola Cinctura a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrictior,</hi> denoting a modeſt woman.</p>
            <p n="8">(8) <hi>Perſeus Andromade) Andromade</hi> was Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to <hi>Cepheus,</hi> and <hi>Caſſiope,</hi> who for her Mothers pride, comparing her beauty with the Sea-Nymphs <hi>Nereides,</hi> was by the Nymphs taken, bound to a Rock, and expoſed to a mercileſs Sea-Monſter, yet notwithſtanding was delivered by <hi>Perſeus,</hi> who ſlew the Monſter, and afterwards married her by the conſent of her Parents. <hi>Metam.</hi> 4.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>—generum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſalutant</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Auxiliam<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> domus, ſervatorem<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> fatentur</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Caſſiope, Cepheuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> pater—</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>—Cepheus</hi> and <hi>Caſſiope</hi> with joy</l>
               <l>Salute him for their Son, whom now they call</l>
               <l>The Saviour of their houſe, and of them all.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Perſeus</hi> was begot by <hi>Jupiter</hi> upon <hi>Danaë</hi> Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to <hi>Acriſius</hi> King of the <hi>Argives,</hi> who being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſht that his Grandchilde ſhould kill him, ſhut his Daughter <hi>Danaë</hi> in a ſtrong Tower, intending with her body to mure her womb up, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently avert his foredoomed fate, but when <hi>Jupiter</hi> in the form of a golden ſhowre, had begotten <hi>Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> upon her, ſhee with her Infant being in a ſmall boat, committed to the Sea in expectation of inevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table deſtruction, were miraculouſly preſerved; <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeus</hi> grown up, returned, and unfortunately ſlew his Grandfather.</p>
            <p n="9">(9) From <hi>India</hi> brought) <hi>India tot a ſerme ſpectat O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rientem,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:60466:19"/>minus in latitudinem, &amp;c. India</hi> (ſaith <hi>Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius, lib.</hi> 8.) lieth toward the Eaſt, containing more in longitude, than latitude; the North parts bee mountainous and hilly, but all the reſt of the Land campain: It hath many famous Rivers, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending down from Mount <hi>Caucaſus,</hi> make a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful progreſs thorow the Countries. <hi>Indus</hi> is more cold than any other of the Rivers, whoſe wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter reſembles the colour of the Sea. <hi>Ganges</hi> is the greateſt of all, which running thorow the Southern Country, until meeting with the oppoſition of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Rocks and Precipeeces, his courſe is turned Eaſtwards, where it is ſwallowed up of the Red Sea. When other Countries be burned with the Sun, <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia</hi> is covered over with Snow; and when other places be frozen, the heat is there intolerable: for which appears no natural reaſon. The Elephants in this Country be bigger and ſtronger than thoſe of <hi>Africk:</hi> The Rivers carry down Gold, and run ſmoothly along, and the Sea doth caſt upon the ſhore both pearls and precious ſtones. <hi>Stephanus</hi> ſaith, the Trees are alwaies green, that the ground bears corn twice a year, that from hence comes <hi>Pep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, Calamus Aromaticus,</hi> and <hi>Cynamon. Aelian lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Vari.</hi> ſaith, their Pigeons are of a yellow colour.</p>
            <p n="10">(10) <hi>Rome</hi> affords) <hi>Rome</hi> the Metropolis of <hi>Italy,</hi> and moſt celebrated City of the whole world, of which <hi>Virgil</hi> in his firſt Egloge makes <hi>Tytyrus</hi> ſpeak thus,
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Urbem quam dicunt Romam Melibaee putavi</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Stultus ego huic noſtrae ſimtlem, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Engliſhed by Mr. <hi>Ogleby.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That City they call <hi>Rome,</hi> I did account</l>
                  <l>Fondly like this of ours, where Swains are wont</l>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:60466:19"/>
                  <l>Yearly with care to wean their tender Lambs;</l>
                  <l>So I conceiv'd Whelps equal to their Dams,</l>
                  <l>And judg'd that Kids were as their Mothers tall,</l>
                  <l>So uſ'd I great things to compare with ſmall:</l>
                  <l>But ſhee 'bove other Cities lifts her head,</l>
                  <l>As o're the Shrubs the lofty Cedars ſpread.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>It was called <hi>Rome</hi> from its founder <hi>Romulus,</hi> who built it on Mount <hi>Palatine,</hi> in a quadrangular form, which Mount hath ever ſince been the Seat of the <hi>Romane</hi> Emperors. It is called <hi>Urbs Septi-collis,</hi> from the ſeven hills on which it ſtandeth, their names are theſe, the <hi>Mount Palatine,</hi> the <hi>Capitolian Mount, Quirinus Mount,</hi> the <hi>Caelian Mount,</hi> the <hi>Mount Eſquilinus,</hi> the <hi>Mount Viminalis,</hi> and the <hi>Mount Aventine. Ovid. Triſt. lib.</hi> 1.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sed quae de ſeptem tot um circumſpicit orbem</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Montibus imperii Roma Deum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> locus.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rome,</hi> which from ſeven hills doth over-look</l>
               <l>The world, the Gods have for their Empire took.</l>
               <l>See <hi>Romulus infra.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p n="11">(11) On <hi>Ida)</hi> a high Mountain that looks to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Troy,</hi> the North-ſide of it reaching from the Straits of <hi>Abidos,</hi> to the <hi>Cyzycene</hi> Fields in the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pontis,</hi> the Weft-ſide looks over the <hi>Helleſpont,</hi> the South makes a Promontory, and the Eaſtern parts decline towards <hi>Miſſia. Hom. lib.</hi> 8. <hi>Iliad.</hi> ſaith, that the top of it is called <hi>Gargarus,</hi> where there is a Temple conſecrate to <hi>Jupiter,</hi> and that it hath many Springs, and multitudes of wilde-beaſts.</p>
            <p n="12">(12) <hi>Lesbos</hi> found) in <hi>Methimna</hi> a Town of <hi>Lesbos,</hi> ſo called from <hi>Methymna,</hi> the daughter of <hi>Macharis,</hi> are abundance of Vines; in this place the famous Harper <hi>Orion</hi> was born.</p>
            <p n="13">(13) Of her Son) of her Son <hi>Aeneas,</hi> who with
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:60466:20"/>ſome Sea-beaten Trojans arrived in <hi>Italy,</hi> where hee van quiſhed <hi>Turnus,</hi> and married <hi>Lavinia,</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="14">(14) <hi>Leo</hi> move) the Sun doth annually move, through the twelve ſigns of the Zodiack, whereof <hi>Leo</hi> is the fifth ſign: in the celeſtial Globe repreſented by a Lion, into the firſt degree of which, the Sun enters on or about the twelfth of <hi>July,</hi> which then bears twenty degrees eleven minutes North decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation from the Aequinexial line. It is never ſeen of us here in <hi>England,</hi> but is fixt in that part of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cliptick; which extends it ſelf over the Iſlands <hi>Cuba, Jamaica</hi> and <hi>Hiſpaniola</hi> in <hi>America.</hi> It is often cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the <hi>Nemean</hi> and <hi>Herculean</hi> Lion, becauſe <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cules</hi> ſlew a Lion in the <hi>Nemean</hi> Forreſt of an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſe and prodigious greatneſs, which the Poets feign to be tranſlated into the ſign <hi>Leo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="15">(15) <hi>Livies</hi> Porch) the <hi>Romans</hi> had certain walks on the ſide of their <hi>Delubrum</hi> which they called <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticus,</hi> and in theſe places it was lawful to trade and confer of worldly occaſions, amongſt which was <hi>Livia Porticus,</hi> or <hi>Livies</hi> Porch, ſo called from <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Livius,</hi> the moſt famous of all the <hi>Roman</hi> Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riographers.</p>
            <p n="16">(16) Where <hi>Belides</hi>) the fifty daughters of <hi>Danaus</hi> ſo called from their Grandfather <hi>Belus:</hi> with whom <hi>Aegiſtus</hi> the Brother to <hi>Danaus,</hi> deſired to marry his fifty Sons, but <hi>Danaus</hi> underſtanding by Oracle that hee ſhould bee ſlain by his Son-in-law, refuſed, yet in the end being compelled thereto by <hi>Aegiſtus,</hi> hee conſummates their marriages, but privately plots with his daughters to murder their fifty husbands well ſteept with Wine in their marriage-beds: all which too too obedient to paternal authority, cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly butchered their wretched busbands, except <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>permnestra,</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:60466:20"/>who out of compaſſion ſpared her Husband <hi>Lynceus,</hi> who ſeeing his Brothers miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable deſtinies, ſlew <hi>Danaus,</hi> and invaded the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the <hi>Argives.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="17">(17) Bewaiſ'd <hi>Adonis</hi>) the Son of <hi>Cynira,</hi> King of <hi>Crprus,</hi> and his daughter <hi>Myrrha,</hi> the darling of <hi>Venus,</hi> who whilſt he was hunting in the <hi>Idalian</hi> For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, was ſlain by a Boar, <hi>Bion. Idylium</hi> 1.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Which I Engliſh,</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Adonis</hi> fair doth on the Mountains lye,</l>
               <l>A white tuſh having peirc'd his white thigh,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Venus</hi> laments whilſt hee expires, black gore</l>
               <l>Flows from his wound.</l>
            </q>
            <p>And a little after.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
               <l>The loving Hounds do howl about the Boy,</l>
               <l>The Mountain-Nymphs lament with <hi>Venus</hi> cry.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Whom <hi>Venus</hi> is ſaid (<hi>Metam.</hi> 10.) to have turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into the flower called an Emony.</p>
            <p n="18">(18) <hi>Niles</hi> Heifer) <hi>Jupiter</hi> being in love with <hi>Io</hi> the daughter of <hi>Anachus,</hi> raviſht her, but being ſurprized by <hi>Juno</hi> to conceal his theft, turned <hi>Io</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a white Cow, which <hi>Juno</hi> begged and commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the cuſtody of <hi>Argus,</hi> who being ſlain by <hi>Jove</hi>'s command, poor <hi>Io</hi> by <hi>Juno</hi> frighted, ran to the banks of the River <hi>Nole,</hi> where <hi>Jove</hi> commiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating her miſ-hap, importuning <hi>Juno,</hi> returned her to her former ſhape. <hi>Metam. lib.</hi> 1.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>De Bove nil ſupereſt, formae niſi candor in illa:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>— nothing now</l>
               <l>But that pure white retains ſhee of the Cow.</l>
            </q>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:60466:21"/>
            <p> Shee after changed her name to <hi>Iſis,</hi> and married <hi>Oſiris</hi> in <hi>Aegypt,</hi> where ſhee was honoured for a God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſſe, and after that was deified at <hi>Rome. Lucan. lib.</hi> 8.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nos in Templa tuam Romana recipimus I ſim.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Into <hi>Romes</hi> Temples wee thy <hi>Iſis</hi> took.</p>
            <p>Where ſhee had a Temple built her in <hi>Campo Martio,</hi> the cauſe of whoſe ruine was this. A young Gentleman called <hi>Mundus,</hi> when hee could by no means entice the chaſte <hi>Paulina</hi> to ſatisfie his luſt, perſwaded the Prieſts of <hi>Iſis</hi> to ſay that they were warned by Oracle, that <hi>Anubius</hi> the God of <hi>Aegypt</hi> deſired the company of the ſaid <hi>Paulina,</hi> ſhe think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Prieſts would not lye, and it being accounted an honour to have to do with a God, was ſtuprated by <hi>Mundus</hi> in the Temple of <hi>Iſis,</hi> under the name of <hi>Anubius,</hi> which hee after confeſſing, the Prieſts were put to death, the Temple beaten down, and the Image of <hi>Iſis</hi> thrown into <hi>Tyber. Lang. Chron.</hi> page 250.</p>
            <p n="19">(19) The <hi>Forums</hi>) there were many <hi>Forums</hi> in <hi>Rome,</hi> of which chiefly three, <hi>Forum Romanum, Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Julium,</hi> and <hi>Forum Auguſtum,</hi> which firſt was chief of all, and by way of excellency called the <hi>Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> as if there were no other <hi>Forum:</hi> Round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout this <hi>Forum Romanum</hi> were built Trades-mens ſhops, here was the <hi>Comitium,</hi> or Hall of Juſtice, the Oratours Pulpit, the Sanctuary, and ſeveral o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtately Edifices.</p>
            <p n="20">(20) <hi>Appias</hi> plac'd) here <hi>Pallas</hi> is meant by <hi>Appias,</hi> but <hi>Venus</hi> and <hi>Pallas</hi> are both called <hi>Appiades,</hi> they had a Temple erected to them upon the <hi>Appian</hi> wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, neer to <hi>Forum Caeſaris.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="21">(21) <hi>Curved Theatres</hi>) places where Plaies and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:60466:21"/>other Shews were publickly acted, in form of a half Moon or Semicircle. <hi>Martial. Spect.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quiequid in Orpheo Rodope Spectaſſe Theatro dicitur, exhibuit, Caeſar, Arena tibi.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>What <hi>Orpheus's</hi> ſaid on <hi>Rodope</hi> to ſee,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Caeſar</hi> the ſtage exhibits unto thee.</l>
            </q>
            <p>There were alſo places called <hi>Amphitheatres,</hi> which were in form of two Theatres joyned toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in a full circle; upon this <hi>Amphitheatre</hi> did Fencers play their prizes, wilde-beaſts were baited, and the Gladiators to exhilerate the Citizens, were miſerably forced to butcher one another.</p>
            <p n="22">(22) <hi>Romulus</hi> deviſedſt) <hi>Numitor</hi> King of the <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banes</hi> in <hi>Italy,</hi> was expelled his Kingdome by his younger Brother <hi>Amulius,</hi> his Son <hi>Lauſus</hi> ſlain, and his Daughter <hi>Sylvia</hi> to prevent all hopes of off-ſpring to <hi>Numitor,</hi> conſecrate by <hi>Amulius</hi> a Prieſt of <hi>Veſta,</hi> but being compreſt by <hi>Mars,</hi> ſhee brought forth <hi>Romulus</hi> and <hi>Remus,</hi> which were by <hi>Amulius</hi> command, together with their Mother thrown in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yber,</hi> but being found by the Shepherd <hi>Fauſtulus,</hi> were preſerved, and nurſed by his wife <hi>Laurentia;</hi> being grown up, they ſlew <hi>Amulius,</hi> and reſtored their Grandfather <hi>Numitor</hi> to his government; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter whoſe death the brothers diſagreeing, fell to arms, by which <hi>Renaus</hi> was ſlain, and <hi>Romulus</hi> alone obtained the Kingdome. <hi>Plut. in Rom.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>ΟΤΙ <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>Rome</hi> (ſaith <hi>Aelian lib.</hi> 7. <hi>var.</hi>) was built by <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> and <hi>Romulus:</hi> but <hi>Florus lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. calls <hi>Romulus</hi> onely the builder of it, hee marked the foundation of the City wall with a plough, drawn by four white horſes, according to <hi>Propert. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>de Urbe Rom.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:60466:22"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quatuor hinc albos Romulus egit equos,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Here <hi>Romulus</hi> did four white horſes drive.</l>
            </q>
            <p>The City being built, <hi>Senatus centum ſeniorum, qui patres dicti ſunt, conſtituitur,</hi> ſaith <hi>Juſt. lib.</hi> 43. Hee conſtituted a Senate, being a hundred of the Elder Citizens, which were called Fathers. Having thus ſtated his Government, hee deſired that his ſouldiers might marry with the <hi>Sabines,</hi> bordering upon them, but was by the <hi>Sabines</hi> reſuſed, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, ſaith <hi>Florus, lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Simulatis equeſtribus, vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines, quae ad ſpectaculum venerant, praeda fuere;</hi> hee deviſed certain ſhows, which when the Virgins came to behold, they were made a prey, and ſeized upon by the ſouldiers.</p>
            <p n="23">(23) <hi>Circus</hi> of a large) the <hi>Romans</hi> had many pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces where they exhibited their plaies unto the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, the moſt remarkable was a great <hi>Circus,</hi> or Shew-place, called <hi>Circus Maximus,</hi> it was a large peece of ground lying neer that part of the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventine</hi> Mount, where <hi>Diana's</hi> Temple ſtood. It was built by <hi>Tarquinius Priſcus,</hi> with divers Galleries called <hi>Fori</hi> round about it, from whence the Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors and Gentlemen of the City did behold the run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning with great horſes at the liſts, the fire-works, tumbling, baiting, and chaſing of wilde-beaſts. The ſeats about this <hi>Circus</hi> were able to contain one hundred and fifty thouſand perſons. There was alſo another <hi>Circus</hi> upon the Hill called <hi>Collis Hortulo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> and this was the <hi>Circus</hi> or Shew-place of the Strumpet <hi>Flora,</hi> who made the people of <hi>Rome</hi> heir to thoſe goods ſhee had gotten by proſtituting her body to young Gentlemen. <hi>God. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Rom. Hiſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="24">(24) <hi>Arena</hi> ſought) the <hi>Amphitheatre,</hi> called <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rena,</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:60466:22"/>from its being ſcattered over with Sand <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o Gravel, that the blood of ſuch as were ſlain in the place, might not make it too ſlippery for the comba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants. <hi>Martial. Spec.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Praeceps Sanguinea dum ſe rotat urſus arena.</q>
            <p n="25">(25) Utmoſt Bounds) the Eaſtern Countries ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected to the <hi>Romanes. Propert. lib.</hi> 3. to <hi>Auguſtus.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>—<hi>parat ultima terra Triumph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tigris &amp; Euphrates ſub tua jure fluent.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>—Remote Lands <hi>Trophies</hi> ſhow,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tigris, Euphrates</hi> in thy Empire flow.</l>
            </q>
            <p n="26">(26) <hi>Craſſus</hi> rejoyce) <hi>Marcus Craſſus</hi> a wealthy <hi>Roman,</hi> who being ſent with an Army againſt the <hi>Parthians,</hi> himſelf, his Son, with eleven <hi>Roman</hi> Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions, were cut off and ſlain, and all their enſigns taken by <hi>Surena</hi> General of the <hi>Parthian</hi> Army, whoſe deaths were fully revenged by <hi>Ventidius,</hi> of whom <hi>Corn. Gall.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Qui nunc Craſſorum manes, direpta<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſigna</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>vindicat Auguſti Caeſaris auſpitiis.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who now for Enſigns loſt, and <hi>Craſſus</hi> ſlain,</l>
               <l>With <hi>Caeſars</hi> fortune, full revenge hath tane.</l>
            </q>
            <p n="27">(27) <hi>Tyrinthius</hi> did) <hi>Hercules</hi> ſo called from the City <hi>Tyrinthia,</hi> where hee was brought up, hee was the Son of <hi>Jupiter,</hi> begotten on <hi>Al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mena,</hi> whilſt hee was in his Cradle, <hi>Juno</hi> ſent two Snakes to deſtroy him, both which hee ſlew: hee was famous for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming many dangerous and Heroick enterprizes; amongſt whoſe many labours I ſhall only mention this, that hee as yet but a youth, compreſt the fifty Daughters of <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſpius</hi> in one night, of whom he got filty Sons called <hi>Theſpiades.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="28">(28) <hi>Thyrſis</hi> fear) a Spear or Javelin bound about with <hi>Ivy,</hi> which was carried by the <hi>Manades</hi> or
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:60466:23"/>Prieſts of <hi>Bacchus</hi> at their Sacrifices which were per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed every third year, in remembrance of his triennial expedition into <hi>India.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="29">(29) Countries Fathers) the Senators which were called <hi>Patres</hi> or Fathers, <hi>Cicero</hi> calls them <hi>Patres con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcripti, quia Romulus, qui Senatores centum, quos ab honore patres appellavit, conſcripſit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="30">(30) Backward fling) the <hi>Parthians</hi> who were moſt excellent at the uſe of darts, with which they would ſeem to flye back on purpoſe to prejudice their enemies.</p>
            <p n="31">(31) <hi>Euphrates, Tygris) Inter Tygrim &amp; Euphra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem tam uber &amp; pinguis ſoli, &amp;c.</hi> betwixt <hi>Tygris</hi> and <hi>Euphrates</hi> (ſaith <hi>Curtius lib.</hi> 5.) the Land is ſo fat and fertil, that the Inhabitants are fain to drive their cattel from paſture for fear they ſhould ſurfeit. <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſt</hi> ſaith, they both <hi>uno fonte manare in Armenia,</hi> flow from one fountain in <hi>Armenia:</hi> but <hi>Curtius</hi> going on, ſaith, Theſe two Rivers have their begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings in the <hi>Armenian</hi> Mountains, where they bee diſtant two thouſand five hundred furlongs, and ſo run forwards, keeping their diſtance till they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach the confines of <hi>Media</hi> and <hi>Gordia,</hi> where they come more neer together, they compaſs round the Country called <hi>Meſopotamia,</hi> and ſo run through the confines of <hi>Babylon,</hi> into the Red-Sea.</p>
            <p n="32">(32) <hi>Paris</hi> the Goddeſſes) the three Goddeſſes <hi>Juno, Pallas</hi> and <hi>Venus,</hi> contending for priority of beauty (occaſioned by a golden Apple, with this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription upon it, This for the faireſt) meeting with <hi>Paris</hi> upon Mount <hi>Ida,</hi> choſe him for the decider of their controverſie, who gave his vote for <hi>Venus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="33">(33) <hi>Menalian</hi> Hound) <hi>Arcadian</hi> Hound, <hi>Mena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> being a very high Hill in that Country.</p>
            <p n="34">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:60466:23"/> (34) <hi>Biblis</hi> who) ſhee fell in love with her own brother <hi>Caunus,</hi> whom ſhee ſo much importuned, that to avoid her, hee fled his Country, whom ſhee purſuing, was by the wood <hi>Nymphs</hi> turned into a fountain. <hi>Met. lib.</hi> 9.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sic lachrymis conſumpta ſuis Phoebeia Byblis</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vertitur in fontem</hi> —</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Phebean Byblis</hi> by her tears conſum'd,</l>
               <l>Into a fountain turn'd. —</l>
            </q>
            <p n="35">(35) <hi>Myrrha</hi>) the Daughter of <hi>Cyniras</hi> King of <hi>Cyprus,</hi> who being enamoured on her Father, and by the aſſiſtance of her Nurſe, obtaining the ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of her luſt, conceived and brought forth <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donis,</hi> for which ſhee was turned into a Tree, from whence diſtils a gum called Myrrh. <hi>Metam. lib.</hi> 10.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Flet tamen &amp; tepidae manant ex arbore guttae:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Eſt honor &amp; lachrymis, ſtillata<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> cortice Myrrha</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nomen herile tenet. —</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Yet ſhee doth weep, the Tree warm drops doth ſpill,</l>
               <l>Honour in tears, Myrrh from the rinds diſtill,</l>
               <l>Which bears her name —</l>
            </q>
            <p n="36">(36) <hi>Gnoſſos</hi> and <hi>Cydon</hi>) the two moſt famous Cities in <hi>Creet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="37">(37) <hi>Paſiphae'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> was the Daughter to <hi>Sol,</hi> and Wife to <hi>Minos</hi> King of <hi>Creet,</hi> who falling in love with a Bull, was by the art of <hi>Daedalus</hi> incloſed in a woodden Cow, covered with a Cow's skin, by which means ſhee injoyed her Bull, betwixt whom was begotten that monſter called the <hi>Minotaure,</hi> which <hi>Daedalus</hi> incloſed in the Labyrinth where hee was ſlain by <hi>Theſeus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="38">(38) Hundred Cities) <hi>Creet</hi> is ſaid to have a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Cities in it, whence it had the Epithet of <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catompolis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="39">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:60466:24"/> (39) Now <hi>Io</hi>) the daughter of <hi>Inachus</hi> whom <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter</hi> turned into a Heifer. <hi>Vide ſupra.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="40">(40) Then <hi>Europa</hi>) ſhee was the daughter of <hi>Age<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor;</hi> with whom <hi>Jove</hi> being in love, transformed himſelf into the ſhape of a Bull, and carried her on his back through the Sea to <hi>Creet,</hi> where reſuming his former ſhape, hee raviſhed her.</p>
            <p n="41">(41) Had <hi>Creſſa</hi> to) <hi>Aerope</hi> called <hi>Creſſa</hi> from <hi>Creet,</hi> who committing adultery with <hi>Thyeſtes</hi> her Husband <hi>Atrens</hi> brother, the children which were born to her by <hi>Thyeſtes,</hi> were ſlain by <hi>Atreus,</hi> and given to their Father to eat, at which horrid wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs the Sun is ſaid to have gone back to the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de Triſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Si non Aeropen frater ſceleratus amaſſet,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Converſos ſolis, non legeremus equos.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Had not <hi>Thyeſtes</hi> for <hi>Aerope</hi> burn'd,</l>
               <l>Wee had not read how <hi>Phebus Carr return'd.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p n="42">(42) <hi>Niſus</hi> daughter) <hi>Scylla,</hi> who ſtole her Fathers purple hair, upon which the fate both of himſelf and Kingdome did depend, and carried it to his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy <hi>Minos,</hi> who beſieged him, and after whom ſhee luſted, but being by him contemned, ſhee at his departure hung on the keel of his ſhip, where ſhe was turned into a Lark, her Father <hi>Niſus</hi> was alſo turned into a Hobby betwixt whom hath ever ſince continued enmity.</p>
            <p n="43">(43) One <hi>Scylla Circes</hi>) the daughter of <hi>Phorcus,</hi> whoſe nether parts the Witch <hi>Circe</hi> changed into grinning doggs, which ſhee not knowing how to reſtore, caſting her ſelf from a precipeece, was turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into a Rock in the <hi>Mamertine</hi>-Sea, betwixt <hi>Scicily</hi> and <hi>Italy,</hi> deſtructive to Mariners.</p>
            <p n="44">(44) <hi>Atrides</hi> from all) <hi>Agamemnon,</hi> ſo called from
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:60466:24"/>his Father <hi>Atreus,</hi> who having by Land avoided a thouſand dangers in that long and deſperate Siege at <hi>Troy;</hi> and afterwards eſcaping a threatning Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack, the Sea being perturbed by an angry <hi>Nep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune,</hi> returning ſafe home was ſlain at a Banquet by his wife <hi>Clitemneſtra,</hi> and her Adulterer <hi>Aegiſtus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="45">(45) The bloody Mother) <hi>Medea,</hi> who by her charms furniſhing <hi>Jaſon</hi> with the golden Fleece, was by him afterward married, to whom ſhee bore two Sons: but hee forſaking her, and marrying <hi>Crëuſa,</hi> daughter to <hi>Creon</hi> King of <hi>Corinth,</hi> the inraged <hi>Medea</hi> conſumed <hi>Crëuſa</hi> in her Pallace with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanted fire, of which fact <hi>Jaſon</hi> coming to take vengeance, ſhee before his face ſtrangled her two Sons, her ſelf flying to <hi>Athens.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="46">(46) <hi>Phaenix Amintors</hi> Son) who by his Mothers advice having to do with his Fathers Concubine, was haunted by the Furies, and flying from his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers preſence, and coming into <hi>Theſſalie,</hi> was made <hi>Achilles</hi> Tutor.</p>
            <p n="47">(47) <hi>Hippolitus</hi> mad horſes) the Son of <hi>Theſeus and Hippolita</hi> the <hi>Amazon,</hi> who conſtantly reſolving to live a ſingle life, in his Fathers abſence, was ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited by his Mother-in-law <hi>Phaedra,</hi> whoſe luſt he repudiating, was by her accuſed to his Father, from whoſe anger flying, hee was torn to peeces by the horſes that drew his Chariot, and was buried in <hi>Diana</hi>'s grove. <hi>Faſt. lib.</hi> 3.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hic latet Hippolitus loris diſcerptus equorum,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Unde nemus nullis illud aditurſequis.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Here lies <hi>Hippolitus</hi> by horſes ſlain:</l>
               <l>Whence no horſe ere came in that grove again.</l>
            </q>
            <p n="48">(48) Doting <hi>Phineus</hi>) the Father of <hi>Orythus,</hi> and <hi>Crambus,</hi> whoſe eyes hee put out; perſwaded there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:60466:25"/>by his ſecond wife <hi>Idaea,</hi> for which his own eyes were after pluckt out by the Furies.</p>
            <p n="49">(49) <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion</hi> when ſad) <hi>Troy</hi> ſo called from <hi>Ilus</hi> the ſoin of <hi>Iros,</hi> which being begirt with <hi>Graecian</hi> ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, and by them reduced to extremities, did ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them more ſorrowful, and conſequently much more watchful and vigilant; but the <hi>Greeks</hi> feigning a departure, left a wooden-horſe, of an immenſe and prodigious greatneſs, whoſe belly was lined with ſouldiers: the <hi>Trojans</hi> joyful of their depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and beleeving this to be the gift of <hi>Minerva,</hi> with Ropes drew the vaſt bulk into the City. <hi>Virg. Aeneid.</hi> 2.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>—circum pueri iunuptae<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> puellae</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sacra canunt, funem<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> manus contingere gaudent.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>—Boyes, Virgins, round about</l>
               <l>Glad touch the Ropes, and ſacred hymns chant out.</l>
            </q>
            <p>In the night the ſouldiers coming out of the horſe, opened the gates to their confederates, which were then returned, ſlew the <hi>Trojans,</hi> and ſet the City on fire.</p>
            <p n="50">(50) And <hi>Pleiades</hi>) the ſeven ſtars feigned to be the ſeven daughters of <hi>Atlas,</hi> their names are, <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectra, Alcione, Celaeno, Maia, Aſterope, Taygete,</hi> and <hi>Merope,</hi> which laſt is hardly to be diſcerned, the reaſon is, becauſe ſix of them married each one a God, but <hi>Merope</hi> married a Mortal, for which ſhee hath ever ſince abſconded her ſelf; they are placed betwixt the mouth of <hi>Taurus,</hi> and the tail of <hi>Aries,</hi> and cauſe Snow in Winter, according to <hi>Lucan. l.</hi> 5.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>—jam ſparſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rat Aemo</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Bruma nives, gelidoq, cadens Atlantis Oly mpo.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>—Now with Winters Snow</l>
               <l>The <hi>Pleiades</hi> did <hi>Aemus</hi> top beſtrow.</l>
            </q>
            <p n="51">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:60466:25"/> (51) <hi>Goat</hi> is ſwallowed) <hi>Capricornus</hi> or the <hi>Goat</hi> is one of the twelve ſings, and the watery <hi>Tropick,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the fartheſt limit of the Sun's courſe South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, the <hi>Aequator;</hi> which entring makes the Winter quarter, and turns his courſe again to the <hi>Aequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxial.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="52">(52) <hi>Allia</hi> before) a River flowing from the <hi>Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctumentan</hi> Mountains in <hi>Hetruria,</hi> where the <hi>Romans</hi> were overthrown and ſlain by <hi>Brennus,</hi> Captain of the <hi>Gauls:</hi> hence they uſed to call an unlucky day <hi>dies allienſis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="53">(53) Feaſt begin) the Feaſt of the Paſſcover which the <hi>Jews</hi> kept on the fourteenth of the month <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſan,</hi> which month containeth part of <hi>March,</hi> and part of <hi>April,</hi> by us now called <hi>Eaſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="54">(54) Man of <hi>Paleſtina</hi>) <hi>Moſes,</hi> by whoſe mouth the Lord commanded the Feaſt of Paſſeover ſhould be kept in remembrance of his paſſing over the houſes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and deſtroying the firſt-born of <hi>Aegypt; Ovid</hi> calls him the man of <hi>Paleſtina,</hi> becauſe hee died on Mount <hi>Abarim,</hi> which is a Hill, (ſaith <hi>Joſephus. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 8. <hi>Antiq.</hi>) neer <hi>Jericho, Pale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtina</hi> containeth <hi>Judea, Samaria,</hi> and <hi>Gali<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ea.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="55">(55) Kings requeſt) <hi>Achilles</hi> at the humble requeſt of King <hi>Priam,</hi> did reſtore the dead body of <hi>Hector</hi> whom hee had ſlain, and dragged his coarſe in Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph. <hi>Hom. Iliad.</hi> 24.</p>
            <p n="56">(56) A Letter won) <hi>Cydippe,</hi> a noble young La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of tranſcendent beauty, whom young <hi>Acontius</hi> being in love with, and fearing a repulſe, becauſe hee both in birth and fortune was inferiour to her, deviſed this means to obtain her; as ſhee ſate in <hi>Diana</hi>'s Temple, hee threw an Apple with this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription. <hi>Ariſtaen. lib.</hi> 1.</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:60466:26"/>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>By <hi>Diana</hi> I will marry <hi>Acontius.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>Which ſhee taking up and reading, at unawares promiſed her ſelf to him, after which time whenſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſhee went about to marry another, ſhee was caſt into a dangerous diſeaſe by the offended God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſs <hi>Diana,</hi> which her friends at laſt underſtanding, married her to <hi>Acontius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="57">(57) <hi>Pergamus</hi> late) a high Tower in <hi>Troy</hi> from which the whole City is called <hi>Pergamus,</hi> which City (ſaith <hi>Dares de excidio Tro.</hi>) after ten years, eight months, and twelve daies ſiege was taken by the <hi>Grecians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="58">(58) Which <hi>Cybil</hi> did) There were (ſaith <hi>Aelian. lib.</hi> 12. <hi>Nar.</hi>) ten <hi>Cybils,</hi> one of which was <hi>Phrygian Cybil,</hi> ſhee firſt invented the Tabor and Pipe, the Cymbal and Timbrel: ſhee was called <hi>Mater Deo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> or the Mother of the Gods, and was worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped at <hi>Berecynthia,</hi> a Town in <hi>Phrygia,</hi> of which <hi>Catul.</hi> 64.</p>
            <q>
               <l>—<hi>Sequimini</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Phrygiam ad domum: Cybelles Phrygia ad nemora deae,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ubi Cymbalum ſonat vox, ubi Tympanareboant.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>—Follow</l>
               <l>To th' <hi>Phrygian</hi> Grotto, Goddeſſe <hi>Cybils</hi> ſhade,</l>
               <l>Where Cymbals ſound, and where the Timbrels plaid.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Her Prieſts were enjoyned to geld themſelves with a Fiſh-ſhell, whoſe manner of worſhip was thus: A <hi>Phrygian</hi> man and woman apparrelled in particoloured garments after the manner of their Country, carried their Goddeſs Picture about, beat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their breaſts, and miſerably howling, after whom followed others playing on Tabors, Pipes, and Cymbals.</p>
            <p n="59">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:60466:26"/> (59) <hi>Liber</hi> ſtiles mee) <hi>Bacchus</hi> ſo called, either be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe (as <hi>Plutarch</hi> ſaies) <hi>pro Boeotiae libertate pugna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit,</hi> hee fought for the liberty of <hi>Boeotia,</hi> or becauſe with Wine hee exhilerates men, and frees them from ſolicitous cares.</p>
            <p n="60">(60) Poor <hi>Ariadne</hi>) the daughter of <hi>Minos</hi> and <hi>Paſiphae</hi> whom <hi>Theſeus</hi> taking out of <hi>Creet</hi> forſook: leaving her diſconſolate on the ſhoar of <hi>Dia,</hi> an Iſland in the <hi>Aegean</hi>-Sea, one of the <hi>Cyclades,</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whom being gone, ſhee thus complains in <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullus;</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Siccine me patriis abvectam, perfide, ab oris,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Perfide deſerto liquiſti in littore Theſeu?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Siccine diſcedens, &amp;c.</hi> Which I tranſlate.</l>
                  <l>Flaſe <hi>Theſens,</hi> was I from my Country took</l>
                  <l>Thus on a forein ſhoar to be forſook?</l>
                  <l>Thus, all the Gods neglected, dar 'ſt thou go,</l>
                  <l>Thy perjuries attending on thee ſo?</l>
                  <l>Alas! could nought avert thy cruel mind,</l>
                  <l>My ſorrow in thee no compaſſion finde?</l>
                  <l>Thy cruel breaſt not pity my eſtate?</l>
                  <l>Ah! thou before ne're mention'd ſuch a fate.</l>
                  <l>Thou bid'ſt mee never look for ſuch a thing,</l>
                  <l>But joyful wedlock, and wiſht Hymen ſing.</l>
                  <l>Which of no force ſleight winds away do bear:</l>
                  <l>Let women ne're beleeve men when they ſwear.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p n="61">(61) Loe <hi>Mimalonides</hi>) the <hi>Menades,</hi> or furious Prieſts of <hi>Bacchus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="62">(62) Old <hi>Silenns</hi>) the Foſter Father to <hi>Bacchus,</hi> who was alwaies wont to ride upon an Aſs.</p>
            <p n="63">(63) The God) <hi>Bacchus,</hi> the inventer of Wine, who by the <hi>Thracians</hi> was worſhipped for a God, it being the cuſtome of old amongſt the Heathens to deifie the inventers of things.</p>
            <p n="64">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:60466:27"/> (64) Others <hi>Evohe ſed</hi>) an exclamatory noiſe which the <hi>Menades</hi> were wont to uſe in praiſe of <hi>Bacchus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="65">(65) <hi>Nyctelius) Bacchus,</hi> ſo called from his ſeaſts, which were performed in the night. <hi>Aeneid.</hi> 4.</p>
            <q>— <hi>Nocturnuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> vocat clamore Cytheron.</hi>
            </q>
            <p n="66">(66) <hi>Juno</hi>'s Bird) the Peacock, whoſe train ſhee beautified with her heardſman <hi>Argus</hi> his hundred eyes. <hi>Metam. lib.</hi> 1.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Excipit hos, volucriſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſua Saturnia pennis</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Collocat, &amp; gemmis caudam ſtellantibus implet.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Yet that thoſe ſtarry Jewels might remain,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Saturnia</hi> fixt them in her Peacocks train.</l>
            </q>
            <p n="67">(67) <hi>Phoebe</hi> and her) <hi>Phoebe</hi> and her ſiſter <hi>Elaira</hi> the daughters of <hi>Leucippus,</hi> raviſhed by <hi>Caſtor</hi> and <hi>Pollux.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="68">(68) The <hi>Aemonian) Achilles</hi> ſo called from his Country of <hi>Theſſaly:</hi> the <hi>Scyrian</hi> is meant by <hi>Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damia</hi> daughter to <hi>Lycomedes</hi> King of <hi>Scyros,</hi> an Iſle in the <hi>Aegean</hi>-Sea, on whom <hi>Achilles</hi> habited in womens apparel, begot <hi>Pyrrhus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="69">(69) Promiſe gave) <hi>Hellen</hi> the faireſt of all <hi>Greece,</hi> whom <hi>Venus</hi> promiſed to <hi>Paris,</hi> which being given, was the ruine of not onely himſelf, but all <hi>Troy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="70">(70) <hi>Daphnis</hi> lookt) a youth of <hi>Sicily,</hi> the inventer of Bucolick verſe, in love with the Nymph <hi>Nais.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="71">(71) <hi>Pirithous</hi> from) the ſon of <hi>Ixiox</hi> joyned in a firm league of friendſhip with <hi>Theſeus,</hi> whoſe wife <hi>Phaedra</hi> ſoliciting him to luſt, hee refuſed out of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to his friend.</p>
            <p n="72">(72) <hi>Hermione Pylades) Pylades</hi> was ſo faithful a friend to <hi>Orestes,</hi> that when <hi>Theas</hi> King of <hi>Taurica</hi> had deſigned to ſacrifice <hi>Oreſtes,</hi> hee affirmed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be <hi>Oreſtes,</hi> that hee might dye for his friend:
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:60466:27"/>whoſe wife <hi>Hermione</hi> hee entirely loved, becauſe ſhe ſo nearly related to his friend.</p>
            <p n="73">(73) <hi>Proteus</hi> uſed) a Sea-deity, the Son of <hi>Ocea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> and <hi>Thetis,</hi> the Poets feign that hee could tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form himſelf into what ſhape hee pleaſed. <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam.</hi> 8.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nam modo te Juvenem, modo te videre Leonem,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nunc violentus aper, nunc quem tetigiſſe timerent</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Anguis eras, modo te faciebant cornuatanrum,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sepe lapis poteras, arbor quo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſaepe videri.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>Which I engliſh,</p>
            <q>
               <l>One while a youth, a Lion then appear,</l>
               <l>Now a fierce Boar, a Snake now, which they fear</l>
               <l>To touch, now horns ſhew thee a Bull to bee:</l>
               <l>A Stone th' art oft, and oft-times turn'd a tree.</l>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="book">
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:60466:28"/>
            <head>The ſecond Book OF <hi>Publius Ovidius Naſo De Arte Amandi.</hi>
            </head>
            <argument>
               <lg>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <l>Daedalus <hi>flight from</hi> Creet, Icarus <hi>fate,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>No love can</hi> Philtra<hi>'s, or fond charms create.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Rude language fits not love. Lady's must find</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Subſequient ſervants, neither ſtorms nor wind</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A Lover muſt retard, how to commend</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A Lady's imperfections, and pretend</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Her faults are handſome: make her think them ſo.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>All hazards for her ſake to undergo.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Loves ſecrets muſt be kept ſo,</hi> Ovid <hi>ſaies,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ending this ſecond Book with his ſelf-praiſe.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </argument>
            <lg>
               <l>SIng (1) <hi>Iô Paean,</hi> twice <hi>Iô Paean</hi> ſing,</l>
               <l>My wiſht-for prey caught in my nets I bring.</l>
               <l>Bayes to my Verſe the Jovial Lover deems,</l>
               <l>And mee before (2) th' <hi>Meonian</hi> man eſteems.</l>
               <l>Such was the (3) <hi>Priameian</hi> that prevail'd,</l>
               <l>And with his fair prize from <hi>Amyclae</hi> ſail'd.</l>
               <l>Such was the man that in his Chariot run,</l>
               <l>And with the courſe fair (4) <hi>Hippodamia</hi> won.</l>
               <l>Whither ſo faſt young man? thy ſhip doth ſteer</l>
               <l>Ith' midſt of th' Sea, no wiſht-for Haven neer.</l>
               <l>'Tis not enough to finde thy Miſtreſs, ſhee</l>
               <l>Py Art is got, muſt ſo continued be.</l>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:60466:28"/>
               <l>It is as much to keep, as to acquire,</l>
               <l>In that is danger, this muſt Art inſpire.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Venus</hi> and <hi>Cupid</hi> ſmile, if ever now,</l>
               <l>And thou <hi>Erato</hi> to whom Lovers bow.</l>
               <l>Great things Ile ſing, how love may conſtant prove,</l>
               <l>And th' Boy which all about the world doth rove,</l>
               <l>Hee's light, hath wings wherewith the Air to cut</l>
               <l>And bounds to them, 'tis very hard to put.</l>
               <l>Though (5) <hi>Minos</hi> do all means of ſcape deny</l>
               <l>A deſperate way <hi>Daedalus</hi> found ith' Skye.</l>
               <l>When hee included had within his frame</l>
               <l>The <hi>Semiox</hi> and Man, the Mothers ſhame.</l>
               <l>Hee ſaid juſt <hi>Minos</hi> my exile prefer</l>
               <l>Let my own Country theſe my bones inter,</l>
               <l>Driven from thence by a ſad fate, where I</l>
               <l>Could never live, O ſuffer mee to dye.</l>
               <l>O let this Boy return, though I've no grace,</l>
               <l>If not the Boy, pity my aged face.</l>
               <l>Such words he ſpoke, ſuch might he ſpeak and more,</l>
               <l>But no return could from the King procure.</l>
               <l>Which when hee ſees, now <hi>Daedalns,</hi> ſaith hee,</l>
               <l>Th' haſt matter for thy ingenuity.</l>
               <l>Both Sea and Land <hi>Minos</hi> poſſeſſeth ſo,</l>
               <l>There is no way by Sea-or Land to go.</l>
               <l>Let's flye through Aire that only open lyes,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Jove</hi> pardon my preſumptuous enterprize.</l>
               <l>I don't affect to touch the Starry Seat,</l>
               <l>For mee to flye there is no way but that.</l>
               <l>Let mee paſs <hi>Styx,</hi> through <hi>Styx</hi> my journey take,</l>
               <l>For that my nature will immortal make.</l>
               <l>Diſtreſs exiles our wills, who'd think men might</l>
               <l>Through the <hi>Aërial</hi> paſſages take flight.</l>
               <l>Hee doth the wings of Birds in order place,</l>
               <l>Hee doth his work with packthread enterlace.</l>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:60466:29"/>
               <l>The quills in fire-ſoftened wax were wrought:</l>
               <l>Thus this new work was to perfection brought.</l>
               <l>The Boy did touch the wax, at th'feathers ſmile,</l>
               <l>Ignorant they were made for's ſhoulder, while</l>
               <l>His Father ſaies, wee with theſe ſayls muſt try,</l>
               <l>To gain our Country, and from <hi>Minos</hi> flye.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Minos</hi> all paſſages but the Aire hath ſhut,</l>
               <l>By my invention wee that Air muſt cur.</l>
               <l>Neither (6) <hi>Boôtis,</hi> nor <hi>Orion</hi> bold,</l>
               <l>Or the <hi>Tegean</hi> Maid, do thou behold.</l>
               <l>Follow mee with thy wings, before thee I</l>
               <l>Will go, keep cloſe and thou ſhalt ſafely fly.</l>
               <l>If wee too neer unto the Sun ſhall ſoar,</l>
               <l>Our wings will melt, and not the heat endure.</l>
               <l>Or if too low, and neer the Sea wee toyl,</l>
               <l>The humid vapours will our feathers ſpoil.</l>
               <l>Keep in the midſt O Son, the winds beware,</l>
               <l>Strike proſprous ſails which way ſo'ere they bear.</l>
               <l>Whilſt hee doth fit them, hee inſtructs the Boy,</l>
               <l>Juſt as old Birds do teach the young to fly.</l>
               <l>Then his own plumes hee on his ſhoulder tyes,</l>
               <l>And trembling doth for th' flight his body poize.</l>
               <l>Ready to ſoar, juſt now hee kiſt his Boy,</l>
               <l>And let a Fathers tear ſteal from his eye.</l>
               <l>There was a little hill did over-look</l>
               <l>The Plain, from which a deſperate flight both took.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Daedalus</hi> flyes, yet evermore looks back,</l>
               <l>And flaggs, that <hi>Icarus</hi> may overtake.</l>
               <l>Now the new Journey pleaſeth, fear's put by,</l>
               <l>And daring <hi>Icarus</hi> doth boldly fly.</l>
               <l>Theſe were eſpy'd by Anglers, who forſook</l>
               <l>Their Rods, themſelves to ſpeedy flight betook.</l>
               <l>(7) <hi>Samos</hi> and <hi>Naxos</hi> did with <hi>Paros</hi> ſtand,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Delos</hi> the (8) <hi>Clarians</hi> love on their left hand.</l>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:60466:29"/>
               <l>At th' right (9) <hi>Lebinthus</hi> and <hi>Calydna</hi>'s wood,</l>
               <l>With Ponds well ſtor'd <hi>Aſtipalia</hi> ſtood.</l>
               <l>When the raſh Boy another way will chuſe,</l>
               <l>Soares up, and quickly doth his father looſe.</l>
               <l>Wax melts, and threeds grow ſlack, a God too nigh:</l>
               <l>Nor longer with the wind his arms can fly.</l>
               <l>Amaz'd, from high into the deep looks where</l>
               <l>Black night was riſen to augment his fear.</l>
               <l>The wax conſum'd, hee his bare arms doth ſhake,</l>
               <l>Trembling, hath nothing whereon hold to take.</l>
               <l>Hee fell, crying Father, Father, as hee went,</l>
               <l>And there the water did his ſpeech prevent.</l>
               <l>Th' unhappy Father <hi>Icarus</hi> doth cry,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Icarus,</hi> where ar't, ſaith hee, where doſt thou fly?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Icarus?</hi> and then ith' waves his wings hee ſpies,</l>
               <l>His name ith' Sea, ith' earth his body lyes.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Minos</hi> could not a Mortals flight reſtrain,</l>
               <l>Yet I will make a flying God remain.</l>
               <l>Hee that doth uſe (10) <hi>Aemonian</hi> Arts is gull'd,</l>
               <l>Or gives what hee from a Colts fore-head pull'd.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Medea</hi>'s herbs will not make love keep warm,</l>
               <l>Nor poiſons mixt drunk with a Magick charm.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Jaſon</hi> with <hi>Phaſias, Ulyſſes</hi> ſhould remain</l>
               <l>With (11) <hi>Circe,</hi> if that ſpells could love obtain.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Philtra</hi>'s to Maids it is in vain to give,</l>
               <l>It wrongs their ſence, doth them to madneſs drive.</l>
               <l>Such wickedneſs abhor, indearing be</l>
               <l>More than thy beauty, 'twill advantage thee.</l>
               <l>Though lovely <hi>Nireus</hi> do old <hi>Homer</hi> pleaſe,</l>
               <l>And (12) <hi>Hylas</hi> raviſht by the <hi>Naides.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To keep your Miſtreſs, don't your ſelf admire,</l>
               <l>The gifts of Nature thoſe of Art require.</l>
               <l>Beauty is frail, in time it will decay,</l>
               <l>And with our youthful age it flyes away.</l>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:60466:30"/>
               <l>Nor Violets, nor Lillies ever grow:</l>
               <l>Nor do pluckt Roſes alwaies lovely ſhow.</l>
               <l>Fair youth, gray hairs are coming on thee now,</l>
               <l>And wrinckles will thy face with furrows plow.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Frame a good mind, the form of that maintain,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Which will unto thy utmoſt day remain.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To deck your neck with Jewels, don't deſire:</l>
               <l>Two languages at leaſt you muſt acquire.</l>
               <l>Not fair, but eloquent <hi>Ulyſſes</hi> was,</l>
               <l>And yet the Sea-Nymphs would his love imbrace,</l>
               <l>At his return how did (13) <hi>Calypſo</hi> wail?</l>
               <l>And ever made the Sea unfit for ſail.</l>
               <l>Shee oft-times would intreat him to relate,</l>
               <l>Becauſe hee ſpoke ſo well, the <hi>Trojan</hi> fate.</l>
               <l>O'th' ſhoar they ſtood, where fair <hi>Calypſo</hi> would</l>
               <l>have the <hi>Odryſians</hi> bloody acts retold.</l>
               <l>Hee had a ſlender Rod in his right hand,</l>
               <l>And what ſhee asks, hee draws upon the Sand.</l>
               <l>This's <hi>Troy,</hi> ſaith he, which mighty walls incloſe,</l>
               <l>This is (14) <hi>Simois,</hi> theſe my tents ſuppoſe.</l>
               <l>This is the field where (15) <hi>Dolons</hi> death was wrought</l>
               <l>Whilſt th'watch expects th'<hi>Aemonian</hi> horſes brought.</l>
               <l>There ſtood <hi>Sithonian Rheſus</hi> tents, that night</l>
               <l>I came with th' captive horſes from the fight.</l>
               <l>More hee would have drawn out when ſuddenly</l>
               <l>A wave doth waſh away both tents and <hi>Troy.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then th' Goddeſs ſaies, what hope for thee is found?</l>
               <l>Doſt ſee what mighty names the Sea hath drown'd?</l>
               <l>Therefore, whoe're you be, do not begin</l>
               <l>To truſt to ſhapes, have Subſtances within.</l>
               <l>A milde behaviour very much will take,</l>
               <l>When boiſterouſneſs, hate and diſſontion make,</l>
               <l>Wee loathe the Kite, that doth ſharp talons keep,</l>
               <l>And Wolves, that uſe to fright the fearful ſheep.</l>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:60466:30"/>
               <l>The gentle Swallow no man ſtrives to take,</l>
               <l>But in what place ſhee will, her neſt may make.</l>
               <l>Hence all contentions, hence a bitter tongue,</l>
               <l>Soft and ſweet language doth to love belong.</l>
               <l>The wives their husbands, husbands wives forſake</l>
               <l>Through ſtrife, things ill at one another take.</l>
               <l>Wives have a gift to chide, they'l not forbear:</l>
               <l>None but ſweet language let your Miſtreſs hear.</l>
               <l>Law hath not you unto one bed confin'd,</l>
               <l>But doth allow your love reward to finde.</l>
               <l>Court her with praiſes, ſuch do pleaſe her ear:</l>
               <l>Then ſhee'l bee alwaies glad when you appear.</l>
               <l>To rich men I need not my skill impart,</l>
               <l>They have no need of mee, nor of my Art.</l>
               <l>Hee's witty that ſaies take it, that ſame man</l>
               <l>Will do much more than my invention can.</l>
               <l>Poor Lovers I inſtruct, my ſelf lov'd poor,</l>
               <l>When gifts I could not, words I gave her ſtore.</l>
               <l>Let ſuch love wiſely, how to ſpeak take care,</l>
               <l>Such things as rich men will not, they muſt bear.</l>
               <l>I angry, once my Miſtreſs locks did move,</l>
               <l>How many daies that anger loſt her love!</l>
               <l>I don't beleeve't, but yet ſhee ſaid that I</l>
               <l>Did tear her Gown, made mee a new one buy.</l>
               <l>If you bee wiſe, example take by mee,</l>
               <l>Avoid offences that ſo coſtly be.</l>
               <l>Peace with your Miſtreſs, war with <hi>Parthians</hi> make,</l>
               <l>Sport or ſpeak any thing you think will take.</l>
               <l>If you your Miſtreſs ſtrange, uneaſie finde,</l>
               <l>Perſevere ſtill, in time ſhee will prove kinde.</l>
               <l>Crook'd bows will bend, if leiſurely you try,</l>
               <l>But if too raſh, they will in peeces fly.</l>
               <l>With eaſie ſtroaks a River may be croſt,</l>
               <l>But if you ſtrike too faſt, ith' ſtream y'are loſt.</l>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:60466:31"/>
               <l>Lions and Tygers are made tame by wit,</l>
               <l>Steers by degrees will to the yoak ſubmit.</l>
               <l>Who love did more than (16) <hi>Atalanta</hi> ſhun?</l>
               <l>Yet by the merits of a man was won.</l>
               <l>'Tis ſaid (17) <hi>Melanion</hi> 'cauſe his Wench detain'd</l>
               <l>Her promiſ'd love under a tree complain'd.</l>
               <l>Oft on his ſhoulders hee his Nets would bear,</l>
               <l>Oft in the Cruel Boar would fix his Spear.</l>
               <l>Wounded hee ſees <hi>Hylaeus</hi> Bow well ſtrung,</l>
               <l>Better known whilſt it did to him belong.</l>
               <l>I do not bid haunt the <hi>Menalian</hi> grove,</l>
               <l>Nor with your Nets upon your ſhoulders rove.</l>
               <l>Nor do I bid you with your breaſt a Dart</l>
               <l>Oppoſe, 'tis eaſie to perform my Art.</l>
               <l>To overcome, you muſt not her withſtand:</l>
               <l>Bee ſure to act what parts ſhee ſhall command.</l>
               <l>What ſhee rejects, reject, if ſhee, allow;</l>
               <l>What ſhee ſaies, ſay, what ſhee denies, do thou;</l>
               <l>If ſhee laugh, laugh; but if ſhee weep, weep too:</l>
               <l>As ſhee her looks diſpoſeth, ſo muſt you.</l>
               <l>If any time ſhee play with you at (18) Dice,</l>
               <l>You muſt throw ill, let her's be her own choice.</l>
               <l>Play for no more than you would gladly loſe,</l>
               <l>And then let yours be alwaies loſing throws.</l>
               <l>Or if at cheſs your man might ſafely paſs,</l>
               <l>Let him be taken by his (19) foe of glaſs.</l>
               <l>Carry her fan in one hand all along,</l>
               <l>And with the other lead her through the throng.</l>
               <l>Bee not aſham'd to hand her to (20) her bed,</l>
               <l>Set by, or reach her ſhooes, as ſhee has need.</l>
               <l>Oft-times you may, then do not fearful ſtand,</l>
               <l>But in your Miſtreſs boſome warm your hand.</l>
               <l>Think it not baſe (for though it bee 'twill pleaſe)</l>
               <l>By holding of her glaſs, her arms to eaſe.</l>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:60466:31"/>
               <l>Hee that in peeces did the Serpents tear,</l>
               <l>That Heaven deſerv'd, which he (21) before did bear,</l>
               <l>A basket 'mongſt th' <hi>Ionian</hi> Maids did uſe,</l>
               <l>And for to card their wooll, would not refuſe.</l>
               <l>Theſe for his Miſtreſs did the <hi>Horoe</hi> do,</l>
               <l>And will you ſcorn ſuch things to undergo?</l>
               <l>If ſhee ſay come to th' <hi>Forum,</hi> her obey,</l>
               <l>Go ſooner than ſhee bids, and longer ſtay.</l>
               <l>If ſhee ſay to you, go, meet ſuch a one,</l>
               <l>Haſte, other things deſer, be ſtay'd by none.</l>
               <l>If in the night ſhee from a banquet come</l>
               <l>And call you, you muſt wait upon her home.</l>
               <l>If ſhee ith' Country call, love hates the ſlow,</l>
               <l>On foct, if th'haſt no Coach nor horſes, go.</l>
               <l>Neither let Summers heat your journey ſtay,</l>
               <l>Nor Winters Snow driven along the way.</l>
               <l>Love is a kinde of war, cowards away,</l>
               <l>Loves Enſigns are not born by ſuch as they.</l>
               <l>Night, winter, long waies, dolorous events,</l>
               <l>All labour's undergone in theſe ſoft tents.</l>
               <l>Oft ſtorms from high pitcht clouds on you ſhall fly,</l>
               <l>Oft you muſt cold upon the bare ground lye.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cynthius</hi> is ſaid <hi>Admetus</hi> beaſts to keep,</l>
               <l>That hee each night in a poor Coat did ſleep.</l>
               <l>What <hi>Phoebus</hi> taught who will not; leave diſdain</l>
               <l>Whoe're you bee that would have love remain.</l>
               <l>If to approach her, thou no ſafe way haſt,</l>
               <l>With an oppoſing lock the door made faſt.</l>
               <l>Your ſelf down to her from the wide roof let,</l>
               <l>Or elſe a paſſage through ſome window get.</l>
               <l>Shee will reioyce to ſee you undertake,</l>
               <l>(Sure marks of love) all dangers for her ſake.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Leander</hi> oft without his Wench could bee,</l>
               <l>Yet hee did ſwimm for her his Love to ſee.</l>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:60466:32"/>
               <l>Let not the ſervants ſhame their place to know,</l>
               <l>Nor be aſham'd great with thoſe Maids to grow.</l>
               <l>Each by her name (no loſs to you) ſalute,</l>
               <l>And humbly beg them to aſſiſt your ſute.</l>
               <l>You muſt, as your eſtate allows, to all</l>
               <l>Her ſervants at ſome times be liberal.</l>
               <l>Reward that Maid to whom ſhee doth confeſs,</l>
               <l>Whoſe hand doth her in the <hi>French</hi> garment dreſs.</l>
               <l>Truſt mee, make all of them your own, but more</l>
               <l>Eſpecially gainhim that keeps the door.</l>
               <l>I do not bid you coſtly gifts preſent,</l>
               <l>But ſleight ones, yet ſuch as will her content.</l>
               <l>When Corn is ripe, and Orchards ponderous are,</l>
               <l>Then let a Boy fruit in a Basket bear.</l>
               <l>Say thoſe unto you out of th' Country came,</l>
               <l>Although by th' way for her you bought the ſame.</l>
               <l>Carry her Grapes in cluſters, that do ſwell,</l>
               <l>Or Nuts which <hi>Amarillis</hi> lov'd ſo well.</l>
               <l>A Throſſel ſent, or a green Chaplet will</l>
               <l>Show, that to her your love is laſting ſtill.</l>
               <l>Rich Gifts conſume men, which old age will rue,</l>
               <l>They that are too profuſe themſelves undo.</l>
               <l>To write her verſes I would teach you how,</l>
               <l>But they (alas) are diſ-eſteemed now.</l>
               <l>Verſe they commend, but Riches they reſpect,</l>
               <l>Rich men they will, though ne're ſuch clowns, accept.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Now is the golden age, honours are gain'd,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And Ladies loves, by heeps of gold obtain'd.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>If <hi>Homer</hi> ſhould, attended by his Muſe,</l>
               <l>Come hither without Gold, they'd him reſuſe.</l>
               <l>Some Ladies learned are, although but few,</l>
               <l>And others that are not, would ſeem ſo too.</l>
               <l>Let your verſe both extol, then alſo will</l>
               <l>The Reader with kind words commend your skill.</l>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:60466:32"/>
               <l>Each of thoſe Ladies will your verſe eſteem,</l>
               <l>And it to ſuch may a ſleight preſent ſeem.</l>
               <l>You may contrive for your advantage ſo,</l>
               <l>That what you would do, ſhee injoyn you to.</l>
               <l>If you are bound to ſet a ſervant free,</l>
               <l>Let him from her requeſt his liberty.</l>
               <l>If you releaſe him, ſhee's oblig'd to you,</l>
               <l>For granting that which you were bound to do.</l>
               <l>She hath the praiſe, you the advantage, uſe,</l>
               <l>Contrive that ſhe may have, and you not loſe.</l>
               <l>Whoe're would have his Miſtreſs love remain,</l>
               <l>That he is raviſht at her looks muſt feign.</l>
               <l>If ſhe wear <hi>Tyrian, Tyrian</hi> wear commend,</l>
               <l>If <hi>Coan,</hi> that becomes her beſt pretend.</l>
               <l>If cloath of Gold, ſay you that wear beſt love,</l>
               <l>If ſhe have courſer on, courſer approve.</l>
               <l>If bare-neckt, ſay ſhe ſets your heart on fire:</l>
               <l>But that ſhe take no cold thereby deſire.</l>
               <l>Is her hair parted, praiſe the parted hair,</l>
               <l>And ſay, the locks that ſhe hath curl'd are fair.</l>
               <l>Her dancing praiſe, her ſinging voice admire:</l>
               <l>Complain when her Air-ſweetning notes expire.</l>
               <l>Honour that company, and that thing commend</l>
               <l>Which ſhe loves, let your words on hers depend.</l>
               <l>If ſhe more cruel than <hi>Meduſa</hi> were,</l>
               <l>Such praiſes will to love incline her ear.</l>
               <l>Yet do not counterfeit apparently,</l>
               <l>Nor let your countenance your words deny.</l>
               <l>Hid Art will profit, ſham'd if ſeen it makes,</l>
               <l>And future credit from your language takes.</l>
               <l>In <hi>Autumn</hi> when the year is faireſt found,</l>
               <l>And the full Grape doth with red Wine abound:</l>
               <l>When th'ſeaſons ſometimes hot, and ſometimes cold,</l>
               <l>Bodies do not in conſtant temper hold.</l>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:60466:33"/>
               <l>May ſhe be well; but if upon her bed,</l>
               <l>She lye by th' unkinde Aire diſtempered,</l>
               <l>Then manifeſt your love to her, then ſow</l>
               <l>What you may after with your ſickle mow.</l>
               <l>No loathe in you of her diſeaſe be found,</l>
               <l>What ſhee would have with your own hands com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound.</l>
               <l>Before her weep, to kiſs conceive no fears,</l>
               <l>And let her dry lips drink your dropping tears;</l>
               <l>Promiſe her any thing in that eſtate,</l>
               <l>To make her merry pretty dreams relate.</l>
               <l>Make the old woman that doth dreſs the rooms,</l>
               <l>Burn in her trembling hand, ſome choice perſumes.</l>
               <l>And let your grateful care in all things go,</l>
               <l>Many their Miſtreſs beds have come to ſo.</l>
               <l>Hate for ſuch offices you will not gain,</l>
               <l>Then with ſedulity 'bout her remain.</l>
               <l>No meats or broths give her that bitter are,</l>
               <l>But may your rival for her ſuch prepare;</l>
               <l>Thoſe ſails with which you from the ſhore do put,</l>
               <l>Muſt be tane down when deeper Seas you cut.</l>
               <l>By exerciſe love ſtrengthens when 'tis young,</l>
               <l>And if it's cheriſht, will in time grow ſtrong.</l>
               <l>You fear the Bull with which a Calf y'have plaid,</l>
               <l>You under th' tree which was a ſprig are laid.</l>
               <l>A River ſmall at firſt, and bigger grows,</l>
               <l>Receiving water that into it flows.</l>
               <l>Inure your ſelf to any thing that will</l>
               <l>Obtain your Miſtreſs, be it ne're ſo ill.</l>
               <l>Incline her ear, be alwaies in her ſight,</l>
               <l>Preſent your ſelf before her day and night.</l>
               <l>But when your language findes beleef in her,</l>
               <l>Your frequent viſits for ſome time defer.</l>
               <l>A field made fallow, will afford more grain,</l>
               <l>So ground long parcht drinks up deſcending Rain.</l>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:60466:33"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Phyllis</hi> indifferently did <hi>Demophoon</hi> love,</l>
               <l>Until ith' Sea ſhe ſaw his ſails to move.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Penelope</hi> laments <hi>Ulyſſes</hi> ſtay,</l>
               <l>So for (22) <hi>Phyllacides, Laodamia.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Abſent not long, leſt time ſhould cure her pain,</l>
               <l>Make her old Loves forget, new entertain.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hellen</hi> (her husband abſent) could not reſt</l>
               <l>Alone, but lodg'd in a warm ſtrangers breaſt.</l>
               <l>What madneſs <hi>Menalaus</hi> was't to leave</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sparta,</hi> whilſt ſtrangers did thy wife receive.</l>
               <l>Who truſts a Dove unto a Hauk to keep,</l>
               <l>Or to a Mountain Woolf a flock of Sheep?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hellen</hi> no crime, no crime did <hi>Paris</hi> know,</l>
               <l>He did what thou or any elſe would do.</l>
               <l>Thou by occaſion didſt thy ſelf abuſe,</l>
               <l>For whoſe advice but thine did <hi>Hellen</hi> uſe?</l>
               <l>A (23) well-bred ſtranger's come, her husband's gone,</l>
               <l>What ſhould ſhe do? ſhe durſt not lye alone.</l>
               <l>See <hi>Menelaus, Hellen</hi> I acquit,</l>
               <l>She did but make uſe of a benefit.</l>
               <l>Neither's the ſandy Boar more cruel found,</l>
               <l>When with his tusks he at the Doggs turns round.</l>
               <l>Nor th' Lioneſs which to her whelps gives ſuck,</l>
               <l>Nor the ſmall Viper by ſome raſh foot ſtruck:</l>
               <l>Then th' wife that in her husbands bed doth finde</l>
               <l>A pretty Wench: her looks expreſs her mind.</l>
               <l>To fire and ſword ſhe flies, ſhame doth not know:</l>
               <l>Born like an Arrow from th' (26) <hi>Aonian</hi> Bow.</l>
               <l>This will the firm, the beſt knit-love divide,</l>
               <l>Such crimes as theſe, to wiſe men are deny'd.</l>
               <l>(25) <hi>Phaſias</hi> moſt barbarouſly her own ſons deſtroies,</l>
               <l>For to revenge their Fathers perjuries.</l>
               <l>Such a Dire Mother hath (26) you Swallow been,</l>
               <l>And ſtill her blood may on her breaſt be ſeen,</l>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:60466:34"/>
               <l>I bid not Ladies onely one bed know,</l>
               <l>Young wives can hardly be contented ſo.</l>
               <l>Uſe (27) ſtoln delights, but let them be conceal'd,</l>
               <l>No credit's got by ſuch a crime reveal'd.</l>
               <l>Give no reward, leſt any ſhould it ſee:</l>
               <l>Nor let your pleaſures at a ſet time be.</l>
               <l>Suſpiciouſly let none eſpy you ſet,</l>
               <l>Nor muſt you often in one place be met.</l>
               <l>And when you write, peruſe that writing well:</l>
               <l>Some underſtand more than the Letters tell.</l>
               <l>Wrong'd love ſharp darts will ſend, juſt wars main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain</l>
               <l>She that erewhile did grieve, makes you complain.</l>
               <l>Whilſt one <hi>Atrides</hi> lov'd, that one was true,</l>
               <l>When he was criminal, ſhe was ſo too.</l>
               <l>She hears how Lawrels were in garlands born,</l>
               <l>And how to (28) <hi>Chryſis</hi> ſhe was made a ſcorn.</l>
               <l>She heard the troubles 'bout (29) <hi>Lyrneſis</hi> made,</l>
               <l>And how the war was a long time delay'd.</l>
               <l>She heard of theſe, but did the <hi>Trojan</hi> ſee:</l>
               <l>How th' Victor would his captives captive be.</l>
               <l>So ſhe <hi>Aegiſtus</hi> doth her Lover make,</l>
               <l>Such a revenge did fair <hi>Tyndaris</hi> take.</l>
               <l>If any ſhould your privacies make known,</l>
               <l>Though manifeſt, you may the fact diſown.</l>
               <l>Be not too much dejected, nor exceed</l>
               <l>Too much in mitth, it will ſuſpition breed.</l>
               <l>Spare not to ſpeak, favour by that is gain'd,</l>
               <l>And Love by often meeting is obtain'd.</l>
               <l>There are that teach th' effects of herbs to prove,</l>
               <l>But in my judgement thoſe things poiſon love.</l>
               <l>Pepper with (30) biting Nettle-ſeed they bruiſe,</l>
               <l>With (31) yellow Pellitory Wine infuſe.</l>
               <l>The Goddeſs with no ſuch things love compels</l>
               <l>That under th' ſhady hill of (32) <hi>Eryx</hi> dwells.</l>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:60466:34"/>
               <l>Eat the white Skalion from (33) <hi>Pelaſgis</hi> ſent,</l>
               <l>Or garden herbs, which will not love prevent.</l>
               <l>Or Eggs, or Honey which on <hi>Hymettus</hi> flows,</l>
               <l>Or th' Apple Which upon the Pine-tree grows.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Erato,</hi> why doſt thou to <hi>Magick</hi> turn?</l>
               <l>A neerer way my Chariot wheel will run.</l>
               <l>You that by my advice your own conceal,</l>
               <l>By th' ſame advice may others thefts reveal.</l>
               <l>Blame not my levity, alwaies with one wind,</l>
               <l>The bending Keel doth not a paſſage finde.</l>
               <l>Sometimes the North, ſometimes the Eaſtern gales,</l>
               <l>Oft South, oft Weſt-winds ſwell the linen ſails.</l>
               <l>The Charioteer doth now let ſlack his rein,</l>
               <l>Anon hee curbs his horſes in again.</l>
               <l>There's ſome that will indulgencies abuſe,</l>
               <l>Though they no rival have, their Miſtreſs looſe:</l>
               <l>Hearts in proſperity more lofty are,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Bleſſings 'tis hard, with equal minds to bear.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>So ſtrength doth by degrees the fire forſake,</l>
               <l>On which the Aſhes do a covering make.</l>
               <l>But yet the heap turn'd o're new fire burns:</l>
               <l>Extinguiſht flames, and former light returns.</l>
               <l>So Love grown dull, muſt be ſtirr'd up, and when</l>
               <l>It falls aſleep, it muſt be rouz'd agen.</l>
               <l>Keep her mind warm, let fear her heart aſſail,</l>
               <l>At the detection of thy crime look pale.</l>
               <l>How much, how oft, not which my verſe contains,</l>
               <l>Hee's bleſt on whom an injur'd Maid complains.</l>
               <l>Shee ſwounds ſoon as his guilt doth reach her ears,</l>
               <l>Bereft of ſpeech, liveleſs, the wretch appears.</l>
               <l>I'm hee whoſe hair ſhee furiouſly would tear,</l>
               <l>To whoſe ſoft eyes ſhe would her ſharp nails bear,</l>
               <l>Whom, weeping ſhee may ſee, angry looks give,</l>
               <l>Without whom fain ſhe would, but cannot live.</l>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:60466:35"/>
               <l>Ask not how long? ſhee grieves but a ſhort ſpace:</l>
               <l>Let not her anger ſtrengthen by delaies.</l>
               <l>Now both your arms about her white neck caſt,</l>
               <l>And weeping let her bee by you imbrac't.</l>
               <l>Kiſs her lamenting, court the weeping Maid,</l>
               <l>Ratifie peace, ſo paſſion is allay'd.</l>
               <l>When ſhee's inrag'd, and doth with anger ſwell,</l>
               <l>Requeſt but Marriage-Rites, and all is well;</l>
               <l>That anger diſſipates, there peace reſides,</l>
               <l>And in that place (beleeve mee) grace abides.</l>
               <l>The Doves that newly fought, will bill and ſport,</l>
               <l>And one another with ſoft murmures court.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Chaos</hi> confuſ'd firſt without order was:</l>
               <l>The Earth, the Heaven, and Sea, had all one face.</l>
               <l>Heaven's put from earth, vaſt Seas imbrace the land,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Chaos</hi> doth in parts digeſted ſtand.</l>
               <l>Wilde Beaſts in Woods, Birds in the Aire abide,</l>
               <l>And Fiſhes in the watery ſtreams do gli de</l>
               <l>Then man ith' ſolitary field did rove,</l>
               <l>And with meer ſtrength his untaught body move.</l>
               <l>The wood his houſe, herbs meat, green leaves his bed,</l>
               <l>Hee with no other a long time was fed.</l>
               <l>Sweet pleaſure ſoftened his fierce mind, they ſay,</l>
               <l>Together man and wife in one bed lay.</l>
               <l>No skilful Maſter taught them what to do,</l>
               <l>How to perform Loves Act, no Art can ſhow.</l>
               <l>Birds had what they could love, and Fiſh did meet</l>
               <l>Ith' midſt of th' ſtream, to taſte this untoucht ſweet.</l>
               <l>The Doe the Buck purſues, ſmall worms their kind,</l>
               <l>And the Salt-Bitch unto the Dog is lin'd.</l>
               <l>The glad Ew skips, a Bull the Heifer gains,</l>
               <l>And the Shee-Goat the unclean hee ſuſtains.</l>
               <l>Keen Mares unto the Horſe will finde a way,</l>
               <l>Nor them can interpoſed Rivers ſtay.</l>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:60466:35"/>
               <l>Preſcribe ſtrong remedies, that will aſſwage,</l>
               <l>And onely give a <hi>Requiem</hi> to her rage.</l>
               <l>Theſe, than <hi>Machaons</hi> druggs, are far more ſure;</l>
               <l>If you offend, theſe pardon will procure.</l>
               <l>Whilſt theſe I ſing, <hi>Apollo</hi> doth inſpire,</l>
               <l>And with his finger ſtrikes his golden lyre.</l>
               <l>In's hand a Lawrel, Lawrel doth incloſe</l>
               <l>His ſacred brow, which him a Poet ſhows.</l>
               <l>Thou Teacher of ſoft Love (to mee thus ſpake)</l>
               <l>Unto my Temple all thy Scholars take.</l>
               <l>There is a Motto, which through th'world doth go,</l>
               <l>That every one ſhould learn himſelf to know.</l>
               <l>Who knows himſelf alone ſhall wiſely love,</l>
               <l>Hee to the utmoſt his deſign will move.</l>
               <l>Hee that a ſweet face hath, let it be ſeen,</l>
               <l>He that looks red, oft on her ſhoulder lean.</l>
               <l>Hee that ſpeaks well, let not his tongue be ſlow,</l>
               <l>Or ſing, or drink, what hee can beſt, that do.</l>
               <l>Let not the learned in his ſpeech declaim,</l>
               <l>Nor the mad Poet boaſt his excellent ſtrain.</l>
               <l>So <hi>Phaebus</hi> warns, <hi>Phaebus</hi> advice obey,</l>
               <l>Credit what ere his ſacred mouth ſhall ſay.</l>
               <l>Hee that doth wiſely love (to come more neer)</l>
               <l>Shall by my Art win, and his wiſht prize wear.</l>
               <l>Alwaies the earth affords not her increaſe,</l>
               <l>To help the ſhip ſometimes the winds do ceaſe.</l>
               <l>Small things advantage, great things love oppoſe,</l>
               <l>And much a Lovers courage undergoes.</l>
               <l>As Hares in <hi>Athos,</hi> or on <hi>Hybla</hi> Bees,</l>
               <l>As many fruits as grow on <hi>Pallas</hi> Trees,</l>
               <l>As th' ſhoar of ſhells, ſo full is Love of pain,</l>
               <l>Which wee endure, and which we muſt ſuſtain.</l>
               <l>They'l ſay ſhee's walkt out, though you her did ſpy,</l>
               <l>Imagine 'tis ſo, do not truſt your eye.</l>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:60466:36"/>
               <l>Is the gate ſhut? ſhe promiſ'd ſhould ſtand wide,</l>
               <l>Suffer't, and lay your ſelf down on your ſide:</l>
               <l>Perhaps her counterfeiting Maid may cry,</l>
               <l>What man is that which at the door doth lye?</l>
               <l>Imbrace the poſts, the cruel wench ſpeak fair,</l>
               <l>In your head Roſes from the wall pluckt, wear.</l>
               <l>If ſhe calls, come, if not, go from the gate,</l>
               <l>It ill becomes ingenious men to wait.</l>
               <l>Your Miſtreſs bids, but would not have you go,</l>
               <l>Thoſe be her words, her meaning is not ſo.</l>
               <l>Take nothing ill, her blows imagine ſweet,</l>
               <l>Neither diſdain to kiſs her dainty feet.</l>
               <l>But theſe are toyes, my Muſe ſpeaks greater things,</l>
               <l>Be preſent all, hear what my fancy ſings.</l>
               <l>Hard things wee ſet on, virtue's alwaies ſo,</l>
               <l>The Art of Love muſt all indeavours know.</l>
               <l>Suffer a rival, conqueſt is with thee,</l>
               <l>And thou a Victor in <hi>Joves</hi> Tower ſhalt be.</l>
               <l>Think it no man, but ſome <hi>Arcadian</hi> Oak,</l>
               <l>(No more Ile ſpeak of that) that ſuch things ſpoke.</l>
               <l>If ſhe but beek, forbear, if write, ſit ſtill,</l>
               <l>And let her go and come whither ſhe will.</l>
               <l>Such things muſt married men with wives endure,</l>
               <l>When they would have ſweet ſleep, their parts ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure.</l>
               <l>Here I confeſs my Art imperfect is,</l>
               <l>What ſhall I do? I'me ignorant in this?</l>
               <l>Shall I endure my Miſtreſs to be courted</l>
               <l>Before my face, with rage not be tranſported?</l>
               <l>One kiſt my Miſtreſs, at which I complain'd,</l>
               <l>Our love's with ſo much barbarouſneſs are ſtain'd.</l>
               <l>This vice not once hath hurt, he excells mee,</l>
               <l>That with all h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r pretenders can agree.</l>
               <l>Better let thefts unknown obſcured lye,</l>
               <l>Leſt ſhe forget her feigned modeſty.</l>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:60466:36"/>
               <l>Young men don't ſtrive your failing loves to take,</l>
               <l>Leſt they ſhould vows in their offences make.</l>
               <l>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tected loves increaſe, both being eſpy'd</l>
               <l>In the ſame fault, their loves are faſter ty'd.</l>
               <l>There is a fable through the whole world taught,</l>
               <l>How <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Venus</hi> were by <hi>Vulcan</hi> caught.</l>
               <l>Great <hi>Mars</hi> ſubmitting unto <hi>Venus</hi> love</l>
               <l>Of a blunt ſouldier did an Amouriſt prove.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Venus</hi> (than whom no Goddeſs is more kinde)</l>
               <l>Did condeſcend to ſatisfie his mind.</l>
               <l>How oft the wanton jeer'd her husbands foot,</l>
               <l>And's harden'd hands, ſo oft ith' fire put?</l>
               <l>She with <hi>Mars</hi> imitating <hi>Vulcans</hi> pace,</l>
               <l>Unto her form adds a becoming grace.</l>
               <l>At firſt they met and acted privately,</l>
               <l>The fault it ſelf was full of modeſty,</l>
               <l>The Sun diſcloſ'd (who can deceive the Sun?)</l>
               <l>And <hi>Vulcan</hi> knew that which his wife had done.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sol</hi> thou didſt ills create, let ſomething be</l>
               <l>Askt for thy ſilence, ſhe will grant it thee.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mulciber</hi> pitcht a net about his bed</l>
               <l>On every ſide, by which their ſight's miſled,</l>
               <l>A journey feigns to (34) <hi>Lemnos,</hi> th' Lovers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Both naked lye intangled in his net.</l>
               <l>He calls the Gods, they caught ith' net ſhew all</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Venus</hi> could ſcarce abſtain from tears let fall.</l>
               <l>They cannot frame their looks, they are ſo ty'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>Nor their obſcene parts with their hands can hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>One ſmiling, ſaid, unconquer'd <hi>Mars</hi> to mee</l>
               <l>Transfer thoſe bonds, if they a barthen be.</l>
               <l>Scarce <hi>Neptune</hi> at thy prayers he them unties,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mars</hi> unto <hi>Crete, Venus</hi> to <hi>Paphos</hi> hies.</l>
               <l>It profits not, before they covered it.</l>
               <l>Which ſhameleſs now they openly commit.</l>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:60466:37"/>
               <l>'Tis ſaid, thou didſt confeſs thy foolery,</l>
               <l>And of thy paſſion haſt repented thee.</l>
               <l>This I forbid, and ſo doth <hi>Venus</hi> too,</l>
               <l>She felt it firſt, and ſhee fore-warns it you.</l>
               <l>Unſeen nets do not for your rival lay,</l>
               <l>Nor intercept his letters by the way.</l>
               <l>Let thoſe men take ſuch things, if any muſt,</l>
               <l>That are by fire and water rendred juſt.</l>
               <l>Loe I acknowledge nought but Love is here,</l>
               <l>Nor do theſe lines any chaſte Matron jeer.</l>
               <l>What prophane man dares (35) <hi>Ceres</hi> rites that knows,</l>
               <l>Or <hi>Samothracian</hi> ſacred things diſcloſe?</l>
               <l>It is a vertue ſecrets to conceal,</l>
               <l>As great a vice things ſacred to reveal.</l>
               <l>For babling <hi>Tantalus</hi> did want his food,</l>
               <l>And thirſty in the middle waters ſtood.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Venus</hi> would have her ſacred rites be hidden,</l>
               <l>And all divulgers are from hence forbidden.</l>
               <l>Though <hi>Venus</hi> Myſt'ries are not cloſed found</l>
               <l>In Cheſt that will not with fierce blows reſound,</l>
               <l>Yet chiefly we this obſervation keep,</l>
               <l>That they for ever do in ſilence ſleep.</l>
               <l>If <hi>Venus</hi> any where diſcloathed ſtand,</l>
               <l>Her ſecrets ſhe concealeth with her hand.</l>
               <l>Cattel will generate ith' open day,</l>
               <l>But ſeen by Maids, they turn their eyes away.</l>
               <l>Strong doors and beds unto our thefts agree,</l>
               <l>In modeſty moſt part muſt covered be.</l>
               <l>Opacous clouds wee wiſh for, and the night:</l>
               <l>We would have leſs of the diſcloſing light.</l>
               <l>When from the Sun and Rain no roof did ſhield,</l>
               <l>But th' Oak both food and covering did yeeld;</l>
               <l>In Groves and Caves people their pleaſures try,</l>
               <l>So great a care they had to modeſty.</l>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:60466:37"/>
               <l>Now for our night-work we have titles ſought,</l>
               <l>Nothing unleſs well praiſ'd for much is bought.</l>
               <l>Be conſtant unto none, that ſo you may,</l>
               <l>This I might once have had, of many ſay.</l>
               <l>You may ſuch Ladies with your finger ſhow,</l>
               <l>But it is rudeneſs if you touch them ſo.</l>
               <l>That which if true they would deny, ſome feign;</l>
               <l>Saying that they have with ſuch Ladies lain.</l>
               <l>Though they their bodies cannot, yet their name</l>
               <l>They will, although not criminal, defame.</l>
               <l>Go then thou hateful pander, ſhut the door,</l>
               <l>And add to it a hundred locks or more.</l>
               <l>What matter? when her ſhame about is ſpread,</l>
               <l>And what ſhee is not, ſhee'd be credited.</l>
               <l>We ſparingly talk of our conſtant Lover,</l>
               <l>And her myſterious thefts our Faiths do cover.</l>
               <l>Let not your love her imperfections know,</l>
               <l>It avails many to diſſemble ſo.</l>
               <l>He did not <hi>Andromeda</hi>'s colour ſcorn,</l>
               <l>That ſwiftly on a flying-horſe was born.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Andromache</hi> to others ſeemed tall,</l>
               <l>Yet <hi>Hector</hi> her his little one did call.</l>
               <l>Acquaintance makes that handſome which is worſt,</l>
               <l>For Love will many faults eſpy at firſt.</l>
               <l>When a young ſlip begins its root to take,</l>
               <l>Each blaſt of wind the tender plant will ſhake.</l>
               <l>But being grown, it will reſiſt all gales,</l>
               <l>And bearing fruit againſt the wind prevails.</l>
               <l>So imperfections vaniſh in a day,</l>
               <l>What is not handſome, ſeems ſo by delay.</l>
               <l>Young tender Kids will not indure the Goat</l>
               <l>At firſt, but he in time inclines them to't.</l>
               <l>With fit tearms mend her faults, call her brown which</l>
               <l>Hath a look darker than <hi>Illyrian</hi> pitch.</l>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:60466:38"/>
               <l>Call a ſquint, <hi>Venus; Pallas,</hi> a yellow skin,</l>
               <l>And call her ſlender that looks lank and thin.</l>
               <l>A low one, active call; one groſs, full face't;</l>
               <l>So let each fault in ſome neer grace be place't.</l>
               <l>Where ſhe was born, her age do not deſire,</l>
               <l>Nor what ſhe to the (36) <hi>Cenſor</hi> gave inquire.</l>
               <l>If ſhe want youth, and be of riper years,</l>
               <l>Or if ſhe plate her gray-inclining hairs,</l>
               <l>Oh youths theſe ages both are fruitful known;</l>
               <l>Theſe fields will bear good Corn, they muſt be ſown.</l>
               <l>Pains muſt in youth and ſtrength be undergone,</l>
               <l>Age with a ſilent foot comes ſtealing on.</l>
               <l>Either go to the Sea's, or plow the Land,</l>
               <l>Or to the wars with weapons in your hand.</l>
               <l>Or elſe incline your ſelf to court a Maid,</l>
               <l>This is a war too, this hath rich men made.</l>
               <l>Add prudence to your work, which all prefers,</l>
               <l>And cuſtome which makes all Artificers.</l>
               <l>Their loſs of youth with neatneſs they'l ſupply,</l>
               <l>And all means to defer old age will try.</l>
               <l>In divers manners they act <hi>Venus</hi> plaies,</l>
               <l>No Tables can deſcribe more ſeveral waies.</l>
               <l>Husbands and wives both ſo indifferent ſeem.</l>
               <l>We can't think they, ſtirr'd up delights eſteem.</l>
               <l>I hate the bed which yields not mutual joyes,</l>
               <l>And that makes mee contemn the love of boyes.</l>
               <l>I hate her that gives of neceſſity</l>
               <l>Being barren, of her wooll doth dreaming lye.</l>
               <l>Pleaſure which duty grants I count not ſo,</l>
               <l>No Maid to mee ſhall ſuch a duty owe.</l>
               <l>I love to hear her wearied voice deſire,</l>
               <l>That I would longer ſtay, bid mee reſpire.</l>
               <l>May I my Miſtreſs conquer'd eyes look on,</l>
               <l>Languiſh with love, bidding her griefs be gone.</l>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:60466:38"/>
               <l>Nature to youth gives not theſe gifts, to ſome,</l>
               <l>They do not until paſt (37) ſeven <hi>Luſtra</hi>'s come.</l>
               <l>Wine drunk too new is ſowre, give mee a cup</l>
               <l>Of year-old Wine unto the brim fill'd up.</l>
               <l>Fierce blaſts the tender Plane tree will deſtroy,</l>
               <l>And Meads new cut will the bare feet annoy.</l>
               <l>To <hi>Hellen</hi> could <hi>Hermione</hi> compare;</l>
               <l>Is <hi>Gorge</hi> like unto her Mother fair?</l>
               <l>Who ere doth vow's to an old <hi>Venus</hi> raiſe,</l>
               <l>If hee remain, merits condign praiſe.</l>
               <l>Loe the concealing bed two Lovers hides</l>
               <l>My Muſe before their chamber door abides.</l>
               <l>There what to ſay they need not learn, nor will</l>
               <l>Their wanton hands within the bed lye ſtill.</l>
               <l>Their fingers will learn how to act their parts.</l>
               <l>And in what private place love ſticks his darts.</l>
               <l>Thus <hi>Hector</hi> did <hi>Andromache</hi> aſſayl,</l>
               <l>Hee did not onely in field-wars prevail.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Achilles</hi> with <hi>Lyrneſis</hi> did no leſs,</l>
               <l>When wearied he would a ſoft bed compreſs:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Briſeis</hi> cloſ'd faſt in thoſe arms remain'd,</l>
               <l>Which he before with <hi>Phrygian</hi> gore had ſtain'd.</l>
               <l>What wanton, did it pleaſe thee that hee ſhould</l>
               <l>In his victorious arms thy body fold?</l>
               <l>Truſt mee, too ſoon ſuch pleaſure muſt not be</l>
               <l>Acted, but by degrees and leiſurely.</l>
               <l>If you perceive where ſhe would have your hand,</l>
               <l>Then let not baſhfulneſs your joyes withſtand.</l>
               <l>You ſhall behold her eyes dart radiant beams,</l>
               <l>Like the refulgent Sun in liquid ſtreams.</l>
               <l>Perhaps ſhee'l ſhrieke, or gentle whiſpers make,</l>
               <l>Sweetly complain, ſuch yeelding language ſpeak.</l>
               <l>What once you do attempt, leave not undone,</l>
               <l>Nor let her in that courſe before you run.</l>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:60466:39"/>
               <l>Keep both together, pleaſure is more ſweet,</l>
               <l>In full conſent, when both the Sexes meet.</l>
               <l>This way obſerve, when leiſure will allow,</l>
               <l>When fear will not to act love's part ſhow how.</l>
               <l>When as delay's not ſafe, then ply the Oar,</l>
               <l>Make uſe of time, ſpur a free horſe the more.</l>
               <l>I've done, give mee the palm young gallants now,</l>
               <l>And place a Myrtle Garland on my brow.</l>
               <l>Of Surgeons <hi>Podalyrius</hi> was the beſt</l>
               <l>For ſtrength <hi>Achilles,</hi> wiſdom (38) <hi>Neſtors</hi> breaſt.</l>
               <l>Sage (39) <hi>Calchas; Ajax</hi> ſtout: skilful they nam'd</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Automedon:</hi> and I for love am fam'd.</l>
               <l>Celebrate mee your Poet, give mee praiſe,</l>
               <l>My name an Eccho through the world ſhall raiſe.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vulcan</hi> (40) t' <hi>Achilles,</hi> I give arms to you,</l>
               <l>Vanquiſh with yours, as hee was wont to do.</l>
               <l>Who with my ſteel makes the <hi>Amazon</hi> bow,</l>
               <l>Muſt write, <hi>to conquer, Naſo taught mee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ow.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The ſoft-skin'd Maids deſire my precepts too,</l>
               <l>Loe, my next care ſhall bee t'accompliſh you.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>The end of the ſecond Book.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="annotations">
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:60466:39"/>
            <head>Annotations on the ſecond Book OF <hi>Publius Ovidius Naſo, De Arte Amandi.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">(1) <hi>IO Paean) Iô</hi> is an exclamation expreſſing joy and ſatisfaction at any thing: the <hi>Romans</hi> uſed it in their ſolemn Triumphs, where the ſouldiers following, cried out, <hi>Iô Triumphe. Hor. Car.</hi> 4. <hi>Ode.</hi> 2.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tu<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> dum procedis, Iô Triumphi,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Non ſemel dicemus, Iô Triumphe.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And <hi>Iô</hi> triumph whilſt thou paſſeſt by,</l>
               <l>We many times will, <hi>Iô</hi> triumph cry.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Quae vox exultantium prae gandio eſt</hi> (ſaith <hi>Aſcenſius</hi> upon the place) whence to ſing <hi>Iô Paean,</hi> is to praiſe or ſing hymns to <hi>Apollo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">(2) <hi>Maeonian</hi> man) <hi>Homer,</hi> called alſo <hi>Maeonides</hi> from his Father <hi>Maeon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">(3) The <hi>Priameian) Paris,</hi> ſo called from his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Priam,</hi> who ſailed from <hi>Amyclae,</hi> a City in <hi>Pelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponneſus,</hi> with his fair prize <hi>Hellen,</hi> that exquiſite piece of beauty, of whom <hi>Dares Phr.</hi> deſcribing <hi>Caſtor</hi> and <hi>Pollux, fuerunt alter alteri ſimilis, capillo flavo, &amp;c. Caſtor</hi> and <hi>Pollux</hi> were like each other, having yellow hair, great eyes, clear complexions, ſlender, and extreamly handſome: <hi>Hellen</hi> was like them, beautiful, of a winning nature, courteous, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:60466:40"/> (4) <hi>Hippodamia)</hi> the daughter of <hi>Oenomaus</hi> King of <hi>Elis,</hi> who propoſing her a prize to him that could overcome him in a Chariot-race, was at laſt, by <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lops</hi> (who bribed his Charioteer <hi>Myrtylus</hi>) out-run, who together with his courſe won the fair <hi>Hippoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia</hi> for his Bride.</p>
            <p n="5">(5) <hi>Minos</hi> doth all means of) a King of <hi>Crete</hi> by whom <hi>Daedalus</hi> was impriſoned in the Labyrinth which himſelf had built, for aſſiſting his Queen <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiphae</hi> in the ſatisfaction of her luſt. <hi>Vide ſupra.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">(6) <hi>Boôtes</hi> nor <hi>Orion) Boôtes, Orion,</hi> and the <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gean</hi> Maid are three of the celeſtial conſtellations, the firſt of which is placed neer <hi>urſa Minor,</hi> the ſecond under the head of <hi>Taurus;</hi> the laft is the ſign <hi>Virgo,</hi> by the Poets feigned to be <hi>Erigone,</hi> who was born in <hi>Tegea,</hi> a City of <hi>Arcadia,</hi> a Country in <hi>Peloponne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> whereof her Grandfather <hi>Oebalus</hi> was King, after her death tranſlated into the ſign <hi>Virgo,</hi> placed in the Zodiack between <hi>Leo</hi> and <hi>Libra.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">(7) <hi>Samos</hi> and <hi>Naxos) Samos</hi> (for its neer ſite to <hi>Thracia,</hi> called <hi>Samothrace) Naxos, Paros,</hi> and <hi>Delos</hi> are Iſlands in the <hi>Aegean</hi> Sea.</p>
            <p n="8">(8) The <hi>Clarians</hi> love) <hi>Apollo</hi> called <hi>Clarius</hi> from <hi>Clarus</hi> a City in <hi>Ionia,</hi> where he had a Temple.</p>
            <p n="9">(9) <hi>Lebinthus</hi> and) <hi>Lebinthus, Calydna,</hi> and <hi>Aſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palaea,</hi> are three Iſlands of the <hi>Sporades</hi> in the <hi>Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terranean,</hi> neer <hi>Crete.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">(10) <hi>Aemonian</hi> Arts) Witchcrafts from the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Witches that in antient time practiſed in <hi>Aemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi> here dwelt the dire Witch <hi>Erictho,</hi> and here grew all ſorts of herbs that were advantagious to their helliſh incantations. <hi>Lucan. lib.</hi> 6.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Theſſala quinetiam tellus herbaſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> nocenteis</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rupibus ingenuit, ſenſura<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſaxa canentes</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:60466:40"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Arcanum ſerale Magos, ibi plurima ſurgunt, &amp;c.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>Engliſhed by Mr. <hi>May.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Beſides <hi>Theſſalia</hi>'s Fields, and Rocks do bear</l>
               <l>Strange killing herbs, and plants, and ſtones that hear</l>
               <l>The charming Witches murmures: there ariſe</l>
               <l>Plants, that have power to force the Deities.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Medea</hi> there a ſtranger, in thoſe fields</l>
               <l>Gather'd worſe herbs than any <hi>Cholcos</hi> yeelds.</l>
            </q>
            <p n="11">(11) With <hi>Circe</hi>) an Inchantreſſe living at <hi>Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceum,</hi> a Promontory in <hi>Italy,</hi> whither <hi>Ulyſſes</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions being driven by a ſtorm at Sea, were by the Witch transformed into Swine; whom <hi>Ulyſſes</hi> by his policy perſwaded to reſtore to their priſtine forms, which ſhe no ſooner had done, but with them he came away, leaving the loathſome habitation of that accurſed Inchantreſſe. <hi>Hom. Odyſ.</hi> 10. <hi>Meta.</hi> 14.</p>
            <p n="12">(12) <hi>Hylas</hi> raviſht) the Son of <hi>Theodamas</hi> King of <hi>Scythia,</hi> who going with <hi>Hercules</hi> out of the Ship <hi>Argo,</hi> to get an Oar in the Woods of <hi>Myſia,</hi> and lying down to drink on the bank of the River <hi>Aska<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius,</hi> hee was by the Water-Nymphs called <hi>Naides</hi> pluckt in and raviſhed.</p>
            <p n="13">(13) <hi>Calypſo</hi> waile) Daughter to <hi>Oceanus</hi> and <hi>Thetys,</hi> ſhee governed the Iſle <hi>Ogygia,</hi> betwixt the Seas <hi>Phoenicium</hi> and <hi>Syriacum,</hi> whither the Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beaten <hi>Ulyſſes</hi> by a ſtorm being driven, was by her entertained, whom ſhee falling in love with, admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to her bed, and detained the ſpace of ſeven years, till hee was by the deſtinies commanded thence. <hi>Hom. Odyſ.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>(14) <hi>Simois)</hi> a River in <hi>Aſia</hi> riſing out of the Mount <hi>Ida,</hi> and running all along by <hi>Troy,</hi> after which meeting with the River <hi>Xanthus,</hi> they toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther make a great Fen or Mariſh, whence they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patiate
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:60466:41"/>themſelves into the <hi>Helleſpont</hi> neer the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>montory Sygaeum.</hi> So in <hi>Epist.</hi> 1. <hi>ad Ulyſſem.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hac ibat Simois, hîc eſt Segeia tellus:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hic ſteterat Priami regia celſa Senis.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Here flow'd <hi>Simois,</hi> this is <hi>Segeian</hi> Land,</l>
               <l>And here did <hi>Priams</hi> ſtately Palace ſtand.</l>
            </q>
            <p n="15">(15) <hi>Dolon</hi>'s Death) a <hi>Trojan</hi> of admirable celeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, who being ſent a ſpy into the Grecian Camp, was taken by <hi>Ulyſſes,</hi> to whom in hope of pardon hee revealed the <hi>Trojan</hi> Counſels, and betrayed <hi>Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> King of <hi>Thrace,</hi> who was then journeying to <hi>Troy,</hi> with the white horſes, whereon depended the <hi>Trojan</hi> fate, after all which hee was ſlain by <hi>Ulyſſes. Hom. Iliad.</hi> 40.</p>
            <p n="16">(16) <hi>Atalanta</hi> ſhun) a Lady of ſuperlative beauty, averſe to <hi>Venus,</hi> but being daily ſolicited with the many importunities of divers Lovers, ſhe promiſed her ſelf to him that could over-run her in a foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>race; which <hi>Hippomanes</hi> (after the vain aſſaies of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny) undertaking, by caſting in her way three golden Apples which ſhee ſtaid to take up, overcame and married her. <hi>Metam. lib.</hi> 10.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>O quoties, cum jam poſſet tranſire, morata eſt</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Spectatoſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> diu vultus invita reliquit!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>How oft ſhe ſtaid, when ſhe could have out-gone;</l>
               <l>Unwillingly his face left looking on!</l>
            </q>
            <p n="17">(17) <hi>Melanion</hi> cauſe) <hi>Hippomanes,</hi> ſo called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, from his throwing Apples out of his hand.</p>
            <p n="18">(18) <hi>Dice)</hi> Players at Dice both by the <hi>Elibertine</hi> and <hi>Conſtantinopolitan</hi> Council under <hi>Justinian</hi> were puniſhed with Excommunication, and <hi>Horatius (lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Carm. Ode.</hi> 24.) ſaith it was by Law then for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden.</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:60466:41"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sou mavis vetita legibus aleae</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quum perjura patris fides</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Conſortem ſocium fallat &amp; hoſpitem,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Indigno<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> pecuniam</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>haeredi properet.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Or at the Dice by Laws deny'd</l>
               <l>His Father's perjur'd Faith doth play,</l>
               <l>And cheats his friend, ſo that hee may</l>
               <l>Wealth for his worthleſs heir provide.</l>
            </q>
            <p>But yet <hi>Xenophon (lib.</hi> 3. <hi>de dictis Socratis</hi>) advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to play at Tables or Dice, to divert from idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p n="19">(19) Foe of Glaſs) this game of Cheſs invented (ſay ſome) by <hi>Pyrrhus,</hi> or, as others, by <hi>Palamedes</hi> at the ſiege of <hi>Troy,</hi> was much practiſed amongſt the <hi>Romans;</hi> their men they made ſometimes of Wax, but moſt commonly of Glaſs. <hi>Martial. lib.</hi> 7. <hi>Epig.</hi> 71.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sic vincas Novium<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Publium<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>
                  </hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mandris, &amp; vitreo latrone clauſos.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>You may of <hi>Novius</hi> and <hi>Publius</hi> win,</l>
               <l>With Knights, and with your man of glaſs ſhut in.</l>
            </q>
            <p n="20">(20) Her bed) The <hi>Romans</hi> chief time of enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment was at ſupper, their Tables were round, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout which were placed three beds, whereon the gueſts did not ſit, but lye along, three uſually on a bed, each of their feet behinde the others back, where they put off their ſhooes becauſe they would not foul the beds, for the moſt part richly covered. <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent. Heautont.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Accurrunt ſervi, ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s detrahunt</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Video alios fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re lect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, ſternere, coenam parare,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Some ſervants run, away their ſhooes do bear,</l>
               <l>Some haſting beds do ſpread, ſupper prepare.</l>
            </q>
            <p n="21">
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:60466:42"/> (21) He before did) <hi>Hercules</hi> whom the Poets feign to ſuſtain Heaven upon his ſhoulder, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing too ponderous for <hi>Atlas,</hi> hee being enamoured on <hi>Omphale,</hi> Queen of <hi>Lydia,</hi> caſting away his Club, and Lions skin, to obtain her love, did not refuſe to take a basket of wooll, and a diſtaff into his hand, which made his wife <hi>Deianira</hi> cry out. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 9.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quem non mille ferae, quem non Stheneleius hoſt is,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Non potuit Juno vincere, vicit amor.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Whom not a thouſand monſters, <hi>Graecian</hi> arms,</l>
               <l>Whom <hi>Juno</hi> neer could conquer, beauty charms.</l>
            </q>
            <p n="22">(22) <hi>Phyllacides Laodamia) Proteſilaus,</hi> called <hi>Phyllacides</hi> from <hi>Phyllace</hi> a Town in <hi>Theſſaly,</hi> hee was the firſt of the <hi>Grecians</hi> ſlain by <hi>Hector;</hi> his wife <hi>Laodamia</hi> ſo firmly loved him, that requeſting the Gods but to ſee the ſhadow of her ſlain husband, and obtaining, expires in the imbracing of it.</p>
            <p n="23">(23) A well-bred ſtranger) <hi>Paris,</hi> on whom <hi>Das Phry.</hi> gives this character, <hi>Paridem candidum, lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gum, fortem, oculis pulcherrimis, capillo molli &amp; fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vo, ore venuſto, voce ſuavi. Paris</hi> was courteous, tall, valiant, hee had fair eyes, ſoft yellow hair, a pleaſing countenance, and an enticing voice.</p>
            <p n="24">(24) <hi>Aonian</hi> Bow) <hi>Apollo</hi>'s Bow with which hee ſlew the Monſter <hi>Python. Metam. lib.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p n="25">(25) <hi>Phaſias</hi> moſt barbarouſly) <hi>Medea,</hi> who ſlew her two Sons that ſhee bore to <hi>Jaſon</hi> before his face, becauſe hee forſook her, and married <hi>Creüſa. Vide ſupra.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="26">(26) Yon Swallow) <hi>Progne,</hi> who ſlew her Son <hi>Itys,</hi> to revenge the rape committed by her husband <hi>Tereus,</hi> upon her Siſter <hi>Philomela,</hi> for which bloody murther ſhee was turned into a Swallow, whoſe breaſt is ſtill ſtained with her Sons blood. <hi>Metam. lib.</hi> 6.</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:60466:42"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>—Neque adhuc de pectore caedis</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Exceſſere notae, ſignata<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſanguine pluma est.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>—the murthering marks remain</l>
               <l>Upon her breaſt, the blood her feathers ſtain.</l>
            </q>
            <p n="27">(27) Stoln delights) the ſtrict Reader may, cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring this place, as judging it too light and wanton to bee inſerted by a Chriſtian, detract from the whole; but I hope he will acquieſce with ſatisfaction, when I ſhall tell him I intended to have ſlipt this and ſome other excreſcents from the body of the tree; but conſidering without declining my reſolutions of rendring it an exact tranſlation, without preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice to the Author, and cenſure to my ſelf, I could not do it, I offer them to modeſt eyes to be lookt upon, as indeed they are, the documents of a Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then.</p>
            <p n="28">(28) <hi>Chryſis)</hi> the Daughter of <hi>Apollo's</hi> Prieſt, and <hi>Agamemnon's</hi> Miſtreſs, who being forced to reſtore her to her Father, did in her room raviſh <hi>Briſeis</hi> from <hi>Achilles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="29">(29) <hi>Lyrneſis) Briſcis,</hi> called <hi>Lyrneſis</hi> from the place where ſhee was born, whom <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rides</hi> after the departure of <hi>Chryſis,</hi> ſeiz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d or, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> great contentions betwixt him and <hi>Achiller. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Iliad.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="30">(30) Biting Nettle-ſeed) the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>: Romant,</hi> which hath of all other the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſtinging quality, and ſtirreth up <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p n="31">(31) Yellow Pellitory) not that the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> or flower<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be yellow, but hee calls it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the yellow bunch, or knob in the mid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the frow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> like that of a Daiſie.</p>
            <p n="32">(32) Of <hi>Eryx</hi> dwell.) <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yx</hi> is a M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>cily,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (ſaith <hi>Aelian lik.</hi> 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:60466:43"/>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, where ſtands a Temple dedicate to <hi>Venus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="33">(33) <hi>Pelaſgis) Arcadia,</hi> ſo called from <hi>Pelaſgus,</hi> ſometimes King thereof, who planted many herbs, and made food of the roots of them.</p>
            <p n="34">(34) To <hi>Lemnos)</hi> an Iſle in the <hi>Aegean</hi> Sea, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous for the reception of <hi>Vulcan,</hi> who for his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity, being ejected Heaven by the gods, fell up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this Iſle, where, being lamed by the fall, hee for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged Thunderbolts for <hi>Jupiter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="35">(35) <hi>Ceres</hi> rites) <hi>Ceres</hi> Daughter to <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Ops</hi> (the firſt that deviſed the manner of ſowing Wheat and Barly, for which ſhee was deified) had her rites, which (ſaith <hi>Cicero) longe maximis &amp; oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultiſſimis Ceremoniis continentur,</hi> were contained in great and hidden myſteries, which it was death for any of her Prieſts to diſcloſe.</p>
            <p n="36">(36) <hi>Cenſor</hi> gave) the Cenſors were officers in <hi>Rome,</hi> to whom every one gave in their names, with the full value of their eſtates: theſe took notice of all ſuch as were ill husbands, neglected their Farms, or left their Vines untilled.</p>
            <p n="37">(37) Seven <hi>Luſtras</hi>) a <hi>Luſtrum</hi> is the ſpace of five years, every fifth year the Cenſors purging the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Army with Sacrifice; ſo that ſeven <hi>Luſtras</hi> is the ſpace of thirty five years.</p>
            <p n="38">(38) <hi>Neſtors</hi> breaſt) the Son of <hi>Neleus</hi> and <hi>Cloris,</hi> hee excelled for wiſdome and cloquence, by which hee ſo much advantaged the <hi>Grecians,</hi> that <hi>Agamem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non</hi> ſaid hee doubted not, if hee had but ten <hi>Neſtors,</hi> ſuddenly to vanquiſh and overcome the <hi>Trojans.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="39">(39) <hi>Chalcas)</hi> a <hi>Greeian Augure,</hi> the Son of <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor:</hi> hee accompanied the <hi>Grecians</hi> in the <hi>Trojan</hi> expedition, where becauſe hee much excelled in the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:60466:43"/>Art of divining, many great things were ſwayed by his Counſel.</p>
            <p n="40">(40) T' <hi>Achilles) Vulcan</hi> at the requeſt of <hi>Thetys,</hi> forged a ſute of Arms for <hi>Achilles,</hi> the ſhield was beautified with moſt excellent workmanſhip; for in it hee preſented the Earth, the Sea, and Heaven, with the Sun, Moon, Planets, and other Conſtellations, two exquiſite Cities, a field of Corn, a golden Vine, and ſeveral other admirable curioſities. <hi>Hom. Iliad.</hi> 18. <hi>lib.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
               <l>Shee with theſe glittering arms from <hi>Vulcan</hi> hies,</l>
               <l>And like a Hauk down to <hi>Olympus</hi> flyes.</l>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="book">
            <pb n="78" facs="tcp:60466:44"/>
            <head>The third Book OF <hi>Publius Ovidius Naſo, De Arte Amandi.</hi>
            </head>
            <argument>
               <lg>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <l>Venus <hi>commands, the Poet doth obey,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Affords her Sex his skill: how Ladies may</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>By Art the faults of Nature rectifie:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>What Books to read: what waies for love to try:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>What places to frequent; how to inſnare</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Amouriſt: what perſons to beware:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>How to revive dead flames, and to beguile</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Their wary Guardians: at what times to ſmile</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Upon their ſervants; laſt of all to flye</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>By</hi> Procris <hi>ſtory, baleful jealouſie.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </argument>
            <lg>
               <l>THe <hi>Greeks</hi> I firſt have harneſſ'd; now remain</l>
               <l>Arms for (1) <hi>Penthiſilea</hi> and her train.</l>
               <l>Go both alike prepar'd; they upon whom</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Venus</hi> and <hi>Cupid</hi> ſmile will overcome.</l>
               <l>For th' naked to reſiſt the arm'd 'tis vain,</l>
               <l>Men by ſuch victories no honour gain.</l>
               <l>But Snakes why doft thou poiſon; ſome will ſay,</l>
               <l>Or mak'ſt whole folds unto the Wolf a prey?</l>
               <l>Repreach not all, for ſome's offences done,</l>
               <l>Let each be as ſhe merits look't upon.</l>
               <l>Though <hi>Menelaus Hellen</hi> can accuſe,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Hellen</hi>'s Siſter <hi>Aga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>emnon</hi> rues:</l>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:60466:44"/>
               <l>Though by <hi>Eriphiles</hi> crime (2) <hi>Oeclides</hi> fell</l>
               <l>Alive, on his 'live horſes, down to Hell:</l>
               <l>Yet vertuous did <hi>Penelope</hi> remain</l>
               <l>Four <hi>Lustra</hi>'s, till her Lord came back again.</l>
               <l>Behold <hi>Phylacides,</hi> whoſe (3) wife they ſay</l>
               <l>T' follow her husband died before her day.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pheretiada</hi>'s redeemed by his wife,</l>
               <l>Who for his ſafety offered her own life.</l>
               <l>Receive mee <hi>Capaneus</hi> (4) <hi>Iphias</hi> cries,</l>
               <l>Wee'l mingle Aſhes ſo ith' (5) <hi>Rogus</hi> dies.</l>
               <l>Ladies are really all vertue, then</l>
               <l>No wonder if ſo much they pleaſe us men.</l>
               <l>But yet our Art requireth not ſuch minds,</l>
               <l>With lighter ſails my Pinnace paſſage findes.</l>
               <l>Nothing but amorous loves by mee are mov'd,</l>
               <l>And I inſtruct how women muſt be lov'd.</l>
               <l>Women, love's bow and flames will eaſily ſhake,</l>
               <l>But not ſo ſoon on men impreſſion make.</l>
               <l>Men oft prove faithleſs, Maids not oft untrue,</l>
               <l>Such crimes (if thou inquireſt) they have few.</l>
               <l>Unconſtant <hi>Jaſon Phaſias</hi> forſakes,</l>
               <l>Another Bride into his boſome takes.</l>
               <l>(6) <hi>Theſius Ariadne</hi> left alone</l>
               <l>A prey to Sea-fowls in a place unknown.</l>
               <l>Enquire ſo many waies why (7) <hi>Phyllis</hi> went,</l>
               <l>And did with careleſs hair ith' Woods lament?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Eliſa</hi>'s (8) Gueſt did unto her afford,</l>
               <l>Though ſhee religious was, a death, a ſword.</l>
               <l>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e teach what loft you, ignorant in love,</l>
               <l>You wanted Art, and Art doth love improve.</l>
               <l>They'd never know, but <hi>Cythera</hi> commands</l>
               <l>That I ſhould teach, whil'ſt ſhee before mee ſtands,</l>
               <l>What have the wretched Girles diſcern'd, ſaith ſhee,</l>
               <l>That men are a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m'd, and they unarmed bee?</l>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:60466:45"/>
               <l>Two books have made them Artiſts, here's a part,</l>
               <l>Remain to bee inſtructed by thy Art.</l>
               <l>Who to's (9) <hi>Therapuean</hi> Bride reproach did raiſe</l>
               <l>Since on a happy Lyre hath ſung her praiſe.</l>
               <l>If you be wiſe, don't handſome Maids diſdain,</l>
               <l>But whilſt you live labour their grace to gain.</l>
               <l>This ſaid, her head being bound with Myrtle, ſhee</l>
               <l>Did pluck a leaf, and gave ſome grains to mee.</l>
               <l>Wee feel the ſacred gift, Heaven brighter ſhines,</l>
               <l>And at this time all care my breaſt declines.</l>
               <l>Ladies whil'ſt wits be ripe, my Arts require,</l>
               <l>What modeſty, her law, and rites inſpire.</l>
               <l>Remember that old age will come, and ſo</l>
               <l>You'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> let no time from you neglected go:</l>
               <l>Whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>'ſt youthful age permits it, you muſt play,</l>
               <l>Years like to current waters ſteal away.</l>
               <l>For to recall paſt ſtreams, it is in vain,</l>
               <l>Nor ſhall an hour once paſt return again.</l>
               <l>Lay hold on time, which goes, and comes no more;</l>
               <l>So pleafing follows not as went before.</l>
               <l>Theſe withered ſtems I Violets have ſeen,</l>
               <l>From this bare Thorn I've got a Garland green.</l>
               <l>The time will come, thou that doſt love deny,</l>
               <l>Grown old, forſaken in thy bed ſhalt lye.</l>
               <l>Ith' night thy door ſhall not with blows be preſt,</l>
               <l>Nor th' entrance in the morn with Roſes dreſt.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Alas how ſoon the face lets furrows in,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And colour fades, though ſet in pureſt skin.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Your treſſes will grow thin, and you will ſay,</l>
               <l>That from a childe they ever have been gray.</l>
               <l>Snakes with their skins do caſt their age off too,</l>
               <l>And Harts their horns being caſt, their ſtrength re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new.</l>
               <l>Helpleſs your time doth poſt to get, don't ſtay,</l>
               <l>The flower which ungot doth ſoon decay.</l>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:60466:45"/>
               <l>Childbirth makes youth to age the ſooner yeeld,</l>
               <l>Continual harveſts make a barren field.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Luna</hi> at her (10) <hi>Endimion</hi> did not bluſh,</l>
               <l>Nor is <hi>Aurora</hi> 'ſham'd of (11) <hi>Cephalus.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Venus,</hi> to paſs by <hi>Adon',</hi> how, tell mee,</l>
               <l>Had'ſt thou <hi>Aeneas</hi> and <hi>Hermione?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To follow goddeſs waies yee mortals try,</l>
               <l>Nor to deſiring men your ſweets deny.</l>
               <l>Though they unconſtant prove, what do you loſe?</l>
               <l>No loſs at all, though thouſand times they uſe.</l>
               <l>Iron will wear, and Flint by uſe grows leſs,</l>
               <l>No fear of that parts loſs doth ere oppreſs.</l>
               <l>To light at others Torches who'l diſdain;</l>
               <l>Or who the vaſt Sea labours to reſtrain?</l>
               <l>Some women do not profit, thus they'l ſpeak,</l>
               <l>What? is all water loſt but what you take?</l>
               <l>My Art none proſtitutes, but doth reprove</l>
               <l>Your idle fears, no loſs proceeds from love.</l>
               <l>Soft Gales ſerve whil'ſt ith' Haven we do ride,</l>
               <l>But ſtronger winds, when in deep floods wee glide.</l>
               <l>I with their dreſs begin, trimm'd Vines abound</l>
               <l>With Wine, and rank Corn grows in well till'd ground.</l>
               <l>Form is Gods gift, and all thereof are glad,</l>
               <l>Although the greater part that gilt ne're had.</l>
               <l>Care will give beauty, which neglect decaies,</l>
               <l>Were it like to th' <hi>Idalian</hi> goddeſſes.</l>
               <l>Though Maids of old did not take ſo much care,</l>
               <l>Nor men ſuch curious apparel wear.</l>
               <l>What if <hi>Andromache's</hi> cloaths did not ſurpaſs,</l>
               <l>No mar'l, her husband a blunt ſouldier was.</l>
               <l>What ſhould the wife of <hi>Ajax,</hi> unto whom</l>
               <l>A ſevenfold ſhield was made, adorned come?</l>
               <l>Formerly they were rude, now <hi>Rome</hi> doth riſe,</l>
               <l>And th' wealth of all the conquer'd world injoyes.</l>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:60466:46"/>
               <l>The (12) <hi>Capitol</hi> with all that it hath ſee,</l>
               <l>And you will ſay, it might <hi>Jove</hi>'s Palace be.</l>
               <l>The (13) <hi>Curia,</hi> worthy ſuch a Councel gain'd,</l>
               <l>Was covered with ſtraw when <hi>Tatius</hi> reign'd.</l>
               <l>Theſe Palaces that glitter 'gainſt the Sun</l>
               <l>Were places once for beaſts to graze upon.</l>
               <l>I'm b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n in the laſt age, I'm glad of it;</l>
               <l>Old <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> pleaſe ſome, theſe do my humours fit.</l>
               <l>Not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> gold is found in the earths womb,</l>
               <l>Nor 'cauſe that Pear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s from divers ſhoars do come;</l>
               <l>Not becauſe Marble from the Hills wee dig,</l>
               <l>Nor 'cauſe wee Veſſels to the green Sea rig.</l>
               <l>But 'cauſe w'are civiliz'd, neatneſs maintain,</l>
               <l>Nor antient rudeneſs to our times remain.</l>
               <l>Your cars with ſtones too coſtly do not ſtore,</l>
               <l>Which the tann'd <hi>Indian</hi> gathers on the ſhoar.</l>
               <l>In cloth of gold, grave women, do not joy:</l>
               <l>That wealth by which you ſeek us, oft lay by.</l>
               <l>Neatneſs will take, your hairs in order place,</l>
               <l>It is the hand that makes or marrs a face.</l>
               <l>There's more than one dreſs, that which is moſt cult</l>
               <l>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke choice of, but firſt with your glaſs conſult.</l>
               <l>Long vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ag'd with a parted hair ſhows well,</l>
               <l>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aodamin</hi>'s treſſes did excel,</l>
               <l>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> that round viſag'd are diſcloſe their ears,</l>
               <l>And in their for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>head a ſmall peak appears.</l>
               <l>Here one doth with her hair neglected ſtand,</l>
               <l>Such thou art <hi>Phoebus</hi> with thy Lyre in hand.</l>
               <l>Another like <hi>Diana</hi> is attir'd,</l>
               <l>When ſheet' oretake a frighted beaſt deſir'd.</l>
               <l>It becom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s this to waft her hair ith' wind,</l>
               <l>And that it doth impede her looks to binde.</l>
               <l>This bedeckt with <hi>Cyllenian</hi> ſhells is brave,</l>
               <l>And that an Apron wears like to a wave.</l>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:60466:46"/>
               <l>You cannot count leaves on well branching trees,</l>
               <l>Nor number <hi>Alpine</hi> Beaſts, or <hi>Hybla</hi>'s Bees:</l>
               <l>Nor can I every dreſſing repreſent,</l>
               <l>Each day doth ſeveral new Modes invent.</l>
               <l>Neglected hair doth many grace, you'l ſay,</l>
               <l>What's newly comb'd was not ſince yeſterday.</l>
               <l>Art covers much, <hi>Iole Alcides</hi> ſpies,</l>
               <l>No ſooner ſeen, but I'm in love, hee cries.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Bacchus</hi> for thee (14) forſaken <hi>Gnoſſis,</hi> cares,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Satyrs</hi> rejoycing into's Chariot bears.</l>
               <l>O how indulgent nature is to you,</l>
               <l>How many waies you may things loſt renew!</l>
               <l>If bald, or hair through age fall off as faſt</l>
               <l>As leaves from trees blown with a Northern blaſt:</l>
               <l>Or gray, it may with <hi>German</hi> herbs dy'd ore</l>
               <l>Receive a better tincture than before.</l>
               <l>Some women will, that have their hair well grown,</l>
               <l>Wear others, and for gain cut off their own.</l>
               <l>Shame not to buy't in publick; I've ſeen ſome</l>
               <l>Openly 'mongſt a throng of Virgins come:</l>
               <l>Why ſtay I upon cloaths, ruffs do not buy,</l>
               <l>Nor Wooll that's twice dipt in a <hi>Tyrian</hi> dye,</l>
               <l>When enow colours are at cheaper rates:</l>
               <l>They're mad that on their backs wear their eſtates.</l>
               <l>Behold the colour of the sky, when clear,</l>
               <l>And in the warm South no dark clouds appear.</l>
               <l>Or (15) <hi>Phryxus</hi> colour chooſe, which hee, 'tis ſaid,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Helle</hi> got by <hi>Ino</hi>'s craft betray'd.</l>
               <l>This's like a wave, and thence a name it had,</l>
               <l>With this I do beleeve Sea-Nymphs are clad.</l>
               <l>That yellow imitates, the Goddeſſe ſhines</l>
               <l>In yellow, that th' (16) light-bringing horſes joyns.</l>
               <l>This Purple <hi>Amethiſt,</hi> this <hi>Paphian</hi> green,</l>
               <l>As th' <hi>Thracian</hi> Crane, or as white Roſes ſeen.</l>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:60466:47"/>
               <l>Acorns and Almonds <hi>Amarillis</hi> pull:</l>
               <l>Some kinde of wax doth give a name to wooll.</l>
               <l>As many Flowers as in the Spring earth bears,</l>
               <l>When Vines put forth, and the cold winter wears:</l>
               <l>So many Dyes wooll takes, what doth become</l>
               <l>Chuſe: any colour ſutes not well with ſome.</l>
               <l>For brown light colours, fair <hi>Briſeis</hi> ſad:</l>
               <l>And ſhee that's raviſht is in mourning clad.</l>
               <l>White becomes black, it pleaſ'd <hi>Cepheus,</hi> who</l>
               <l>In ſuch Attire did to <hi>Seriphos</hi> go.</l>
               <l>How oft I've warn'd that luſt do not prevail,</l>
               <l>Nor that long hairs do your rough leggs aſſail.</l>
               <l>I do not teach the Girls of <hi>Caucaſus,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That drink the ſtreams of <hi>Myſian Caicus.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>What? muſt I teach your teeth, how to keep fair,</l>
               <l>Or t' waſh your mouth each morn in water clear?</l>
               <l>You, how with wax to make them whiter know:</l>
               <l>What is not red by Nature, Art makes ſo.</l>
               <l>By Art the wrinckle of the brow's unſpyde,</l>
               <l>A little leather hollow cheeks will hide.</l>
               <l>Be not aſham'd flames in your eyes to ſhow</l>
               <l>With Saffron, which doth nigh to <hi>Cydnus</hi> grow.</l>
               <l>I've writ one little book, yet great for care,</l>
               <l>In which I teach loſt beauties to repair.</l>
               <l>Ye blemiſht Maids from hence your helps obtain:</l>
               <l>My Art hath alwaies for your goods took pain.</l>
               <l>Let not your Lovers finde your Boxes laid</l>
               <l>Upon the Table, Art conceal'd will aid.</l>
               <l>Whom will not painting of the face offend,</l>
               <l>Which laid too thick doth to the boſome tend?</l>
               <l>How <hi>Oeſipum</hi> doth ſmell, though ſent from <hi>Greece,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Being dry, 'tis taken from a dirty fleece.</l>
               <l>My advice is, not openly to take</l>
               <l>Dee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>'s marrow, or your foul teeth whiter make.</l>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:60466:47"/>
               <l>They grace a face, but odious be to ſight,</l>
               <l>Many things doing loathe, though done delight.</l>
               <l>Th' Statue which does for th' work of <hi>Myron</hi> paſs,</l>
               <l>Sometimes a ſhapeleſs and hard ſubſtance was.</l>
               <l>To make a Ring, the Gold is beaten full:</l>
               <l>The clothes you wear ſometime were baltered wool.</l>
               <l>The ſtone was rough ſhould ſhadow nobleneſs,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Venus</hi> naked in a ſhower expreſs.</l>
               <l>Adorn your ſelves, when faſt aſleep wee deem:</l>
               <l>Dreſt by a curious hand you'l fairer ſeem.</l>
               <l>Why ſhould I know the cauſe you look ſo fair;</l>
               <l>Be private when you do your looks prepare.</l>
               <l>Men ſhould not all things know, they hate the ſight</l>
               <l>Of things, that don't if unconceal'd, delight.</l>
               <l>The guilded ſtreamers ore the ſtage, behold,</l>
               <l>Waving, and th' wood ore-laid with thin leaf-gold.</l>
               <l>No people there, before 'tis fram'd, muſt ſit,</l>
               <l>And whil'ſt 'tis making, it will none admit.</l>
               <l>I don't forbid in publick t' dreſs your head;</l>
               <l>Nor that your locks your dainty neck ore-ſpread.</l>
               <l>But that you be not peeviſh then beware,</l>
               <l>Nor do too oft untie your looſened hair.</l>
               <l>I hate thoſe Ladies that their Maids will bite,</l>
               <l>Scratch them ith' face, and with their Bodkins fight.</l>
               <l>Being blooded it will make her curſe and ſwear,</l>
               <l>And crying, lug her Miſtreſs hateful hair.</l>
               <l>Shee that's ill-hair'd, to lock her door had beſt,</l>
               <l>Or alwaies be in ſome cloſe Cloyſter dreſt.</l>
               <l>I ſuddenly my Miſtreſs came upon,</l>
               <l>Surpriz'd her hair ſhe wrong ſide out clapt on.</l>
               <l>Let ſuch diſgraces happen to my foe,</l>
               <l>And the like ſhame to <hi>Parthian</hi> women go.</l>
               <l>Lame may their cattel be, their paſture bare,</l>
               <l>May their trees have no leaves, their heads no hair.</l>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:60466:48"/>
               <l>Nor <hi>Semele,</hi> nor <hi>Leda</hi> need bee taught,</l>
               <l>Nor (17) ſhe, whom a feign'd Oxe to <hi>Sidon</hi> brought.</l>
               <l>Nor <hi>Hellen,</hi> whom <hi>Atrides</hi> would regain,</l>
               <l>And whom thou <hi>Trojan Paris</hi> doſt detain.</l>
               <l>Both fair and foul come to learn from my Art,</l>
               <l>But ſtill the fairer are the leſſer part.</l>
               <l>The fair to learn my Precepts have leſs need,</l>
               <l>Their Beauty is a gift doth Art exceed.</l>
               <l>The Sea compoſ'd Sea-men at eaſe may lye,</l>
               <l>But when it ſwells, muſt all their skill imply.</l>
               <l>Moſt faces have ſome faults, which hide and doo</l>
               <l>As much as may be, mend your body too.</l>
               <l>If low, ſit down, leſt ſtanding you ſhould ſhow</l>
               <l>As though you ſate; or to a bed couch, go,</l>
               <l>Where being thrown, that none your ſtature ſpy,</l>
               <l>Upon your feet let ſome looſe mantle lye.</l>
               <l>Shee that's too ſmall, may have a vail, which caſt</l>
               <l>About her ſhoulders, hangs beneath her waſte.</l>
               <l>Shee that's too pale, with Purple dye her cheek,</l>
               <l>Shee that is black, the <hi>Pharian</hi> fiſh muſt ſeek.</l>
               <l>An ill-ſhap't foot hide in a dainty ſhooe,</l>
               <l>Nor from your meaſled leggs your ſtrings undo.</l>
               <l>Her that's crook-ſhoulder'd, ſtuffings will prefer,</l>
               <l>A breaſt too flat's rail'd with a ſtomacher.</l>
               <l>What ere ſhee ſaies, be ſure ſhee point at none,</l>
               <l>Whoſe hands are fat, or nails be dirty grown.</l>
               <l>She muſt, whoſe breath's unſweet, not faſting ſpeak,</l>
               <l>Neither a ſeat too neer her ſervant take,</l>
               <l>If your teeth black, or out of order grow,</l>
               <l>Take heed leſt you ſhould them by laughing ſhow.</l>
               <l>Who'd think that Ladies ſhould be taught to laugh;</l>
               <l>Yet that done handſomely will ſet them off.</l>
               <l>Let not much mirth your hollow cheeks reveal,</l>
               <l>And ever with your lips your teeth conceal.</l>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:60466:48"/>
               <l>Your bodies with much laughter do not ſtrain,</l>
               <l>Y'are loud at any thing that's light and vain.</l>
               <l>Some will in laughing draw their mouth awry,</l>
               <l>Others do frame a face as they would cry.</l>
               <l>And ſuch a ditty make with their rude voice,</l>
               <l>(18) As when an Aſs at th'Mill doth make a noiſe.</l>
               <l>Whither will not Art extend? women are taught,</l>
               <l>And how to weep in handſome manner brought.</l>
               <l>In ſome 'tis handſome not to ſpeak ſo plain,</l>
               <l>But to liſp out, their tongue ſome words conſtrain.</l>
               <l>It is a handſome fault, and pleaſeth more,</l>
               <l>To learn to ſpeak leſs than they could before.</l>
               <l>When theſe do profit you, approve my care;</l>
               <l>And with a ſtately ſtep your body bear.</l>
               <l>There is a ſtate in going, which doth take,</l>
               <l>Carriage doth Lovers, or Neglecters make.</l>
               <l>This moves by Art, the wind her garment ſwells,</l>
               <l>And being proud, ſhee in her gate excels.</l>
               <l>That looking ruddy like an <hi>Umbrian</hi> Bride,</l>
               <l>Doth in her walking take a ſpacious ſtride.</l>
               <l>But there a ruſtick mode in this may be,</l>
               <l>One rudely walks, another leiſurely.</l>
               <l>Let both your ſhoulders and your neck be bare</l>
               <l>For them to ſee, which your admirers are.</l>
               <l>But this white skins muſt do at th'ſight of this</l>
               <l>I uſe, as far as it is nak't, to kiſs.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Syrens</hi> (Sea-monſters) with their notes could ſtay</l>
               <l>A floating ſhip, if it came that away.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ulyſſes</hi> hearing theſe, did neer relax</l>
               <l>His body, his (19) friends ears cloſe ſtopt with wax.</l>
               <l>All (20) learn to ſing, for ſinging is a grace,</l>
               <l>The voice is oft a pander to the face.</l>
               <l>Now repeat what you from the ſtage did bring,</l>
               <l>And then a verſe in wandring meaſures ſing.</l>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:60466:49"/>
               <l>Ladies in (20) Muſick alſo ſhould have skill,</l>
               <l>Their left hands hold a harp, their right a quill.</l>
               <l>Wilde beaſts and ſtones at (21) <hi>Orpheus</hi> harp did ſtir,</l>
               <l>The lake of hell, and the three-headed Cur.</l>
               <l>Thou juſt revenger of thy Mothers fall,</l>
               <l>The ſtones themſelves at thy voice made a wall.</l>
               <l>The Fiſh are thought the Muſick to deſire,</l>
               <l>In the known fable of <hi>Arions</hi> Lyre.</l>
               <l>Learn with your hand the Pſaltery to ſtrike,</l>
               <l>To that, for muſick ſweet, no muſick's like.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Callimachus,</hi> and <hi>Coan</hi> Poets ſcan,</l>
               <l>Or th' <hi>Tejan</hi> wanton muſe of the old man.</l>
               <l>The wanton <hi>Sappho</hi> read, you alſo may</l>
               <l>Read <hi>Geta</hi>'s Father, who ſo well could play.</l>
               <l>And thou <hi>Tibullus</hi> read <hi>Propertius</hi> verſe,</l>
               <l>Or ſome of <hi>Gallus,</hi> or thine own rehearſe.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Phryxus</hi> thy Siſters golden fleece ſo fam'd</l>
               <l>By <hi>Varro</hi> muſt amongſt the reſt be nam'd.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aeneas</hi> flight, th'Original of <hi>Rome,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>No extant work more fam'd in <hi>Latium.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>My name perhaps amongſt the reſt is found,</l>
               <l>My writings ſhall not be in <hi>Lethe</hi> drown'd.</l>
               <l>Read over, ſome ſhall ſay, our Maſters charms</l>
               <l>So excellent, where hee both Sexes arms.</l>
               <l>Or the three books which ſtil'd <hi>Amorum</hi> be,</l>
               <l>Muſt with an active eye be ſearcht by thee.</l>
               <l>With a clear voice ſing his Epiſtles ore,</l>
               <l>Which hee did make, unknown to all before.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Phoebus</hi> grant this, yee Deities divine,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Bacchus</hi> renown'd, grant this yee Muſes nine.</l>
               <l>I alſo (21) dancing in young Ladies love,</l>
               <l>As you are taught, your active fingers move.</l>
               <l>Motion upon the ſtage doth chiefly take,</l>
               <l>Their very action them a grace doth ſpeak.</l>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:60466:49"/>
               <l>Small things I ſhame to teach, as how to name</l>
               <l>A caſt at Dice, or how to throw the ſame.</l>
               <l>Sometimes ſhee caſts three Dice, well skill'd what throws</l>
               <l>Should lye at bottome, what to call for knows.</l>
               <l>At Cheſs ſhee muſt play heedfully, be wiſe</l>
               <l>Her man is taken with two enemies.</l>
               <l>A man by odds ſurpriz'd may move, but then</l>
               <l>Returning, oft renews the game agen.</l>
               <l>Light (22) balls muſt alſo be with rackets ſtruck,</l>
               <l>And you muſt ſtir no balls, but what you took.</l>
               <l>Play ſuch a trick at Cards, by which appear</l>
               <l>How many months are in the moving year.</l>
               <l>How on a board three ſtones on each ſide lye,</l>
               <l>Which ſhee keeps laſt, that gets the victory.</l>
               <l>Uſe many ſports, to ſport young Beauties know;</l>
               <l>For oftentimes love takes deep rooting ſo.</l>
               <l>It is an eaſie thing to uſe your throws,</l>
               <l>But harder far your carriage to compoſe.</l>
               <l>They are unwiſe that play with too much care,</l>
               <l>Then oftentimes their breaſts too open are.</l>
               <l>They'l rage unhandſomely, contend and brawl,</l>
               <l>And for their winnings will at variance fall.</l>
               <l>To make a clamorous noiſe it doth diſpleaſe,</l>
               <l>Or t' call th' offended gods for witneſſes.</l>
               <l>There is no faith at Tables found: how I</l>
               <l>Have ſeen ſome at their games to fret and cry:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Jove</hi> grant that none may ſo themſelves diſcover</l>
               <l>That any care would take to pleaſe a Lover.</l>
               <l>Theſe idle ſports nature to women gave,</l>
               <l>But men muſt far more active pleaſures have.</l>
               <l>To toſs a ball, or ſhoot in bows well tride,</l>
               <l>To learn to fence, or a proud horſe to ride.</l>
               <l>Maids muſt not in the fields, or cold air go,</l>
               <l>Or upon Seas, that do unpleaſing flow.</l>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:60466:50"/>
               <l>But they may gently walk in <hi>Pompey</hi>'s ſhade,</l>
               <l>When hot by <hi>Phoebus, Virgo</hi>'s head is made.</l>
               <l>Or walk in <hi>Laureat Peans</hi> Palaces</l>
               <l>That <hi>Paretonian</hi> ſhips ſunk in the Seas.</l>
               <l>Which things his Siſter and his Wife had found,</l>
               <l>Whilſt his head was with naval honours crown'd.</l>
               <l>The Altars of the <hi>Memphian</hi> heifer ſee,</l>
               <l>Or the three Theaters that famous be.</l>
               <l>See the (23) <hi>Arena</hi> ſprinkled with warm gore,</l>
               <l>Or the Goal by th' hot Chariot wheel run ore.</l>
               <l>What is unſeen's unknown, no love profeſt,</l>
               <l>'Tis pity a good face ſhould want a teſt.</l>
               <l>If <hi>Orpheus</hi> or <hi>Thamyras</hi> you ſurpaſs</l>
               <l>In ſinging, yet unknown, you get no grace.</l>
               <l>Had <hi>Venus</hi> not been drawn b' <hi>Apelles</hi> skill,</l>
               <l>Shee in the waves had layn forgotten ſtill.</l>
               <l>What do the ſacred Poets ſeek but fame,</l>
               <l>The cuſp of which is onely all our aim.</l>
               <l>Formerly Poets were by Kings maintain'd.</l>
               <l>And rich gifts have the ancient <hi>Chori</hi> gain'd.</l>
               <l>Their names were celebrated with regard,</l>
               <l>Then they did Poets with ſtor'd gold reward.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Callabrian Ennius</hi> deſerv'd to be</l>
               <l>Great <hi>Scipio</hi> contiguous to thee.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Ivy</hi> without honour lies, a name</l>
               <l>Of Idleneſs uſurps the Muſes fame.</l>
               <l>Fame muſt awake it ſelf, had <hi>Homer</hi> ſlept,</l>
               <l>Eternal fame his <hi>Iliads</hi> had not kept.</l>
               <l>Had <hi>Danaë</hi> all company refrain'd</l>
               <l>Till old, ſhe might have in her Tower remain'd.</l>
               <l>Fair creatures, it will much advantage you,</l>
               <l>Often to walk out into publick view.</l>
               <l>The Wolf for one prey to the whole flock hies:</l>
               <l>At a whole team of fowl <hi>Joves</hi> Eagles flies:</l>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:60466:50"/>
               <l>Let a fair Maid in publick place be found,</l>
               <l>One ſhee perchance may 'mongſt amany wound.</l>
               <l>Be ſtudious to pleaſe in every place,</l>
               <l>To get a fame, act all things with a grace:</l>
               <l>'Tis accidental: ſtill hold out a hook,</l>
               <l>Where you leaſt think ſometimes a fiſh is took.</l>
               <l>The hills in vain ſometimes by Hounds are ſought,</l>
               <l>Whil'ſt that a Hart unforc't ith' Net is caught.</l>
               <l>What could <hi>Andromede</hi> leſs hope than that</l>
               <l>Her tears ſhould any Lover penetrate?</l>
               <l>Oft at a Husbands grave a new one's gain'd,</l>
               <l>Her careleſs head and tears will grace though feign'd.</l>
               <l>Avoid thoſe men that over-curious are,</l>
               <l>That do their locks in mode and figure wear.</l>
               <l>What to a thouſand they to you will ſay,</l>
               <l>And in no place their wandring loves will ſtay.</l>
               <l>What won't a woman, when a man's more light;</l>
               <l>Though to have other men perchance ſhee might.</l>
               <l>You'l ſcarce beleeve, yet truſt, <hi>Troy</hi> had not fell</l>
               <l>If <hi>Priams</hi> Councel th'had obſerved well.</l>
               <l>There be under pretence of love that cheat,</l>
               <l>And onely gain baſely deſire to get.</l>
               <l>Let not the hair deceive with <hi>Jeſſamy,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nor the ſmall Bracelets which unfolded lye.</l>
               <l>Be not deceiv'd with clothes that do adorn,</l>
               <l>Nor all the Rings upon his fingers worn.</l>
               <l>Perhaps this ſpruce youth may a cheater be,</l>
               <l>And more in love with thy fine clothes, than thee.</l>
               <l>Give mee my own, oft Maids deſpoil'd of all,</l>
               <l>Reſtore my clothes, will through the <hi>Forum</hi> call.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Appiades</hi> and <hi>Venus</hi> did behold</l>
               <l>Theſe ſtrifes from Temples bright with burniſht gold.</l>
               <l>There are ſome Ladies <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> diſhoneſt fame,</l>
               <l>From many faithleſs learn to be the ſame.</l>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:60466:51"/>
               <l>By others, fear leſt you ſhould once complain,</l>
               <l>No man accounted faithleſs, entertain.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Athenians</hi> truſt not <hi>Theſius</hi> though hee ſwear,</l>
               <l>Whom hee invokes, gods of his making are.</l>
               <l>Right heir of <hi>Theſeus</hi> crime <hi>Demophoon</hi> thou</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Phyllis</hi> deceived'ſt: no faith remaineth now.</l>
               <l>Make vows to them, if they make vows to you</l>
               <l>If they perform, perform your promiſe too.</l>
               <l>Shee may as well extinguiſh (24) <hi>Veſta</hi>'s fire,</l>
               <l>And from the Temple ſacred things deſire,</l>
               <l>For men <hi>Aconitum</hi> with Hemlock bruiſe,</l>
               <l>As <hi>Venus,</hi> once reward receiv'd, refuſe,</l>
               <l>Hold in the reign my Muſe, I'l come to thee,</l>
               <l>Nor with the moving wheel diſturbed be.</l>
               <l>Let letters try the foord firſt, written fair,</l>
               <l>And a fit meſſenger thoſe letters bear.</l>
               <l>Obſerve his language as you read it ore,</l>
               <l>Whether hee feign, or from his heart implore.</l>
               <l>After ſome time write back to him, delay</l>
               <l>Doth love increaſe if not too long you ſtay.</l>
               <l>Give not your ſelf away too eaſily,</l>
               <l>Nor ſtifly, what hee ſhall requeſt, deny.</l>
               <l>Make him both fear and hope as oft as you</l>
               <l>Remit his faults, make him leſs fearful too.</l>
               <l>Write handſome words in an accuſtom'd phraſe,</l>
               <l>And a ſmoothe ſtile, neat form of ſpeech gets praiſe.</l>
               <l>Lovers at dubious words are oft-times wilde,</l>
               <l>Without good language a fair face is ſpoil'd.</l>
               <l>Though you the (25) honoured <hi>Vittae</hi> do not wear</l>
               <l>Your ſervants oft by you deceived are.</l>
               <l>By Boys or Maids you may your Letters ſend,</l>
               <l>But to no Lover any gifts commend.</l>
               <l>How I have ſeen Maids at ſuch loſs look pale,</l>
               <l>And ſorrow ever after, them aſſail.</l>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:60466:51"/>
               <l>Hee's faithleſs truly that ſuch gifts detains,</l>
               <l>But his breaſt burning <hi>Aetna</hi>-like remains.</l>
               <l>To repel fraud, let fraud be uſed now,</l>
               <l>Arms againſt Arms to take, the Laws allow.</l>
               <l>T'write many hands you may your ſelves inure,</l>
               <l>They're loſt that would ſuch things from mee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure.</l>
               <l>Unleſs his ſeal you break, write not again;</l>
               <l>Nor let one Letter ſeveral hands contain.</l>
               <l>Ladies the Writers loves, ſubſcrib'd muſt be:</l>
               <l>Think oft on her, that often thinks on thee.</l>
               <l>If wee from ſmall to great our minds may lead,</l>
               <l>And our full ſails in curved Havens ſpread.</l>
               <l>It concerns beauty anger to aſſwage,</l>
               <l>Peace becomes men, 'tis fit for beaſts to rage.</l>
               <l>Rage ſwells the cheek, black blood ith' veins doth ſtart,</l>
               <l>Makes eyes look like to angry <hi>Gorgons</hi> dart.</l>
               <l>Hence rage, a pipe's not ſo much worth to mee,</l>
               <l>Said <hi>Pallas,</hi> who her ſelf ith' brook did ſee.</l>
               <l>Ith' height of rage, if to a Glaſs you go,</l>
               <l>Your face to be the ſame you'l hardly know.</l>
               <l>A proud and ſtately look no Lover brooks,</l>
               <l>Love is increaſed moſt with gentle looks.</l>
               <l>Too much diſdain wee hate (truſt one that knows)</l>
               <l>The countenance the ſeed of hate oft ſows.</l>
               <l>If hee looks, look; and if hee ſmile, ſmile too:</l>
               <l>Make ſigns to him, if hee makes ſigns to you.</l>
               <l>Thus whil'ſt hee toyes, the Boy his wand forſakes</l>
               <l>Sharp (26) pointed Arrows from his quiver takes.</l>
               <l>Wee love none ſad, <hi>Ajax Tegmeſſa</hi> lov'd,</l>
               <l>With ſprightful Ladies cheerful men are mov'd.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Andromache, Tegmeſſa</hi> unto mee,</l>
               <l>Neither of you two ſhould a Miſtreſs be.</l>
               <l>I ſcarce beleeve (but that a birth doth ſhow)</l>
               <l>You to your husbands ere in bed you go.</l>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:60466:52"/>
               <l>But <hi>Ajax</hi> melancholy wife hath ſaid,</l>
               <l>Light of my ſoul, which a glad husband made.</l>
               <l>Who will examples from great things refuſe,</l>
               <l>Or any great Commanders name not uſe?</l>
               <l>That this a Troop gives to be diſciplin'd,</l>
               <l>Horſe-men to this, enſigns to that aſſign'd.</l>
               <l>Look ſo on us for what uſe each one ſhews</l>
               <l>To fit the beſt, in his ſure place diſpoſe.</l>
               <l>Let rich men give, and hee that reads the Laws,</l>
               <l>Being eloquent, defend a Clients cauſe.</l>
               <l>Wee that are Poets only verſes ſend,</l>
               <l>Who before others do to love pretend.</l>
               <l>Wee ſpread abroad the praiſe of a ſweet face,</l>
               <l>Wee honour <hi>Nemeſis,</hi> wee <hi>Cynthia</hi> grace.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Orient</hi> and <hi>Occident</hi> knew <hi>Lycoris,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Many inquire who my <hi>Corinna</hi> is.</l>
               <l>Dece it is not by ſacred Poets uſ'd,</l>
               <l>But by our Arts good manners are infuſ'd.</l>
               <l>Nor pride doth us induce, nor love of gain,</l>
               <l>Wee for a bed or grove all ſports refrain.</l>
               <l>W'are eaſily caught, wee burn with fervent heat,</l>
               <l>And our affections are as firm as great.</l>
               <l>Nature by curious Art is gentler made,</l>
               <l>By exerciſe behaviour will bee had.</l>
               <l>Ladies kinde to <hi>Aonian</hi> Poets prove,</l>
               <l>All power they have, and them the Moſes love.</l>
               <l>A God is in us, wee with Heaven commerce,</l>
               <l>Hee doth his rayes from airery Seats diſperſe.</l>
               <l>'Tis ſin, with Poets riches to expect,</l>
               <l>Ah but alaſs! Maids do this ſin neglect.</l>
               <l>Yet at firſt ſight do not your ſelves diſcloſe,</l>
               <l>New Lovers will, the nets eſpy'd, oppoſe.</l>
               <l>Naggs that are newly mouth'd Grooms do not ride,</l>
               <l>With the ſame bits they well-way'd horſes gu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>de.</l>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:60466:52"/>
               <l>To catch one ſtay'd in years, and a young man,</l>
               <l>Neither the manner or ſame courſe is tane.</l>
               <l>Hee's rude, in Loves Tents never had a place,</l>
               <l>That as a new ſpoil would your bed imbrace.</l>
               <l>Hee knows none elſe, to you alone is bound,</l>
               <l>Great hedges muſt ſuch grain as this ſurround.</l>
               <l>Competitors remov'd, your love you'l gain,</l>
               <l>For love and rule no ſharers entertain.</l>
               <l>Old men do by degrees affection take,</l>
               <l>They will accept what young men will forſake.</l>
               <l>They'l force no doors, nor burn with boundleſs rage,</l>
               <l>Nor on their Miſtreſs face commit a ſtrage.</l>
               <l>Neither their own, or Miſtreſs clothes they'l tear,</l>
               <l>Nor ſhall th'have cauſe to wail their pluckt off hair.</l>
               <l>Such things thoſe act, with youthful flames incloſ'd,</l>
               <l>But theſe Loves Darts receive with breaſts compoſ'd.</l>
               <l>Old men like Torches into water put,</l>
               <l>Burn with a lingring fire, like wood new cut.</l>
               <l>Theſe Loves are ſure, thoſe ſhort, yet full of May,</l>
               <l>Then crop the fruit that will ſo ſoon decay.</l>
               <l>Open to th' foe, let all delivered bee,</l>
               <l>That faith may be found in diſſoyalty.</l>
               <l>Love eaſily granted will not long remain,</l>
               <l>Then ſome denials in ſweet language feign.</l>
               <l>Let him attend the gate, cry cruel door,</l>
               <l>Now threaten much, and then as much implore.</l>
               <l>Wee love not things too ſweet, ſharper are found</l>
               <l>To cure us: ſhips with too much wind are drown'd.</l>
               <l>This is the cauſe men do their wives neglect,</l>
               <l>They ſhew them at the firſt too much reſpect.</l>
               <l>Let th' Porter their acceſs ſometimes deny,</l>
               <l>For love neglected burns more ardently.</l>
               <l>Dull ſwords reject, now fight with active ſteel,</l>
               <l>I'm ſure the force of my own ſhafts to feel.</l>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:60466:53"/>
               <l>When the young Amouriſt falls in your ſnare,</l>
               <l>Hoping that none with him your love ſhall ſhare,</l>
               <l>Seeing a rival to participate,</l>
               <l>But for theſe Arts his love would ſoon rebate.</l>
               <l>The horſe, the (27) Barriers left runs well, if more</l>
               <l>Follow him cloſe at heels, or run before.</l>
               <l>Scorn will revive flames quite extinct, loe I</l>
               <l>Cannot love thoſe that cannot mee deny.</l>
               <l>Yet not to make him grieve much, or ſuppoſe</l>
               <l>Being troubled, there is more in't than hee knows.</l>
               <l>Your Porter may conſole and let him know</l>
               <l>Hee troubles more than hee hath cauſe to do.</l>
               <l>Pleaſure with ſafety purchaſed, leſs wee prize</l>
               <l>To be more free with <hi>Thais,</hi> fears deviſe.</l>
               <l>Though you might let him in at th'door, yet through</l>
               <l>The window take him, and ſeem frighted too.</l>
               <l>Inſtruct your ſubtil Maid to come in poſt,</l>
               <l>Cry hide the Gentleman, or w' are all loſt.</l>
               <l>Yet you muſt mix his fear with love, leſt hee</l>
               <l>Should think a night cannot worth ſo much be.</l>
               <l>I'd like to have omitted how you may</l>
               <l>Your Guardian and watchful Nurſe betray.</l>
               <l>Let wives their husbands fear, guard their own fame,</l>
               <l>Law, Duty, Modeſty command the ſame.</l>
               <l>Thee whom revenge hath ranſom'd who'l indure</l>
               <l>To be reſtrained, aid from my Art procure.</l>
               <l>Though <hi>Argus</hi> many eyes attend, you ſhall</l>
               <l>By giving fair words oculate them all.</l>
               <l>If by your Guardian you ſhould be deny'd</l>
               <l>To write, then (28) waters at fit time provide.</l>
               <l>What if your will-obeying Maid complies,</l>
               <l>And in her boſome doth a way deviſe</l>
               <l>To carry Letters, bring back in her ſhooe</l>
               <l>Delightful papers, what can Guardians do?</l>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:60466:53"/>
               <l>The Maid being of your Councel may give leave</l>
               <l>To write upon her back, which will receive</l>
               <l>Your characters, if them in (29) Milk you write,</l>
               <l>Rubb'd with a Coal are manifeſt to ſight.</l>
               <l>On Paper made of humid line well dreſt,</l>
               <l>Your characters may be unſeen expreſt.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Acriſius</hi> of his Daughter care did take,</l>
               <l>Yet ſhee a Grandfather of him did make.</l>
               <l>What can a Guardian, whil'ſt that Stages be</l>
               <l>Ith' City, whil'ſt you may horſe-courſes ſee?</l>
               <l>Or whil'ſt you may to (30) <hi>Pharian Iſis</hi> go,</l>
               <l>Buſied in ſacrifice, the reſt not ſo.</l>
               <l>Or whil'ſt the goddeſs from mens eyes if they</l>
               <l>Approach her uncommanded, turns away:</l>
               <l>Ladies the (31) Baths do many pleaſures hide,</l>
               <l>Then let your Guardian at the door abide</l>
               <l>Watching your Gown; or elſe feign a diſeaſe,</l>
               <l>So to your Chamber admit whom you pleaſe.</l>
               <l>Whil'ſt a falſe key may reach you what to do,</l>
               <l>Or a Poſtern a way deſired ſhew.</l>
               <l>A Guardian alſo is deceiv'd with Wine,</l>
               <l>Or with the Grap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s pluckt from the Spaniſh Vine.</l>
               <l>And there are ſoporiferous cups will keep,</l>
               <l>And drown'd their eyes in a Lethean ſleep.</l>
               <l>So him deſpiſ'd your complice doth not ſtay</l>
               <l>With lingring pleaſures, or a ſlow delay.</l>
               <l>But what need I ſo many waies preſcribe,</l>
               <l>Since with rewards you may your Keeper bribe:</l>
               <l>Gifts, truſt mee, will both men and gods beguile,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Jove</hi> himſelf will at an offering ſmile.</l>
               <l>What do the wiſe ſince fools do preſents love,</l>
               <l>Hee that reward receives, will ſecret prove.</l>
               <l>Your Keeper purchaſ'd once, hee's ever ſo,</l>
               <l>Hee'l ne're refuſe that aid hee once did ſhow.</l>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:60466:54"/>
               <l>Of your companions I am to complain,</l>
               <l>That hurt, to men doth not alone pertain.</l>
               <l>Beleeve mee, they will of your pleaſures ſhare,</l>
               <l>And others Hounds purſue your wanton Hare.</l>
               <l>The Maids that doth about the beds attend,</l>
               <l>Truſt me, more times than one, hath been my friend.</l>
               <l>Keep not too fair a Maid, for oft-times ſhee</l>
               <l>Hath better than her Miſtreſs pleaſed mee.</l>
               <l>Fond man what do I; make my ſelf a prey,</l>
               <l>Open my breaſt to foes; my ſelf betray?</l>
               <l>Birds teach not Powlers how to be undone,</l>
               <l>Nor do the Deer inſtruct the Dogs to run.</l>
               <l>I'l publiſh this, which help to Maids affords,</l>
               <l>And arm them to my loſs with <hi>Lemnian</hi> ſwords.</l>
               <l>You may with eaſe make us beleeve y'are kind,</l>
               <l>The Amouriſts, with forward faiths, you'l finde.</l>
               <l>Look on your ſervant, ſigh and ask why hee</l>
               <l>Hath been from you ſo long; then let him ſee</l>
               <l>Some tears let fall, for him deep ſorrow feign,</l>
               <l>And in your countenance your fingers ſtain.</l>
               <l>Credulous and compaſſionate hee'l be,</l>
               <l>And ſay, ſhee doth this for the love of mee.</l>
               <l>If hee be ſpruce, and loves to look in's glaſs,</l>
               <l>Hee'l think the goddeſſes dote on his face.</l>
               <l>Grieve not though wrong do ne're ſo great appear,</l>
               <l>Neither be jealous though ſtrange things you hear.</l>
               <l>Truſt not to tales too ſoon, they injure love:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Procris</hi> example may no light thing prove.</l>
               <l>There is neer to (32) <hi>Hymertus</hi> Flowery head</l>
               <l>A ſacred ſpring, the earth with ſoft graſs ſpread:</l>
               <l>Low Groves, where <hi>Arbutes</hi> with the graſs do meet,</l>
               <l>Roſemary, Lawrel, ſhady Mirtle ſweet:</l>
               <l>There thick-leav'd Box, and Tamarix alſo,</l>
               <l>There the low Shrubs, and lofty Pine-trees grow.</l>
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:60466:54"/>
               <l>So many ſorts of leaves, graſs tops ſo fair</l>
               <l>Were ſhak't by <hi>Zephirus,</hi> a wholeſome Air.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cephalus</hi> grateful reſt, his Hounds forſook,</l>
               <l>The young man in this place his eaſe oft took.</l>
               <l>Come gentle moving Air, hee uſ'd to ſay,</l>
               <l>Come to my breaſt and fan this heat away.</l>
               <l>Some that by chance his words did over-hear,</l>
               <l>Bore back the ſound to his wives trembling ear.</l>
               <l>Air for a Harlots name, poor <hi>Procris</hi> gueſt,</l>
               <l>Swounding ſhee falls, with jealouſie poſſeſt.</l>
               <l>Looking as pale as Grapes late gathered,</l>
               <l>Or leaves with winters froſt enveloped.</l>
               <l>Pale as full Quinces which depreſs the Tree,</l>
               <l>Or Corn before 'tis fully ripe, can be.</l>
               <l>Her ſenſe return'd, ſhee tears her clothes, and now</l>
               <l>Her dainty cheeks, with her ſharp nails, doth plow.</l>
               <l>Baging, away ſhee hies, diſperſt her hair,</l>
               <l>Like <hi>Bacchus</hi> Prieſt that doth the <hi>Thirſis</hi> bear.</l>
               <l>When ſhe approacht the place, ſhe would take none,</l>
               <l>But ſilently enters the Wood alone.</l>
               <l>What wretched <hi>Procris</hi> had thy mind poſſeſt,</l>
               <l>To lurk, what ardour beat within thy breaſt?</l>
               <l>Thou thoughtſt that Air would come, whatever ſhe,</l>
               <l>And that her vertues ſhould diſcovered be.</l>
               <l>Thy coming grieves now 'cauſe thou wouldſt not take</l>
               <l>Now't pleaſeth, theſe unſtedfaſt love doth make.</l>
               <l>The place, name, guide command belief from thee,</l>
               <l>And what the mind fears, it concludes to be.</l>
               <l>Thus when ſhee ſaw the graſs with feet depreſt,</l>
               <l>Her trembling heart did beat againſt her breaſt.</l>
               <l>Now Middaies Sun gave ſhadows leſs extent</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ortus</hi> and <hi>Veſper</hi> equal in aſſent.</l>
               <l>Loe <hi>Cephalus Cyllene's</hi> ſtock to th' place</l>
               <l>Returns, and with ſpring-water cools his face:</l>
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:60466:55"/>
               <l>Sad <hi>Procris</hi> is conceal'd; oth' graſs being laid</l>
               <l>Come <hi>Zephyrus,</hi> come gentle Air, hee ſaid.</l>
               <l>Now when ſhee ſaw the error of the name</l>
               <l>Into her face a lively colour came.</l>
               <l>T'imbrace her husband ſhee in haſt doth riſe,</l>
               <l>And'mongſt the buſhes makes a ruſtling noiſe.</l>
               <l>Hee (the ſound heard) did for a wilde beaſt look,</l>
               <l>And bravely up his Bow and Arrows took.</l>
               <l>Wretch, 'tis no beaſt, what doſt? hold faſt thy dart;</l>
               <l>Ah mee! th' haſt ſtruck a woman to the heart.</l>
               <l>Ah thou haſt hit a faithful breaſt, ſaid ſhee,</l>
               <l>This place hath ever had a wound by thee.</l>
               <l>Before my day I dye, in jur'd by none,</l>
               <l>This place made mee ſuſpect thee faithleſs grown.</l>
               <l>From mee my breath, to Air ſuſpected, flies,</l>
               <l>I dye; with thy lov'd hand cloſe up my eyes.</l>
               <l>So ſaid, her breath her careleſs breaſt did leave,</l>
               <l>Which her unhappy husband did receive.</l>
               <l>Hee doth her dying in his arms imbrace,</l>
               <l>And with ſad tears waſheth the wound apace.</l>
               <l>But wee'l return, and in theſe things be plain,</l>
               <l>That her wiſht Port my wearied Keel may gain.</l>
               <l>You look to Banquets, I ſhould you conduct,</l>
               <l>And with fit poſtures for that place inſtruct.</l>
               <l>Come late, and in a handſome dreſs appear</l>
               <l>Not to be forward, ſpeaks moſt welcome there.</l>
               <l>If you be black, yet there you'l ſeem moſt fair,</l>
               <l>I th' night all imperfections covered are.</l>
               <l>The manner muſt be learnt to carve and eat,</l>
               <l>Don't with your fingers oyl your face at meat.</l>
               <l>Feed not too much on dainties, but forbear,</l>
               <l>And rather let your ſtomach want i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s ſhare.</l>
               <l>Had <hi>Hellen</hi> greedy ſeem'd to <hi>Pari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ves,</l>
               <l>He would have loath'd, and diſeſteem'd his prize.</l>
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:60466:55"/>
               <l>To drink is far more handſome, Maids, for you,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Bacchus</hi> with <hi>Cupid</hi> joyn'd no hurt will do.</l>
               <l>Yet do not drink your heads to diſcompoſe,</l>
               <l>Nor till in your eyes, each thing double ſhows.</l>
               <l>Women will, madifi'd, with too much Wine,</l>
               <l>In any ſordid copulation joyn.</l>
               <l>Nor after meat lye down to eaſe your eyes,</l>
               <l>Many diſgraceful things from ſleep ariſe.</l>
               <l>I ſhame to teach you more, but <hi>Venus</hi> ſhee,</l>
               <l>Affirms our ſubject chiefly ſhame to be.</l>
               <l>Each one muſt actions from her body take,</l>
               <l>And poſtures all alike, you muſt not make.</l>
               <l>You that are fair, lye upwards with your face,</l>
               <l>Shew you your back to whom your back's a grace.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Melanion Attalanta</hi>'s legs between</l>
               <l>His ſhoulders bore, if neat they muſt be ſeen.</l>
               <l>Low women ride (33) <hi>Thebais</hi> being tall,</l>
               <l>Married, ne're ſate on <hi>Hector</hi>'s horſe at all.</l>
               <l>Shee that would have her curious waſte eſpyde,</l>
               <l>Muſt ſit upon the ſeat, her neck aſide.</l>
               <l>Shee whoſe ſweet form preſents no fault to th' eye,</l>
               <l>Careleſly ſtretcht upon the Couch may lye.</l>
               <l>Shame no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, like <hi>Phillis</hi> Mother, to untie,</l>
               <l>And 'bout your ſhoulders let your looſe hair fly.</l>
               <l>You on whoſe breaſts <hi>Lucina's</hi> wrinkles light,</l>
               <l>Like the ſwift <hi>Parthian,</hi> keep your back in ſight.</l>
               <l>Love hath a thouſand waies perform'd with eaſe,</l>
               <l>To lye half Supine oth' right ſide, may pleaſe.</l>
               <l>Not <hi>Phaebus Tripos,</hi> nor horn'd <hi>Ammon</hi> ſhows</l>
               <l>More Truth to you, than doth my Muſe diſcloſe.</l>
               <l>If there be truth in Art by long uſe gain'd,</l>
               <l>Beleeve't our verſes have that truth obtain'd.</l>
               <l>Women arriv'd at full maturity</l>
               <l>May theſe perceive, two ſharing equal joy.</l>
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:60466:56"/>
               <l>Nor pleaſing voices, nor ſweet tunes refuſe,</l>
               <l>And you ſometimes muſt amourous language uſe.</l>
               <l>You to whom nature <hi>Venus</hi> ſenſe denies,</l>
               <l>With a mendacious tongue pretend ſweet joyes.</l>
               <l>Unhappy Maid is ſhee whom ſenſe doth leave,</l>
               <l>Where man and woman equal ſweets receive.</l>
               <l>Yet let not them perceive that you do feign,</l>
               <l>And active motions will beleef obtain.</l>
               <l>To mention what doth pleaſe us beſt, forbear</l>
               <l>Modeſty bids, yet ſecret ſigns declare.</l>
               <l>Shee that reward, <hi>Venus</hi> perform'd, requires,</l>
               <l>Not that her prayers ſhould ere be herard deſires.</l>
               <l>Let not the light your marriage-beds come neer,</l>
               <l>Many things ſhould bee undiſcovered there.</l>
               <l>The Play is done, 'tis time they ſhould return</l>
               <l>That have our yoak upon their ſhoulders born.</l>
               <l>As youths before, my crowd of Maids write thus</l>
               <l>Upon your ſpoils, <hi>Ovid inſtructed us.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="annotations">
            <pb n="103" facs="tcp:60466:56"/>
            <head>Annotations upon the third Book OF <hi>Publius Ovidius Naſo, De Arte Amandi.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">(1) <hi>PEnthiſilia</hi> and) a Queen of the <hi>Amazones, Post Orythiam Penthiſilea regno potita eſt, cujus Trojano bello inter fortiſſimos viros, &amp;c.</hi> (ſaith <hi>Juſtin. lib.</hi> 2.) After <hi>Orythia Penthiſilia</hi> obtained the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Trojano bello inter fortiſſimos viros, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (ſaith <hi>Juſtin. lib.</hi> 2.) After <hi>Orythia Penthiſilia</hi> obtained the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, who amongſt the moſt couragious Captains in the <hi>Trojan</hi> war, made large proof of her valour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Grecians.</hi> Shee was ſlain before <hi>Troy,</hi> but by whom it is uncertain. <hi>Dyctis Cretenſis lib.</hi> 4. ſaith, <hi>Achilles inter equitum turmas Penthiſiliam nactus, hast a petit, &amp;c. Achilles</hi> amongſt the troops of horſe finding <hi>Penthiſilia</hi> wounded her with his ſpear; and dragging her miſerably by the hair, ſlew her. But <hi>Dares Phrygius</hi> ſaith, <hi>Penthiſilia Neoptolemum ſauciat, ille dolore accepto, amazonum ductricem Penthiſiliam obtruncat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now ſuch as ſhall deſire to know what theſe <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazons</hi> were, I ſhall indeavour to ſatisfie out of <hi>Juſtin. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Ulinos &amp; Scolopitus per factionem Opti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matum, dome pulſi, &amp;c.</hi> The two young Princes, <hi>Uli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos</hi> and <hi>Scolopitus</hi> being by the Primates of <hi>Scythia,</hi> expelled their Country, drew along with them a conſiderable company of young men, who ſeating themſelves in <hi>Capadocia</hi> neer the River <hi>Thermodon,</hi> occupied the fields of the <hi>Themiſcyrians,</hi> whom they
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:60466:57"/>had ſubjected, and for many years accuſtoming themſelves to rob and ſpoil their neighbouring con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fines, were at laſt ſet upon and ſlain by the people. The wives of theſe men perceiving all hopes of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity were in their husbands cut off, fall to arms; firſt defending themſelves at home, afterwards tranſmitting the war to their neighbours: with whom they diſdained to marry, calling it ſlavery, not matrimony, have dared, a ſingular example of all ages, to inlarge without the aſſiſtance of huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands, the bounds of their republick. Now incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raging themſelves in the contempt of husbands, that ſome might not ſeem more happy than others, they ſlew thoſe men that remained amongſt them, and with the daily ſlaughter of their neighbours, they proſecute the revenge of their murthered husbands, At length by war obtaining peace to preſerve the ſtate of their Government, they proſtitute their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies to men of neighbouring Countries: their male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>children they deſtroyed; but the Girls they careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly brought up, inſtructing them in the exerciſe of fencing, riding, hunting, and the like: They were called <hi>Amazons ab</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, from the burning of their breaſt, that it might not impede their ſhooting.</p>
            <p n="2">(2) <hi>Oiclides</hi> fell) <hi>Amphiaraus,</hi> called <hi>Oiclides</hi> from his Father <hi>Oicleus;</hi> a <hi>Grecian</hi> Prophet, the husband of <hi>Eriphiles,</hi> whom King <hi>Adraſtus</hi> would take with him to the war of <hi>Thebes,</hi> but hee foreſeeing hee ſhould never return, concealing himſelf, was at laſt diſcovered by his wife <hi>Eriphiles</hi> to <hi>Adraſtus</hi> for a chain of gold: with whom going to <hi>Thebes,</hi> an Eagle at feaſt ſtooping, ſnatcht <hi>Amphiaraus</hi> dart, and ſoaring up with it, let it fall; which fixing in
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:60466:57"/>the ground, became a Lawrel: <hi>Amphiaraus</hi> going to cut it down, was by a ſudden rupture of the earth ſwallowed up together with his Chariot and horſes; which <hi>Themis</hi> foretold in <hi>Metam.</hi> 9.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Subducta<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſuos manes tellure videbit</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vivus adhuc vates</hi>—</l>
               <l>A living Prophet ſhall his own Ghoſt ſee</l>
               <l>Swallowed ith'earth—</l>
            </q>
            <p n="3">(3) Wife they ſay) <hi>Laodamia,</hi> who died imbracing the ſhadow of her ſlain husband. <hi>vide ſupra.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">(4) <hi>Iphias</hi> cries) called alſo <hi>Evadne,</hi> the wife of <hi>Capaneus,</hi> whom ſhe loved ſo intirely, that when he was ſlain by a Thunderbolt at <hi>Thebes,</hi> and his Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral ſolemnized, ſhee caſt her ſelf into the fire to be conſumed with him.</p>
            <p n="5">(5) <hi>Rogus</hi> dies) It was antiently a cuſtome not to bury the dead bodies in the ground, but to burn them with fire, to prevent the Tyrannous abuſe of their enemies, who were wont to take up, after their conqueſts, the dead corps, and execute their malice upon them. This fire being made in a dead pile, was called <hi>Pyra,</hi> when burning, it was called <hi>Rogus.</hi> When the dead body was laid upon the <hi>Pyra,</hi> his eyes were again opened, to ſhew him Heaven if it were poſſible, and a half-penny put in his mouth, which they ſuppoſed to be the wages of <hi>Charon,</hi> for ferrying him over the <hi>Stygian</hi> Lake.</p>
            <p n="6">(6) <hi>Theſeus Ariadne) Vide ſupra, in Not. ad lib.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p n="7">(7) <hi>Phyl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is</hi> went) the Daughter to <hi>Licurgus</hi> King of <hi>Thrace,</hi> who proſtituted her body to <hi>Demophoon,</hi> upon promiſe of marriage, after the compoſing of thoſe differences that his abſence had incurred at
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:60466:58"/>home: but hee by the weight of his Country af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, being detained after the limit of his promiſed time, gave her leiſure to ſuſpect her ſelf deſpiſed, and deſpairing of the performance of his promiſe, hanging her ſelf, was turned into an Almond-tree without leaves, after which <hi>Demophoon</hi> returning and imbracing the naked trunk, it preſently budded and put forth.</p>
            <p n="8">(8) Gueſt did) <hi>Aeneas,</hi> who (ſaith <hi>Virg. lib.</hi> 4.) by the commands of the gods leaving <hi>Carthage; Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do,</hi> who was paſſionately in love with him, after his departure, ſlew her ſelf with the <hi>Trojans</hi> ſword which hee had forgot behinde him; yet in truth <hi>Dido</hi> lived (according to the beſt Chronologers) eighty odd years after the <hi>Trojan,</hi> though the Poet in his Romantick Poem take the liberty to make them contemporaries.</p>
            <p n="9">(9) <hi>Therapnean</hi> Bride) <hi>Laeda</hi> the wife of <hi>Tyndarus,</hi> who at <hi>Therapnae,</hi> a Village of <hi>Laconia,</hi> brought forth the <hi>Tyndarides.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">(10) <hi>Endimion</hi> doth not) a Shepherd whom <hi>Jove</hi> received into Heaven, but ambitioning the love of <hi>Juno,</hi> was firſt deceived with a cloud, and after for his pride ejected the caeleſtial habitations, and doom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to perpetual ſleep, whom <hi>Luna</hi> falling in love with, concealed in a Grott on <hi>Latmus</hi> a Mountain of <hi>Caria.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="11">(11) <hi>Cephalus</hi>) a young man, the husband of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cris,</hi> with whom <hi>Aurora</hi> falling in love, when ſhee could by no means make him decline his chaſtity, raviſhed him by force.</p>
            <p n="12">(12) <hi>Capitol</hi>) a famous Tower in <hi>Rome,</hi> built by <hi>Tarquinius Superbus,</hi> on the <hi>Tarpeian</hi> Mount, after called <hi>Mons Saturnius,</hi> or <hi>Saturns</hi> Mount, where
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:60466:58"/>the glorious ſpoils of the <hi>Roman</hi> Conquerers were hung up. It was called the <hi>Capitol,</hi> becauſe when the foundation was laid, a mans head was digged up freſh and lively, as if it had been newly buried, it being ſuppoſed the head of one <hi>Tolus</hi> long before deceaſed, whence from <hi>Caput</hi> and <hi>Tolus</hi> it was called <hi>Capitolium.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="13">(13) <hi>Curia</hi> worthy) There were in <hi>Rome</hi> ſeveral <hi>Curia's,</hi> of which chiefly one built by <hi>Tullus Hoſtili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> thence called <hi>Curia Hoſtilia,</hi> which was the chief Councel-houſe, whither the <hi>Roman</hi> Senators aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled themſelves for the determining of ſtate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matters.</p>
            <p n="14">(14) Forſaken <hi>Gnoſſis</hi>) <hi>Ariadne,</hi> whom <hi>Theſeus</hi> forſaking, <hi>Bacchus</hi> found and took to wife, beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on her the <hi>Cnoſſian</hi> Crown, beautified with ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſtars, which hee before received of <hi>Venus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="15">(15) <hi>Phryxus</hi> colour) <hi>Phryxus</hi> the Son of <hi>Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas,</hi> King of <hi>Thebes,</hi> who with his Siſter <hi>Helle,</hi> to eſcape the cruelty of their Stepmother <hi>Ino,</hi> mounted on the back of a golden Ramm, croſſing over the <hi>Pontick</hi> Streights, <hi>Helle</hi> fell off and was drowned in the Sea, which from her name was called <hi>Helle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpont.</hi> But <hi>Phryxus</hi> arriving in ſafety at <hi>Colchos,</hi> ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificed his Ramm to <hi>Jupiter,</hi> hanging up his golden fleece in the Temple, whence it was afterwards ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by <hi>Jaſon,</hi> and the reſt of the <hi>Argonantes.</hi> The Ramm in his priſtine form was placed among the Stars, and is known by the Vernal Equinoxial Sign <hi>Aries.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Impoſitam<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſibi qui non bene pertulit Hellen</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tempora nocturnis aequa durna facit.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Hee that in ſafety did not <hi>Helle</hi> bear,</l>
               <l>Gives day and night of length an equal ſhare.</l>
            </q>
            <p n="16">
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:60466:59"/> (16) Th' light bringing horſes) the four horſes of the Sun brought out by <hi>Aurora,</hi> the goddeſs of the morning, their names are <hi>Pyrois, Eous, Aethon</hi> and <hi>Phlegon,</hi> according to <hi>Metam. lib.</hi> 2.</p>
            <q>
               <l>—<hi>Volucres Pyroeis, Eous &amp; Aethon</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Solis Equi, quart uſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Phlegon.</hi>—</l>
            </q>
            <p n="17">(17) Shee whom a feigned) <hi>Europa</hi> whom <hi>Jove</hi> carried in the ſhape of a Bull.</p>
            <p n="18">(18) As when at the Mill) I may well expect ſome Ladies frowns at the tranſlation of this rude <hi>Simile,</hi> but I hope they will vaniſh into ſmiles, when they ſhall know I acknowledge it to be ſo.</p>
            <p n="19">(19) Friends ears) <hi>Ulyſſes</hi> premoniſht by <hi>Circe</hi> of the inchanting melody of the <hi>Syrens;</hi> with ſoft wax cloſed up the ears of all his companions, and canſed himſelf to be faſt bound to the Maſt, that hee might hear them, but though never ſo much attracted, not be able to get looſe, by which means hee eſcaped their allurements, though at the air of their bewitch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing voices bee called upon his friends to unbinde him, indeavouring to unlooſe himſelf. <hi>Hom. Odyſſ. lib.</hi> 12.</p>
            <p n="20">(20) Learn to ſing) muſick) dancing) here gentle Reader, give mee leave out of <hi>Lucian. de ſaltatione</hi> to anſwer thoſe cenſorious and <hi>Eſchilean</hi> pated (for I cannot term them hairbrain'd) men, that go about to vilifie thoſe princely recreations, <hi>Scio vos illecebris hiſce, &amp;c.</hi> I know if you did but hear them play, you would bee ſo raviſhed with the ſenſe of them, that you would (let mee add, if your corporeal de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapidations have not rendred you incapable of ſuch exerciſes) dance for company your ſelves. Yea
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:60466:59"/>
               <hi>Scaliger</hi> himſelf ſo famed by all the <hi>Criticks,</hi> ſaith, <hi>in muſicis ſupra omnem fidem capior &amp; oblector, &amp;c.</hi> I am extraordinarily taken and delighted with mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick; I am hugely detained with the grace and beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of women; I do gladly behold them dance, and am pleaſed to be idle amongſt them. And <hi>Epicurus</hi> uſed theſe as means to recover his ſick patients; hee laid them on a down-bed, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rowned with a Garland of ſweet ſmelling flowers, in a perfumed cloſet, deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cately ſet out, and after a potion or two of cordial drink, hee brought in a beautiful young Maid to play on a Lute, ſing and dance.</p>
            <p n="21">(21) <hi>Orpheus</hi>) an excellent Poet and Muſician of <hi>Thrace,</hi> who made the barbarous people, yea the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry trees and ſtones to dance after his Harp. <hi>Met. lib.</hi> 11.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Carmina dum tali Sylvas animoſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ferarum,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Threicius vates &amp; ſaxa ſequentia traxit.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>Having loſt his wife <hi>Euridice,</hi> hee deſcended to Hell to ſeek her, where with his Harp hee ſo charm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Cerberus, Pluto,</hi> and <hi>Proſerpine,</hi> that hee had his wife reſtored to him, but looking back before hee was got out (the thing only excepted in the reſtaura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) ſhee was again taken away. <hi>martial. lib.</hi> 14. <hi>Epig.</hi> 165.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Reddidit Euridicen vati, ſed perdidit ipſe</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>dum ſibi non credit, nec patienter amat.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The Poet got <hi>Euridice,</hi> but ſhee</l>
               <l>Was with diſtruſt loſt, and impatiency.</l>
            </q>
            <p n="22">(22) Balls muſt) <hi>Ludum parvae pilae</hi> is commended
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:60466:60"/>by <hi>Gallen,</hi> whether with the hand or racket; it was of great requeſt amongſt the antient <hi>Greeks,</hi> mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>Homer,</hi> and was firſt invented by <hi>Aganella,</hi> a Maid of <hi>Corcyra,</hi> who preſented the firſt Ball ever made to <hi>Alcinous</hi> his Daughter, and taught her the uſe of it.</p>
            <p n="23">(23) <hi>Arena</hi> ſprinkled) the <hi>Amphitheater,</hi> a ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>place in <hi>Rome,</hi> where the <hi>Gladiatours</hi> were wont to fight, all ſorts of wilde beaſts were brought to tear one another in peeces. <hi>Aulus Gellius</hi> in his fifth book <hi>de Atticis Noct.</hi> affirms that a certain ſlave being brought hither to be an Actor in theſe beaſtly Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedies, a Lion of immenſe greatneſs came from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the reſt, and fawned upon him, not ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any other of the wilde beaſts to injure or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt him; at which the Citizens wondring, inquired the cauſe, to whom the wretch told, that flying from his Maſter into a certain deſert, hee concealed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in a great cave, where hee had not long abode before a mighty Lion came halting in, with a legg bloody, and deeply wounded; the Lion inſtead of devouring (which hee only expected) came for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, looking pitifully, as though hee would com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain to him of his pain, at which, taking courage, hee applied ſome herbs to the ſore, binding it up as well as hee could, which hee had no ſooner done, but the Lion made out for his prey, and brought in certain peeces of raw fleſh, which hee made his dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly food of. At length, wearied with this ſavage life, left the deſert, and betaking him to his travels, was caught by his old Maſter, and brought from <hi>Aegypt</hi> hither to be a Gladiator; ſince whoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture it ſeemed the Lion was alſo taken and brought to <hi>Rome.</hi> At which the people gave him
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:60466:60"/>the Lion to lead through the ſtreets, as a Miracle. <hi>de Arena, vide ſupra.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="24">(24) <hi>Veſtas</hi> fire) the Nunnery of <hi>Veſta</hi> ſtood neer to <hi>Caſtors</hi> Temple, to which belonged ſix Virgins or Votaries, whoſe office was chiefly to keep the ſacred fire, for the extinction of which, they were had into a dark corner, ſtript naked, and ſcourged by the chief <hi>Pontifex.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="25">(25) <hi>Vittae</hi> do not) a filler with which the Veſtals bound their hair. <hi>Vide ſupra.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>(26) Sharp pointed Arrows) If any ſhall wonder at this adjective to Arrows, concluding them all to be ſharp pointed, I ſhall ſatisfie him out of <hi>Metam. lib.</hi> 1. that <hi>Cupid</hi> had of two ſorts.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Deque Sagittifera prompſit duo tela Pharetra,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Diverforum operum: fugat hoc, facit illud amorem.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quod facit auratum eſt, &amp; cuſpide fulget acuta:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quod f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gat obtuſum eſt, &amp; habet ſub arundine plum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bum.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Engliſhed by the admired Sir <hi>George Sandis.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Two different Arrows from his quiver draws,</l>
               <l>One hate of love, the other love doth cauſe:</l>
               <l>What cauſ'd was ſharp, and had a golden head,</l>
               <l>But what repulſt was blunt, and tipt with Lead.</l>
            </lg>
            <p n="27">(27) Barriers left) the <hi>Romans</hi> had at the end of their <hi>Circus,</hi> certain Barriers called Carceres, that is places railed in, from which the horſes began their Races.</p>
            <p n="28">(28) Waters at fit time) waters to write with, as the water of <hi>Chalchantum, Alum,</hi> or <hi>Sal Armonia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum,</hi> with the two firſt, what ever you ſhall write on Paper cannot be read, till held in water, the laſt, betwixt you and the fire.</p>
            <p n="29">
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:60466:61"/> (29) Milk you write) the Milk of a Figg-tree, with which you may write upon any part of your body, being dry, it will not be read till rubbed over with a Charcoal.</p>
            <p n="30">(30) <hi>Pharian Iſis) Aegyptian Iſis,</hi> to whom there was conſecrate a Temple in <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="31">(31) <hi>Hymettus</hi>) a Mountain of <hi>Athens</hi> abounding with Bees, and plenty of honey.</p>
            <p n="32">(32) <hi>Thebais</hi> being tall) <hi>Audromache,</hi> the wife of <hi>Hector,</hi> and daughter to <hi>Aetion</hi> King of <hi>Thebes,</hi> whence ſhee is called <hi>Thebais. Dares Phrygins</hi> gives us this character of her, <hi>Andromacham oculis claris, candidam, longam, &amp;c. Andromache</hi> was fair eyed, courteous, tall, lovely, modeſt, affable and diſcreet; which vertues may be truly aſſerted inherent to the <hi>Major</hi> part of her glorious ſex, which gives mee oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to conclude with that of my Author. <hi>lib.</hi> 3.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ipſa quo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> &amp; cultu eſt &amp; nomine faemina virtus:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nec mirum populo ſi placet ipſa ſuo.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Ladies are really all vertue, then</l>
               <l>No wonder if ſo much they pleaſe us men.</l>
            </q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:60466:61" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
